<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The brides ornaments viz. fiue meditations, morall and diuine. 1. Knowledge, 2. zeale, 3. temperance, 4. bountie, 5. ioy.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Aylett, Robert, 1583-1655?</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A00002</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 1000.5</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S115415</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99850634</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99850634</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">15849</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00002)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15849)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 910:09)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The brides ornaments viz. fiue meditations, morall and diuine. 1. Knowledge, 2. zeale, 3. temperance, 4. bountie, 5. ioy.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Aylett, Robert, 1583-1655?</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 123, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by William Stansby,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1625.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Contains the 3rd and 4th books of "The brides ornaments", "Urania", and "The converts conquest" each with separately dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</NOTE><NOTE>In verse.</NOTE><NOTE>Formerly STC 1004a.</NOTE><NOTE>Identified as STC 1004a on UMI microfilm reel 910.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A00002">
<STC T="S">1000.5</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99850634</BIBNO>
<VID>15849</VID>
</IDG>
<GROUP>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE BRIDES ORNAMENTS, <HI>Viz.</HI> Fiue MEDITATIONS, Morall and Diuine.</P>
<P>1. Knowledge, 2. Zeale, 3. Temperance, 4. Bountie, 5. Ioy.</P>
<Q><BIBL>IOHN 17. 3.</BIBL>
<HI>This is life eternall, that they may know thee the onely true God, and Iesus Christ whom thou hast sent.</HI></Q>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM STANSBY. 1625.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="table of contents">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE CONTENTS of the whole Booke.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The third Booke.</HEAD>
<ITEM>1. Knowledge.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Zeale.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Temperance.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. Bountie.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5. Ioy.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The fourth Booke.</HEAD>
<ITEM>1. Prudence.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Obedience.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Meeknesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. Gods Word.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5. Prayer.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. VRania.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. The Authors vow or wish, atthe Con∣secration of the Right Honourable the Lord <HI>Maynards</HI> Chappell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. The Muses health to the same.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. The Conuerts Conquest.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRA∣BLE AND REVEREND FA∣THER IN GOD, GEORGE, LORD Bishop of <HI>London,</HI> Lord high ALMENER to the Kings most Excellent MAIESTIE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>O <HI>me</HI> thy <HI>Fauour,</HI> to <HI>thee</HI> my Relation</L>
<L>Doe tie <HI>mee</HI> in a double Obligation:</L>
<L>These <HI>Graces fiue</HI> to <HI>thee</HI> to dedicate,</L>
<L>Which best I think thy worth accommodate;</L>
<L>Who art the bounteous <HI>Almener</HI> of the King</L>
<L>Of <HI>Bounty;</HI> whose great wisdome did <HI>thee</HI> bring</L>
<L>For thy <HI>large spirit,</HI> and well tempred <HI>zeale</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>Temples</HI> broken <HI>head</HI> and <HI>sides</HI> to heale:</L>
<L>Whose loue to <HI>Knowledge</HI> Humane &amp; Diuine,</L>
<L>As in the <HI>Schooles,</HI> so in the <HI>Church</HI> doth shine.</L>
<L>These outward <HI>Vertues:</HI> plainly doe declare,</L>
<L>What inward <HI>Graces</HI> in <HI>thee</HI> likewise are:</L>
<L>The chiefe is <HI>spirituall Ioy;</HI> which in thy Breast,</L>
<L>God make <HI>thee</HI> feele, as wee doe see the rest.</L>
</LG>
<P><HI>Your Lordships bounden in all dutie and seruice,</HI></P>
<P>ROBERT AYLETT.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To Reuerend Diuines.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Ost honor'd &amp; belou'd! Enquire you why</HI></L>
<L><HI>A</HI> Lawyer <HI>meddles with</HI> Diuinitie?</L>
<L><HI>I diue no</HI> seas profound <HI>of disputation,</HI></L>
<L><HI>But wade in</HI> shallow Fords <HI>of</HI> meditation:</L>
<L><HI>I write no</HI> Systema, <HI>no</HI> Institution</L>
<L><HI>No</HI> Babels Fall, <HI>nor</HI> Sions Restitution:</L>
<L><HI>Nor whither</HI> Tithes <HI>by</HI> Law diuine <HI>are due,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Or doe to</HI> you <HI>by</HI> Positiue <HI>accrew:</HI></L>
<L><HI>These</HI> mysteries <HI>I leaue to</HI> sound Diuines,</L>
<L><HI>That searched haue profundest</HI> Scripture-mines.</L>
<L>Seditious superstitious Nouelties</L>
<L><HI>I hate; my mind I onely exercise</HI></L>
<L><HI>In your</HI> pure, easie, sweet, diuinest notions,</L>
<L><HI>And them, at</HI> leasure, <HI>suit to my</HI> deuotions.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<HEAD>To Iohn a Nokes.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THou lik'st my Verses well, but not to flatter,</L>
<L>Dislik'st <HI>Diuinitie</HI> should be my <HI>matter.</HI></L>
<L>What now? will <HI>Lawiers</HI> turne <HI>Diuines?</HI> thats braue.</L>
<L>No: By no meanes! They haue no soules to saue.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE BRIDES ORNAMENTS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. I. <HI>Of Heauenly</HI> KNOWLEDGE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG> Daily <HI>warfare</HI> is a <HI>Christians life,</HI></L>
<L>Where <HI>Souldiers</HI> all, not onely stand in need</L>
<L>Of <HI>Armes</HI> and <HI>Valour</HI> (to maintaine the strife</L>
<L>The cursed <HI>Serpent</HI> makes with <HI>Adams</HI> seed)</L>
<L>But of this <HI>Treasure, Knowledge,</HI> both to feed</L>
<L>Their <HI>Soules</HI> with <HI>food</HI> most pure Celestiall,</L>
<L>And furnish with such <HI>Weapons</HI> as they need;</L>
<L>I therefore her <HI>Loues Treasurer</HI> doe call,</L>
<L>For we in daily want stand of her <HI>Treasure</HI> all.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>By feigned <HI>Treasure;</HI> did the <HI>Serpent</HI> traine</L>
<L>Our two first Parents to their cursed sinne;</L>
<L>Pretending they should goodly <HI>treasure</HI> gaine,</L>
<L>And <HI>Knowledge,</HI> both of <HI>good</HI> and <HI>euill,</HI> win:</L>
<L>But <HI>good</HI> doth end, where <HI>euill</HI> doth begin;</L>
<L>For drosse they doe exchange their purest gold.</L>
<L>The <HI>Serpent</HI> bad without, themselues within</L>
<L>They find the euill, as the <HI>Serpent</HI> told:</L>
<L>But vp to Heav'n flies <HI>good,</HI> which can no <HI>ill</HI> behold.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus all our <HI>Treasures</HI> lost we had before,</L>
<L>The <HI>Knowledge</HI> of <HI>Gods nature</HI> and his <HI>will,</HI></L>
<L>And we become vnarm'd, rude, naked, poore;</L>
<L>Of all things ignorant, but doing ill:</L>
<L>Now vs our enemies may easily kill,</L>
<L>We hauing lost our <HI>weapons</HI> and our <HI>treasure:</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>wealth</HI> and <HI>weapons</HI> if regaine we will,</L>
<L>We must attend this heau'nly <HI>Ladys</HI> pleasure;</L>
<L>Diuine sweet <HI>Knowledge</HI> not confin'd by weight or measure.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="2" REF="4"/>
Thou <HI>Word incarnate!</HI> whom aright to know</L>
<L>Is Life eternall, Ioy and happy rest,</L>
<L>To mee this <HI>Ladies</HI> wondrous Beautie show,</L>
<L>And richest <HI>treasures,</HI> which in <HI>golden Chest.</HI></L>
<L>Thou hid'st from <HI>Hell</HI> and malice of the <HI>Beast;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Knowledge,</HI> contain'd in either Testament:</L>
<L>Wherein thy Will and Nature is exprest</L>
<L>How we should liue and <HI>Serpents</HI> sting preuent,</L>
<L>How conquer <HI>Hell,</HI> and <HI>serue thee</HI> with a true intent.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Some <HI>Knowledge</HI> call, <HI>th'habit of demonstration,</HI></L>
<L>Some her to <HI>know</HI> by <HI>causes</HI> doe define;</L>
<L>Some <HI>th'vnderstandings sound determination,</HI></L>
<L>Wee her to <HI>heau'nly Doctrine</HI> here confine:</L>
<L>Which in a <HI>threefold Booke to man</HI> doth shine,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Creatures, first, and latter Testament,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Booke of Creatures</HI> shewes <HI>Gods</HI> power diuine,</L>
<L>The <HI>Law</HI> is much in <HI>types</HI> and <HI>shadowes</HI> spent,</L>
<L>Whereof the <HI>Gospel</HI> is the full accomplishment.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In <HI>Booke of creatures,</HI> all men may obserue</L>
<L><HI>Gods Wisdome, Goodnesse; Power, and Prouidence,</HI></L>
<L>By which he made the world and doth preserue</L>
<L>In truest motions, its circumference:</L>
<L>Sending from Heav'n raines sweetest influence;</L>
<L>Filling our hearts with Mirth and Ioyfulnesse;</L>
<L>And giuing all things, <HI>Motion, Being, Sense:</HI></L>
<L>This doth <HI>Gods power</HI> and <HI>God-head</HI> plaine expresse;</L>
<L>But not his <HI>Will,</HI> which leads to endlesse happinesse.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet by this Booke are left without excuse</L>
<L>Idolaters, who downe to <HI>stocks</HI> doe fall;</L>
<L>Which their owne hands haue made for such abuse,</L>
<L>And leaue their <HI>Maker,</HI> blessed ouer all;</L>
<L>Who as his <HI>Power and Goodnesse generall</HI></L>
<L>Appeares most plainly in this Worlds Creation;</L>
<L>So doth his gracious <HI>Bountie</HI> on them fall,</L>
<L>In sending food for daily sustentation,</L>
<L>And in their healths and liues continuall preseruation;</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="3" REF="4"/>
The next two <HI>Bookes,</HI> most plainly doe disclose</L>
<L><HI>Gods will particular, and generall,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Particular</HI> to <HI>Patriarchs, Prophets,</HI> those</L>
<L>That till <HI>Christs</HI> time, on <HI>God</HI> aright did call:</L>
<L>For this did not on all the Nations fall,</L>
<L><HI>Gods</HI> will was then in <HI>Iury</HI> onely knowne:</L>
<L>But now the <HI>Gospel</HI> soundeth out to all,</L>
<L>The seed thereof in eu'ry Nation's sowne,</L>
<L>Which doth reueale hid mysteries before vnknowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>The first, Gods</HI> power and prouidence doth shew;</L>
<L><HI>The second,</HI> types out our Regeneration;</L>
<L><HI>The third,</HI> directly leadeth vs to know</L>
<L>All that is needfull, for our owne Saluation;</L>
<L>Ev'n from Election to Glorification:</L>
<L>This Booke reueales all secret mysteries,</L>
<L>Hidden in <HI>Christ,</HI> before the Worlds foundation;</L>
<L>Though worldlings this, as folly doe despise,</L>
<L>Yet this true <HI>Knowledge</HI> onely happy, makes and wise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As some great <HI>Princes</HI> might and Maiestie,</L>
<L>Is often to the meanest stranger knowne;</L>
<L>But his most <HI>secret counsell</HI> and <HI>decree,</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>friends</HI> and <HI>counsellours</HI> is onely showne.</L>
<L><HI>Ev'n</HI> so <HI>the King of Kings</HI> holds not vnknowne</L>
<L>From <HI>Heathens</HI> sight, his <HI>Maiestie</HI> and <HI>might:</HI></L>
<L>But hath disclosed onely to his owne,</L>
<L>The <HI>secret</HI> of his <HI>counsells,</HI> and <HI>delight;</HI></L>
<L>Whereby they may him worship, please, and serue aright.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is the <HI>Knowledge</HI> which I seeke to trace,</L>
<L>This onely doth true happinesse affoord,</L>
<L>Whereof the onely cause is inward <HI>Grace,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>vnderstanding Gods</HI> most holy Word:</L>
<L>The helpes which <HI>humane Learning</HI> doe record;</L>
<L><HI>Law, History, Arts, Physicke, Poetrie;</HI></L>
<L>Are but as <HI>seruants</HI> waiting on their <HI>Lord,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>hand-maids</HI> to their <HI>dame Diuinitie;</HI></L>
<L>All <HI>Knowledge</HI> without this is foolish vanitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="4" REF="5"/>
Sweet <HI>Grace,</HI> which dost true <HI>Knowledge</HI> of <HI>Gods</HI> will,</L>
<L>To <HI>Babes and sucklings</HI> oftentimes reueale,</L>
<L>When from great <HI>Clerkes</HI> of Wisdome and <HI>deepe</HI> skill,</L>
<L>Thy pleasure is this <HI>treasure</HI> to conceale;</L>
<L>Oh <HI>sacred breath!</HI> which in our hearts doth steale,</L>
<L>Like sweetest <HI>Zephyrus</HI> most pleasing wind,</L>
<L>Whence no man knowes, yet doth it surely seale,</L>
<L>That certaine <HI>Knowledge</HI> which I seeke to find,</L>
<L><HI>Knowledge of God and Christ the Sauiour</HI> of mankind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>All <HI>Graces</HI> that doe serue <HI>Loues Royall Queene</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>heauenly Knowledge</HI> haue their maintenance,</L>
<L>And alwayes in her company are seene,</L>
<L>None without <HI>Knowledge</HI> may neere <HI>Loue</HI> aduance;</L>
<L>With her are <HI>Diligence,</HI> and <HI>Temperance:</HI></L>
<L><HI>True Faith</HI> so neere her euer doth attend,</L>
<L>You would her take for <HI>Knowledge</HI> at a glance,</L>
<L>Though often <HI>Faith</HI> doth so her selfe transcend,</L>
<L>That shee beyond the reach of <HI>Knowledge</HI> doth ascend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Not <HI>Faith</HI> alone, but <HI>Workes</HI> accompany</L>
<L>True <HI>Knowledge,</HI> who in words doth make profession</L>
<L>He knowes <HI>God,</HI> but in <HI>Workes</HI> doth him deny,</L>
<L>Is ev'n a lyar by his owne confession;</L>
<L>How many from this rule doe make digression?</L>
<L>That would in <HI>Knowledge</HI> be accounted high,</L>
<L>But giue themselues to Pride, Lust, and Oppression;</L>
<L>Enuy, dissembling, Schisme, Idolatry</L>
<L>Alas true <HI>Knowledge</HI> neuer kept such company.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Some onely seeke to <HI>know,</HI> that they may <HI>know;</HI></L>
<L>And this is <HI>foolish curiositie,</HI></L>
<L>And some of Learning make a goodly show,</L>
<L>And this is <HI>base and idle vanitie:</HI></L>
<L>Some <HI>Knowledge</HI> seeke for their <HI>vtilitie,</HI></L>
<L>Or their preferment, which is <HI>filthy gaine,</HI></L>
<L>Some to teach other, which is <HI>Charitie,</HI></L>
<L>Some by this <HI>Knowledge</HI> seeke Heav'n to attaine,</L>
<L>To know and walke not right is damnable and vaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="5" REF="5"/>
I liken this true <HI>Knowledge</HI> to the flower,</L>
<L>Or blossome springing from the root of <HI>Grace,</HI></L>
<L>That doth most gloriously adorne <HI>Loues bower,</HI></L>
<L>And fills with pleasant odours all the place:</L>
<L>Which blossome beautifull, in little space,</L>
<L>It selfe into most goodly fruits doth spend,</L>
<L><HI>Faith, Mercy, Peace</HI> each good and perfect <HI>grace,</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>fruit</HI> so farre the <HI>flower</HI> doth transcend,</L>
<L><HI>God, Men,</HI> and <HI>Angels</HI> tast it, and the same commend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As Blossomes doe not from <HI>root</HI> liuely spring,</L>
<L>That after blowing, haue a fruitlesse fall;</L>
<L>So <HI>Knowledge</HI> that in <HI>Workes</HI> is vanishing,</L>
<L>Had neuer any <HI>root</HI> from <HI>grace</HI> at all.</L>
<L>But is like to <HI>good seed,</HI> that's said to fall</L>
<L>From sowers hand, downe by the high-way side,</L>
<L>Whose rooting being shallow, loose, and small,</L>
<L>Could not the <HI>Suns</HI> hot scorching heat abide;</L>
<L>But in the blade, with some, small light affliction dide.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Some liken heau'nly <HI>Knowledge</HI> to the <HI>Sunne,</HI></L>
<L>Then which in this world nothing more to sight</L>
<L>Obiected is: But we by <HI>Sinne</HI> become,</L>
<L>Like him borne blind, depriu'd of naturall light.</L>
<L>Till some <HI>Power</HI> supernaturall enlight,</L>
<L>And though more plaine in this world nothing's showne,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Gods</HI> eternall <HI>God-head, goodnesse, might;</HI></L>
<L>Yet vntill <HI>Grace</HI> enlighten 'tis vnknowne,</L>
<L>No cause hereof in God, but in our selues is knowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Knowledge</HI> is like the talents which the <HI>Lord,</HI></L>
<L>When he went forth did to his seruants lend:</L>
<L>The first who his one talent vp did hoard,</L>
<L>Like him, that for his <HI>Knowledge</HI> doth contend;</L>
<L>But therewith not himselfe, nor others mend:</L>
<L>Hee that with talents two, gain'd other twaine;</L>
<L>Is he that doth his time and labour spend</L>
<L>To saue himselfe, and those with him remaine,</L>
<L>But he that gaind the fiue; seeks all mens soules to gaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="6" REF="6"/>
I <HI>Knowledge</HI> to the <HI>Virgins Lamps</HI> compare,</L>
<L>Which foolish <HI>maids</HI> had <HI>common</HI> with the Wise,</L>
<L>Oile workes of Pietie and Mercy are;</L>
<L>Which foolish Virgins idlely doe misprise,</L>
<L>But when one, <HI>Loe the Bridegrome comes,</HI> out cryes,</L>
<L>The foolish Virgins <HI>Lamps</HI> are spent and done,</L>
<L>Wherefore they must to merits merchandize,</L>
<L>And borrow when they of their owne haue none,</L>
<L>The Churches <HI>Treasury</HI> will furnish ev'ry one.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Like Widowes Oile, that doth encrease by spending,</L>
<L>Like flames, that lightning others, gaine more light.</L>
<L>Like Vsurers coine, that doth augment by lending;</L>
<L>Like Ioy, that most encreaseth by delight.</L>
<L>Like <HI>Manna</HI> that the Angels food is hight,</L>
<L>Whereof each gathers what may him suffice:</L>
<L>Except such as in Flesh-pots more delight,</L>
<L>Like Springs which more you draw, the faster rise,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Tutors,</HI> who by teaching Schollers, grow more wise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>No <HI>Simile</HI> can her so well expresse,</L>
<L>As infinite and boundlesse treasury;</L>
<L>Or Sea of waters which become no lesse:</L>
<L>Though Fountaines all with streames it doth supply.</L>
<L>How infinite is this grand mystery,</L>
<L>To lay of nothing this huge Worlds foundation:</L>
<L>One God, three persons in the <HI>Trinitie,</HI></L>
<L>Oh depth of <HI>Knowledge! Gods</HI> owne <HI>Incarnation,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Obedience, Passion, Resurrection, Exaltation.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh! I am drown'd, here <HI>Elephants</HI> may swim,</L>
<L>My <HI>Lambe-like Muse</HI> in <HI>shallow Fords</HI> must wade,</L>
<L>And seeke for <HI>Knowledge</HI> to desist from <HI>Sinne,</HI></L>
<L>And make <HI>Faith, Mercy, Pietie</HI> my trade.</L>
<L>By <HI>Faith,</HI> I know, Christs merits mine are made;</L>
<L>The rest are-fruits of my Sanctification,</L>
<L>Abundant <HI>Knowledge</HI> doth with sorrow lade,</L>
<L>To <HI>Know</HI> and doe <HI>God's</HI> willis delectation,</L>
<L>And onely by <HI>Christs</HI> merits bringeth to Saluation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="7" REF="6"/>
This is the <HI>Knowledge</HI> which our <HI>Sauiour</HI> meant,</L>
<L>When as he it <HI>eternall life</HI> did call;</L>
<L>To <HI>know God, and the Christ</HI> which he had sent:</L>
<L>This is the <HI>Knowledge</HI> so much sought of all,</L>
<L>Before and since the <HI>Law,</HI> and euer shall,</L>
<L>Though till <HI>Christs</HI> time, it was so shadowed;</L>
<L>As couer'd it in types and signes seem'd small,</L>
<L>But since <HI>Times fulnesse</HI> is accomplished,</L>
<L>Behold, they all in <HI>Christ</HI> are easie to be read.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>By this did <HI>Abel</HI> offer of his Sheepe,</L>
<L>The fat, and <HI>God</HI> accepted his oblation:</L>
<L>By this so well <HI>Gods Law</HI> did <HI>Henoch</HI> keepe,</L>
<L>Hee him exalted from earths habitation;</L>
<L>For this did <HI>Abram</HI> Ieaue both house and Nation,</L>
<L>Assured, that from out his Loines should spring</L>
<L>That <HI>Knowledge,</HI> which to <HI>know</HI> was his saluation</L>
<L>Herein did <HI>Dauid,</HI> though he were a <HI>King,</HI></L>
<L>Take more delight than <HI>Crowne,</HI> or any worldly thing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>See <HI>next</HI> his royall sonne, <HI>King Salomon,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Then whom</HI> arise a <HI>Wiser</HI> neuer shall,</L>
<L>Who knew plants natures, eu'n from <HI>Lebanon</HI></L>
<L><HI>Her Caedars tall</HI> to <HI>Hysope</HI> by the <HI>wall:</HI></L>
<L>Who as in <HI>Wealth</HI> in <HI>Knowledge</HI> passed all;</L>
<L>Yet after hee had traced <HI>Uanitie,</HI></L>
<L>And found how sonnes of men thereby did fall.</L>
<L>Him to this <HI>Knowledge</HI> did againe apply:</L>
<L>And swanlike sang <HI>Christs Churches Epithalamy.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Wake I, or sleepe, or am I in a trance?</L>
<L>Or doe another <HI>Salomon</HI> behold?</L>
<L>A <HI>Dauid</HI> who doth far and wide aduance,</L>
<L>His gracious scepter? But no bounds can hold</L>
<L>His <HI>Knowledge,</HI> secret things for to vnfold;</L>
<L><HI>Law, History, Arts</HI> and <HI>Philosophy,</HI></L>
<L>All noble <HI>sciences</HI> that can be told,</L>
<L>Yet seemes to loue alone <HI>Diuinitie.</HI></L>
<L>Which truely can direct in <HI>Peace</HI> to liue and die.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="8" REF="7"/>
Who as hee is the <HI>Learnedest of Kings,</HI></L>
<L>So 'tis his Ioy and Glory for to be,</L>
<L>The <HI>King of learned men;</HI> which in all things,</L>
<L>Makes God to prosper him as all may see,</L>
<L>This makes him raise to place of high degree,</L>
<L>Men of great <HI>knowledge,</HI> well to rule the <HI>Land,</HI></L>
<L>And put downe <HI>Ignorance</HI> and subtiltie,</L>
<L>Which highest in their owne conceits doe stand;</L>
<L>Long sway thou <HI>Brittons</HI> Scepter with thy sacred hand.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And when thy Cloake, <HI>Elias-</HI>like, must fall</L>
<L>Vpon <HI>Elisha</HI> thine vndoubted heire,</L>
<L>Inherite hee thy <HI>Peace</HI> and <HI>Knowledge</HI> all,</L>
<L>And in thy <HI>Spirit</HI> rule as in thy chaire:</L>
<L>But I must leaue this field so ample faire,</L>
<L>Teach mee, O Lord, to <HI>know</HI> and <HI>doe</HI> thy will,</L>
<L>And let thy <HI>grace</HI> againe in me repaire</L>
<L>Thine <HI>Image</HI> lost, and all corruptions kill;</L>
<L>Thus we thy will on Earth, as they in Heav'n fulfill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This <HI>knowledge</HI> must stand by vs at our last,</L>
<L>When as wee ready are our soules to tender</L>
<L>To him, that for false <HI>knowledge</HI> curious tast,</L>
<L>Though guiltlesse did his life to Iustice render:</L>
<L>For this the <HI>Holy Ghost</HI> doth more commend her,</L>
<L>That bare her <HI>Sauiours knowledge</HI> in her brest;</L>
<L>Than that shee bare him in her wombe; yet tender,</L>
<L>For <HI>One</HI> all <HI>Generations</HI> call her blest,</L>
<L>By th'other one of his <HI>true members</HI> shee doth rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But though this onely necessary is,</L>
<L>And first for our saluation to be sought,</L>
<L>Wee onely at our last of it haue misse,</L>
<L>As too meane subiect for ambitious thought:</L>
<L>Thus the vnlearned rise, and heav'n haue cought,</L>
<L>When <HI>greatest Clerks</HI> with Sciences profound,</L>
<L>Heartlesse, and comfortlesse to Hell are brought,</L>
<L>For God doth their great wisedome oft confound,</L>
<L>Because their inward parts are not sincere and sound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="9" REF="7"/>
Alas! of <HI>knowledge</HI> here we haue no care,</L>
<L>But all our <HI>youth</HI> in follies idely spend;</L>
<L>Our strength in lusts and strifes away we weare;</L>
<L>In <HI>age</HI> we worldly profit all intend:</L>
<L>Alas what gaine we by this at our end?</L>
<L>When our fraile Body doth returne to dust,</L>
<L>Our Soule to him that gaue it must ascend,</L>
<L>Whereof least iot of time account they must,</L>
<L>Which hath been spent in discord, profit, folly, lust.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh! knew we but the vertue of this treasure?</L>
<L>Like to the Merchant wise, we would sell all</L>
<L>To buy it, where we should find profit, pleasure,</L>
<L>Such Ioy as neuer on our hearts did fall:</L>
<L>Oh heav'nly Comfort! Ioy spirituall:</L>
<L>Delight vnspeakeable in hearts that' grow,</L>
<L>Of those that shee is conuersant withall;</L>
<L>What Ioy can there be greater than to know</L>
<L><HI>Gods</HI> endlesse <HI>Loue</HI> in <HI>Christ,</HI> which shee to vs doth show.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sure I could wish my whole life here to spend,</L>
<L>In this diuine most holy contemplation,</L>
<L>whereof I know not how to make an end,</L>
<L>Shee yeelds such plentie of sweet meditation:</L>
<L>Most heav'nly mysteries of our Creation,</L>
<L>Wherein appeare <HI>Gods</HI> might and Maiestie;</L>
<L>But aboue all his loue in mans saluation</L>
<L>This is that wondrous hidden mystery,</L>
<L>Into the which eu'n <HI>Angels</HI> did desire to pry.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But we confesse though thou dost here reueale,</L>
<L>Abundant <HI>knowledge,</HI> yet we little know</L>
<L>Wherefore 'gainst vs the <HI>Heathen</HI> may appeale</L>
<L>Who though thou didst to them but glimpses show</L>
<L>Of <HI>Truth,</HI> and <HI>Iustice,</HI> did more righteous grow,</L>
<L>Than wee that doe thy <HI>sacred Truth</HI> confesse;</L>
<L>And make of <HI>Puritie</HI> a glorious show;</L>
<L>But to adorne the <HI>Gospel</HI> we professe</L>
<L>With workes of <HI>Charitie,</HI> Ah! wee doe nothing lesse.</L>
</LG>
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<LG>
<L><PB N="10" REF="9"/>
Oh it is meate and drinke, we know not of;</L>
<L>To know and doe our heav'nly Fathers will:</L>
<L>Our blessed <HI>Sauiour</HI> alwayes fed thereof,</L>
<L>And hereof <HI>Saints</HI> and <HI>Angells</HI> eate their fill.</L>
<L>These are the fruitfull plants which flourish still,</L>
<L><HI>Milke, Hony, liuing Water, spiced Wine;</HI></L>
<L>Which doe refresh <HI>Christs Spouse</HI> when shee is ill:</L>
<L>These <HI>richest Iewells,</HI> which her make so fine,</L>
<L><HI>Locks, Ribands, Roses,</HI> which so gloriously do shine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For this, shee is the <HI>Bridegroomes darling Doue,</HI></L>
<L>And vnto her that bare her, onely deare:</L>
<L>For this the daughters, when they see her loue,</L>
<L>And all the <HI>Queenes</HI> and <HI>Wiues</HI> make merry cheere:</L>
<L>This makes her looke than <HI>Sunne</HI> and <HI>Moone</HI> more cleere.</L>
<L>Her <HI>nauell, belly, head, necke, brests</HI> adorne;</L>
<L>With these shee to her <HI>husband</HI> doth appeare,</L>
<L>More <HI>beautifull,</HI> than is the fairest <HI>morne;</HI></L>
<L>Or faire like <HI>twinning Ews,</HI> on <HI>Gilead</HI> washt and shorne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thou that such heav'nly <HI>Knowledge</HI> didst instill,</L>
<L>Into plaine Fishers that they could confound</L>
<L>By argument, ev'n Clerkes of greatest skill,</L>
<L>And diue into thy <HI>Mysteries</HI> profound:</L>
<L>Who by their <HI>clouen-fiery tongues</HI> forth sound,</L>
<L>The <HI>Knowledge</HI> of thy <HI>Truth</HI> to ev'ry Nation;</L>
<L>Canst make this <HI>Knowledge</HI> in mine heart abound,</L>
<L>By one, sparke of diuine illumination,</L>
<L>And rauish my weake soule with heav'nly admiration.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And though imperfect here our <HI>Knowledge</HI> be,</L>
<L>By reason of our humane imperfection,</L>
<L>And for by <HI>Faith</HI> alone, we things doe see,</L>
<L>And nothing <HI>know</HI> indeed in true perfection;</L>
<L>Yet when thy <HI>Spirit</HI> cleares our minds infection,</L>
<L>Wee shall then <HI>know,</HI> ev'n as we now are <HI>knowne;</HI></L>
<L>And things now seene, by mirrour-like inspection;</L>
<L>To vs shall be most euidently showne,</L>
<L>In <HI>Knowledge</HI> we shall reape, what we in Faith haue sowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="11" REF="9"/>
What then's <HI>imperfect,</HI> shall be done away,</L>
<L><HI>Knowledge</HI> shall perfect our felicitie;</L>
<L>Which is our free beholding God, for ay,</L>
<L>In his great <HI>Goodnesse, Loue,</HI> and <HI>Maiestie,</HI></L>
<L>So farre as <HI>finite</HI> may <HI>infinitie,</HI></L>
<L>Farther to reach my <HI>Muse</HI> dares not be bold,</L>
<L>When <HI>Angels</HI> of so high sublimitie,</L>
<L><HI>Gods</HI> Light and Maiestie cannot behold,</L>
<L><HI>Finite</HI> with <HI>infinite</HI> can no proportion hold.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. I. <HI>Of</HI> ZEALE <HI>and godly</HI> IEALOVSIE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>OH that some holy fire enlightening,</L>
<L>My Soule now rauish would with thoughts diuine,</L>
<L>Whilst I of <HI>Iealousie, Loues</HI> daughter sing,</L>
<L>And godly <HI>Zeale,</HI> which like the <HI>Sunne</HI> doth shine,</L>
<L>Alas! <HI>Minerua,</HI> and the <HI>Muses</HI> nine,</L>
<L>Are too weake helpes their aide here to intreate,</L>
<L>With <HI>Colefrom Altar</HI> let some <HI>Seraphine</HI></L>
<L>Touch my rude tongue, and set my braine on heate,</L>
<L>The <HI>Glory</HI> of this <HI>Grace</HI> in loftie rhimes to sweate.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Fit Subiect, for a sacred <HI>Poets</HI> Verse,</L>
<L>Which should it selfe in <HI>Extasie</HI> transcend,</L>
<L><HI>Zeales</HI> sacred Praise, with <HI>Knowledge</HI> to rehearse</L>
<L>Both <HI>Method</HI> and <HI>Deuotion</HI> doe commend:</L>
<L>Who as the <HI>houshold Chaplaine</HI> doth intend,</L>
<L>To all that liue in Royall Court of <HI>Loue;</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Prayers</HI> for them all, to heau'n doth send,</L>
<L>For without <HI>Zeale</HI> none possible can moue,</L>
<L>To high <HI>Olimpus</HI> Court, the Seate of mightie <HI>Ioue.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="12" REF="10"/>
For <HI>Prayers</HI> that to Heau'n seeke to ascend,</L>
<L>Without the Feruour of this sacred <HI>Zeale,</HI></L>
<L>Fall downe like smoakie vapours, that intend</L>
<L>Into Aires middle region to steale:</L>
<L>But those that are supported by her seale</L>
<L>Like <HI>Fumes</HI> of incense by the <HI>Lamb</HI> contend</L>
<L>Eu'n in th'Almighties presence to reueale</L>
<L>Our wants, and craue his aid vs to defend:</L>
<L>'Gainst worlds and <HI>Serpents poyson</HI> to our latest end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh! <HI>thou,</HI> to whom it was both drinke and meate,</L>
<L>To finish and to doe thy Fathers Will,</L>
<L>Whom <HI>Zeale</HI> of <HI>Gods</HI> owne house eu'n vp did eate,</L>
<L>And made thee on the Crosse thy bloud to spill:</L>
<L>Who whipst out Merchants that thy house did fill,</L>
<L>With doues and money, theeues and merchandize,</L>
<L>Some <HI>Zea-lous</HI> iuice into my pen distill,</L>
<L>And raise my mind aboue her wonted guise,</L>
<L>That so my <HI>Muse</HI> may with her matter sympathise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>All other holy <HI>Graces</HI> disposition,</L>
<L>By rules of <HI>Art</HI> I formerly define;</L>
<L>But <HI>Zeale</HI> so feruent is no definition</L>
<L>Can her containe, or bound in any line;</L>
<L>Onely shee is by nature, pure, diuine,</L>
<L><HI>Beloued daughter</HI> to the <HI>Queene</HI> of <HI>Loue,</HI></L>
<L>Whose <HI>mothers Graces,</HI> so in her doe shine,</L>
<L>Shee well the <HI>primate</HI> of her <HI>Court</HI> may proue,</L>
<L>And ranked be for place, all other <HI>Peares</HI> aboue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I here omit that <HI>Zeale,</HI> which without hate</L>
<L>Of others, doth to vertuous deeds contend,</L>
<L>And vs enflames that <HI>good</HI> to emulate,</L>
<L>Which we to be in others apprehend:</L>
<L>I here that holy <HI>Iealousie</HI> commend,</L>
<L>Which onely doth from <HI>Loue</HI> diuine proceed;</L>
<L>When, not for <HI>our,</HI> but <HI>Gods</HI> cause, we intend</L>
<L>To loue both him and his in word and deed,</L>
<L>For this is that right <HI>Zea'le</HI> which of true <HI>Loue</HI> doth breed.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="13" REF="10"/>
<HI>Truth</HI> comes by <HI>knowledge,</HI> and from <HI>zeale, deuotions;</HI></L>
<L>When therefore <HI>zeale</HI> doth with true <HI>knowledge</HI> meete,</L>
<L>Shee doth inlarge our hearts with heav'nly notions,</L>
<L>Sublime, transcendant, admirable, sweet;</L>
<L>But where this <HI>knowledge</HI> wants, shee's vndiscreet,</L>
<L>Rash, violent, seditious, rude and blind,</L>
<L>Faults for so faire a <HI>Lady</HI> farre vnmeet;</L>
<L>You see two <HI>zeales</HI> here of a differing kind,</L>
<L>I leaue the worst, and seeke the fairest out to find.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sweet <HI>Lady!</HI> daughter to the <HI>Queene of Loue;</HI></L>
<L>Which is the cause of <HI>Zeale</HI> and <HI>Iealousie,</HI></L>
<L>If you will aske mee what this <HI>Queene</HI> doth moue,</L>
<L>To loue vs wretches that in sin doe lye;</L>
<L>I answere, <HI>Goodnesse</HI> of her <HI>Maiestie.</HI></L>
<L>Most excellent is then this holy fire,</L>
<L>Of <HI>zeale,</HI> proceeding from such ancestry,</L>
<L><HI>Goodnesse</HI> and <HI>Loue,</HI> which therefore wee require</L>
<L>To true effects of <HI>Loue</HI> and <HI>Goodnesse</HI> to aspire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sweet <HI>zeale!</HI> How fairely dost thou beautifie</L>
<L>Th'affection, where thou mak'st thy habitation,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Temple,</HI> which thy Lord did purifie,</L>
<L>When as his Soule with <HI>zeale</HI> and indignation,</L>
<L>Was mou'd to see <HI>Gods</HI> Temples prophanation,</L>
<L>Not suffering thy house of endlesse rest,</L>
<L>To be abus'd by Pride or lustfull passion,</L>
<L>Th'affection which doth lodge within my brest,</L>
<L>The <HI>Temple</HI> where <HI>Christ</HI> and the <HI>Holy Ghost</HI> should rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Companions of <HI>Zeale</HI> are <HI>Pietie,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Faith, Knowledge, Patience, Fortitude,</HI> and <HI>Right,</HI></L>
<L>In workes of <HI>Mercy, Peace,</HI> and <HI>Charitie,</HI></L>
<L>And sweet <HI>Humilitie</HI> is her delight:</L>
<L>With all her Power shee is opposite</L>
<L>Against all that <HI>Gods glory</HI> may oppose,</L>
<L>Shee spends in feruent <HI>Prayers,</HI> day and night;</L>
<L>And those by <HI>Knowledge</HI> doth so well compose,</L>
<L>They bring <HI>Gods blessings</HI> down, and vp his Iudgements close.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="14" REF="11"/>
Oh <HI>Zeale</HI> with <HI>Knowledge, Faith</HI> and <HI>Charitie,</HI></L>
<L>Who able is thy vertue to commend,</L>
<L>Which doth the <HI>Church</HI> into one <HI>Body</HI> tye,</L>
<L>And for <HI>Gods glory</HI> onely dost contend:</L>
<L>For <HI>publike good,</HI> and not for <HI>priuate end.</HI></L>
<L>Lo! th' <HI>Angells-Being</HI> doth in <HI>zeale</HI> consist;</L>
<L>Whose <HI>sacred ardour</HI> doth all flames transcend,</L>
<L>Wherewith they oft enlight our minds darke mist,</L>
<L>When flames of hottest <HI>zeale</HI> they to our soule suggest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh! <HI>Loue</HI> as strong as <HI>Death</HI> and <HI>Iealousie,</HI></L>
<L>Cruell as <HI>graue:</HI> Thy flames like coales of fire</L>
<L>Consume and burne vp all most violently,</L>
<L>No Streames or Flouds can quench her sacred ire,</L>
<L>Should we sell all we haue, we could not buy her:</L>
<L>The Daughter <HI>zeale</HI> is like the Mother free,</L>
<L>Them both from <HI>Heau'n</HI> th' <HI>Almightie</HI> doth inspire,</L>
<L>And therefore neither will affronted bee,</L>
<L>With <HI>Riualls,</HI> Heathen <HI>Gods</HI> most base <HI>Idolatree.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Fond <HI>Zeale</HI> that's fitly called which doth want</L>
<L><HI>Faith, Knowledge, Loue diuine,</HI> and <HI>Graces</HI> all,</L>
<L>It still doth most vaine superstitions haunt,</L>
<L>And to most base <HI>Idolatry</HI> doth fall,</L>
<L>Vnhumane <HI>Fury; Madnesse tragicall!</HI></L>
<L>Of men, whom thus blind <HI>zeale</HI> and strange desire,</L>
<L>Transports beyond <HI>rage diabolicall,</HI></L>
<L>To offer vp their children in the fire</L>
<L>Of some offended deuill to appease the ire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Strange is this <HI>zealous fury</HI> of the rude,</L>
<L>When <HI>Ignorance</HI> doth guide their blind deuotion,</L>
<L>The gathering of the froward multitude,</L>
<L>When they be stirred with some feruent motion:</L>
<L>All following some braine-sicke idle notion,</L>
<L>With discontent, against authoritie,</L>
<L>Raise <HI>Schismes in Church, in Common-wealth Commotion;</HI></L>
<L>Pretending all their <HI>Conscience-liberty,</HI></L>
<L>Alas! these be no fruits of holy <HI>Iealousie.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="15" REF="11"/>
<HI>God</HI> often by an <HI>Anthropopathy,</HI></L>
<L>By which his nature best wee vnderstand,</L>
<L>Ascribes vnto himselfe this <HI>Iealousie,</HI></L>
<L>As being link'd in <HI>Hymens</HI> holy band;</L>
<L>Vnto his <HI>Church,</HI> his <HI>vndefiled:</HI> And</L>
<L>His <HI>Church</HI> againe, to shew her feruent <HI>Loue,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Ioy</HI> shee takes in her new ioyned hand,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Loue-sicke Bride</HI> the <HI>Bridegroome</HI> oft doth proue,</L>
<L>And him with <HI>zeale</HI> inuites her to imbrace and <HI>Loue.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Neuer new <HI>wedded Bridegroome</HI> was more faine</L>
<L>Of his <HI>new-Bride,</HI> than <HI>Christ</HI> is of his <HI>Doue,</HI></L>
<L>Neuer did truest <HI>Turtle</HI> more complaine,</L>
<L>For losse of <HI>Mate,</HI> than this <HI>Spouse</HI> of her <HI>Loue;</HI></L>
<L>It would a stony heart to fountaines moue</L>
<L>Of teares to heare the Churches piteous mone,</L>
<L>When shee doth misse him whom her <HI>Soule doth loue,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Where's my belou'd? Ah whither is shee gone?</HI></L>
<L>And left his <HI>saddest Deare,</HI> to sigh and sit alone.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And therefore as a <HI>Signet</HI> on his heart,</L>
<L>And as the <HI>Seale</HI> that is on his right hand,</L>
<L>Shee would be ioyn'd, that shee might neuer part,</L>
<L>But alwayes in his <HI>Grace</HI> and <HI>presence</HI> stand.</L>
<L>No <HI>Keeper</HI> in <HI>Christs</HI> Vineyard must command,</L>
<L>Hee will his Vineyard prune and dresse alone,</L>
<L>Whereby his <HI>Iealousie</HI> wee vnderstand,</L>
<L>His <HI>Vine</HI> the <HI>Bridegroome</HI> will haue drest of none,</L>
<L>The <HI>Bride</HI> out of his presence neuer will be gone.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Doth mine inuention faile? that wont to flow</L>
<L>In <HI>Similes,</HI> that make hard things seeme plaine?</L>
<L>Or doth the whole Creation here below,</L>
<L>Nothing affoord <HI>zeales</HI> nature to explaine?</L>
<L>Alas all earthly <HI>Similes</HI> are vaine</L>
<L>T'expresse the nature of this <HI>Heau'nly fire,</HI></L>
<L>Which in the glorious <HI>Angells</HI> doth remaine,</L>
<L>And in the <HI>Spirits</HI> of that blessed Quire,</L>
<L>Which here with Hymnes and Praises doe <HI>Gods loue</HI> admire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="16" REF="12"/>
Shall dust and ashes dare yet be so bold,</L>
<L>Her to the <HI>holy fire</HI> to compare</L>
<L>Which in the <HI>Bush</HI> thy seruant did behold</L>
<L>Flaming, but did the <HI>Bush</HI> not singe or seare:</L>
<L>Such flames of <HI>zeale</HI> oft in our hearts there are,</L>
<L>Which doe enlighten them, but not consume</L>
<L>These flames our <HI>Prayers</HI> to <HI>Iehoua</HI> beare,</L>
<L>By these our <HI>Praises</HI> spiritually vp fume,</L>
<L>And in Gods nostrils are like incense and perfume.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Or shall I like her to some Lionesse</L>
<L>Rob'd of her whelps, by some aduenturous hand,</L>
<L>Who in her wondrous woe, and furiousnesse,</L>
<L>Deuour's and slayes all in her way that stand:</L>
<L>Who can the force of <HI>Iealousie</HI> withstand?</L>
<L>Being of so great strength and wondrous might,</L>
<L>God grant our <HI>zeale</HI> the Truth may vnderstand,</L>
<L>And that true <HI>Knowledge</HI> may your minds inlight,</L>
<L>To make vs <HI>zealous</HI> for <HI>Gods glory</HI> and the right.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>May I not like her to strong churlish wine,</L>
<L>Which doth confound the braine, inflame the blood:</L>
<L>But cool'd with water pure, and sugar fine,</L>
<L>For both of them is soueraigne and good:</L>
<L>Eu'n so doth <HI>Iealousies</HI> most feruent mood,</L>
<L>Allaid with <HI>sugar</HI> of sweet <HI>Charitie,</HI></L>
<L>And coold with <HI>sweetest Christalline</HI> pure floud,</L>
<L>The silent streames of soft <HI>Humilitie,</HI></L>
<L>Transcend in all good workes, of <HI>Loue</HI> and <HI>Pietic.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is the <HI>zeale</HI> and sacred emulation,</L>
<L>Which the Originall doth signifie;</L>
<L>Which hath with <HI>Loue</HI> in <HI>Heau'n</HI> her habitation,</L>
<L>And all our actions here doth sanctifie,</L>
<L>And when our Maker vs shall glorifie,</L>
<L>Behold! our <HI>zeale</HI> shall in perfection shine,</L>
<L>Begun on earth in true sinceritie,</L>
<L>And as our Fleshly courage doth decline,</L>
<L>Our <HI>zeale</HI> will grow more hot, and neerest to diuine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="17" REF="12"/>
<HI>Zeale</HI> made old <HI>Abram, Hagars</HI> sonne reiect,</L>
<L>For scoffing at his holy promisd seed,</L>
<L>And <HI>Moses Pharaohs</HI> Court and grace neglect,</L>
<L>When hee th' <HI>Egyptians Destiny</HI> did reed,</L>
<L>That smote a brother of the holy breed:</L>
<L>This <HI>zeale</HI> made noble <HI>Phineas</HI> with his speare,</L>
<L>Slay <HI>Zimry</HI> and <HI>Cosbi</HI> in their damned deed,</L>
<L>Though <HI>Saul</HI> the fat of <HI>Amalec</HI> would spare;</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Samuels zeale</HI> doth <HI>Agags</HI> flesh in pieces teare.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh had his Master <HI>Eli's</HI> burnt so hot</L>
<L>Against his sonnes, when they by violence</L>
<L>The fattest of Gods offrings from him got,</L>
<L>And with foule <HI>Lust</HI> defil'd the <HI>sacred Tents:</HI></L>
<L>Had he like <HI>Phineas</HI> punish't this offence?</L>
<L>Our eares then should not haue so tingeled,</L>
<L>To heare of Gods great wrath and sore offence,</L>
<L>He and his sonnes in one day slaughtered,</L>
<L>And all his race from th' <HI>Arke</HI> for euer banished.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Zeale</HI> made the warlike <HI>Dauid</HI> to aspire</L>
<L>To build an house for <HI>Gods</HI> owne habitation,</L>
<L>And though warres crost his <HI>zeale</HI> and good desire,</L>
<L>Yet made he for it royall preparation,</L>
<L>And's Sonne it finisht on his laid foundation,</L>
<L>Who gold and siluer vessels in did bring,</L>
<L>It making <HI>Iudahs</HI> Ioy, the admiration</L>
<L>Of all the World, the Seat of the great King,</L>
<L>Whither the <HI>Tribes</HI> goe vp, for his true worshipping.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I may with this example dignifie</L>
<L>The noble <HI>zeale</HI> of our late <HI>famous Queene,</HI></L>
<L>Who much desired to reedifie</L>
<L><HI>Paules</HI> Temples ruines, which so fearefull seeme,</L>
<L>And make her faire as euer shee was seene:</L>
<L>But warres abroad, and broiles within her Land,</L>
<L>Most fatall to this pious worke haue beene;</L>
<L>So as it still most ruinous doth stand,</L>
<L>Expecting helpe from <HI>Solomons</HI> pacificke hand.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="18" REF="13"/>
<HI>Zeale</HI> like a <HI>Torch</HI> it owne selfe doth consume,</L>
<L>whil'st burning it to others giueth light,</L>
<L>And like to sweetest <HI>incense</HI> and <HI>perfume</HI></L>
<L>For others Good, spends all her force and might,</L>
<L>Oh <HI>blessed fire!</HI> if kindled aright,</L>
<L>It burne with Loue of Heauen, and holy things,</L>
<L>Retaining in our hearts, both day and night,</L>
<L>His sweet imbraces, who is <HI>King</HI> of <HI>Kings,</HI></L>
<L>Loathing the worlds vaine wanton wicked dallyings.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This <HI>Cupid</HI> be thy soules and hearts delight,</L>
<L>Whose <HI>Bow</HI> and golden shafts of <HI>Zeale</HI> and <HI>Loue,</HI></L>
<L>Doe conquer <HI>Fury's, Fates,</HI> and worlds despight,</L>
<L>And stay the <HI>thunderbolts</HI> of angry <HI>Ioue:</HI></L>
<L>Oh see the force of <HI>Loue</HI> and <HI>Zeale</HI> doth moue</L>
<L>All powers that in <HI>Heau'n, Earth, Hell</HI> transcend;</L>
<L>Grant <HI>thee</HI> alone I zealously may <HI>Loue;</HI></L>
<L>And let thy <HI>Iealousie</HI> me safe defend,</L>
<L>That neuer to <HI>strange Gods</HI> I my affection bend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Let vs learne <HI>zeale</HI> of him that in the day's</L>
<L>Of's slesh, did offer <HI>Prayers,</HI> supplication</L>
<L>With strongest cry's and teares to God alwayes,</L>
<L>That able was to saue him from his <HI>Passion;</HI></L>
<L>And learne of him true holy <HI>indignation,</HI></L>
<L>To be ev'n eaten vp with feruent <HI>zeale,</HI></L>
<L>To see <HI>theeues den,</HI> in Gods owne <HI>habitation,</HI></L>
<L>But first let <HI>Knowledge</HI> our <HI>Commission seale</HI></L>
<L>That where <HI>this Feruour wounds,</HI> our <HI>Charitie may heale.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But ah our <HI>zeale</HI> of <HI>Prayer</HI> now growes cold,</L>
<L><HI>Zeale</HI> of <HI>Gods glory</HI> like our <HI>Charitie,</HI></L>
<L>And as the world declines, now waxing old,</L>
<L>Ev'n so doth all our <HI>zeale</HI> and <HI>pietie:</HI></L>
<L>We raise our <HI>houses</HI> ev'n to dare the <HI>skie,</HI></L>
<L>But raze <HI>Gods Temples</HI> equall with the ground,</L>
<L>Our Fathers built them for posteritie,</L>
<L>And left with <HI>Ornaments</HI> adorned round,</L>
<L>But we them with their <HI>Ornaments</HI> seeke to confound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="19" REF="13"/>
As for the <HI>Temples</HI> of the <HI>Holy Ghost,</HI></L>
<L>I meane our <HI>hearts</HI> the <HI>Bridegroomes</HI> habitation,</L>
<L>We will bestow on them no spirituall cost,</L>
<L>But leaue them foil'd with vilest prophanation;</L>
<L><HI>Pride, Lust, Vaine-glory,</HI> all abomination,</L>
<L>Tis time to wish this holy Bishops <HI>zeale</HI></L>
<L>Would make of them to God new consecration,</L>
<L>And that the <HI>Holy Ghost</HI> their doores would seale,</L>
<L>Against all spirituall theeues, that <HI>holy goods would steale.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh that some holy fit of <HI>Heau'nly</HI> fire,</L>
<L>Raising my <HI>Muse</HI> to <HI>zealous contemplation,</HI></L>
<L>Would in mine heart that feruent flame inspire,</L>
<L>And <HI>zealous Loue</HI> Saint <HI>Paul</HI> bare to his nation,</L>
<L>When, as hee could haue wish't eu'n reprobation</L>
<L>For their sakes, from whose flesh <HI>Christ</HI> did descend;</L>
<L>Or of the Prophet, by predestination</L>
<L>Most sure, his name in <HI>Booke of Life</HI> was pen'd</L>
<L>Yet wisht it wiped out Gods glory to defend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But I confesse, we rather doe enuy,</L>
<L>Gods gifts and graces in our Bretheren,</L>
<L>And <HI>Iosuah</HI>-like forbid them prophesie,</L>
<L>Shewing more <HI>zeale</HI> to honour Greatnesse, then</L>
<L>To Glorifie the <HI>King of Heau'n,</HI> yea when</L>
<L>We in our hearts find any emulation,</L>
<L>'Tis for vaine-glory, and the praise of men,</L>
<L>To build our houses, not <HI>Gods habitation,</HI></L>
<L>And leaue faire large possessions to our generation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Let vs with <HI>Dauid</HI> make a sacred vow,</L>
<L>And to th'Almightie <HI>God</HI> of <HI>Iacob</HI> sweare</L>
<L>Neuer to come within our house, nor bow</L>
<L>Our <HI>Limbs</HI> vpon our <HI>Beds,</HI> till we prepare</L>
<L>A place <HI>Gods spirituall Temple</HI> vp to reare:</L>
<L>Nor euer suffer sleepe within our eyes,</L>
<L>Or slumber in our eye-lids to appeare,</L>
<L>Till we an habitation doe deuise,</L>
<L>Where we may to th'Almightie offer sacrifice.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="20" REF="14"/>
My mind inflame Lord with that hot desire</L>
<L>And <HI>zeale</HI> to glorifie thy <HI>holy name,</HI></L>
<L>That like thy <HI>Martyrs</HI> I may dread no fire,</L>
<L>Because I feele within a hotter flame.</L>
<L><HI>Hot Coles</HI> therefore shall be to mee the same,</L>
<L>As to the <HI>Martyr</HI> was the <HI>Boiling Oyle,</HI></L>
<L>Which did more coole indeed than him inflame,</L>
<L>Because his <HI>zeale</HI> within did hotter boile,</L>
<L>Sweet heau'nly dewes doe most inrich the hottest soile.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh were mine head a conduit full of teares,</L>
<L>Mine eyes two rocks continually to run,</L>
<L>As well to cleanse foule <HI>Lusts</HI> of youthfull yeeres,</L>
<L>As coole the zealous slames in me begun;</L>
<L>Had I thus once my Bridegroomes presence won,</L>
<L>I neuer would let goe my well-laid hold,</L>
<L>Till hee into my <HI>Mothers</HI> chamber come,</L>
<L>With sweet embraces ay, mee to infold,</L>
<L>His ardent <HI>Loue</HI> would neuer let my <HI>zeale</HI> grow cold.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. III. <HI>Of</HI> TEMPERANCE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>MY <HI>Muse</HI> now fares like to some <HI>Pilot</HI> wise,</L>
<L>Who hauing some dread stormes of danger past,</L>
<L>That tost his vessell oft vp to the skies,</L>
<L>Now sailing in the calme with temperate blast,</L>
<L>Goes gently on, lest too much dangerous hast</L>
<L>His ship vnwares on hidden rocke impight,</L>
<L>And him and all his hopes away should cast,</L>
<L>For thus it oft befalls some carelesse wight,</L>
<L>To wreck in <HI>fairest calme,</HI> when they the storme haue quight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="21" REF="14"/>
I late was tost in rough and boisterous <HI>Sea,</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Zeale</HI> and <HI>Iealousie,</HI> which hauing past,</L>
<L>I am to saile in calme and fairest <HI>Lea,</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Temperance,</HI> most abstinent and chast;</L>
<L>Therefore my <HI>Muse</HI> goes on with sober hast,</L>
<L>Knowing against her many dangers lie,</L>
<L>Which by the <HI>touch, tongue, smell, eye, eare,</HI> or <HI>taste,</HI></L>
<L>Would her <HI>entrap,</HI> and bring in <HI>ieopardy,</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>Poets</HI> by the <HI>Syr'ts</HI> and <HI>Syrens</HI> doe imply.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And therefore did the famous blind <HI>Bards</HI> quill,</L>
<L>Preferre <HI>Vlysses</HI> in his Court of <HI>Fame,</HI></L>
<L>Who of this <HI>Temperance</HI> had got the skill,</L>
<L>Fore <HI>Aiax, Hector,</HI> or <HI>Achilles</HI> name,</L>
<L>His <HI>Odysses</HI> may testifie the same</L>
<L>Which were compos'd his <HI>Temperance</HI> to commend</L>
<L>By which he men and monsters ouercame,</L>
<L>And did life, honour, chastitie defend,</L>
<L>'Gainst <HI>Syrens</HI> and <HI>Enchantments</HI> to his latest end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And sure the <HI>Heathen,</HI> to all <HI>Christians</HI> shame,</L>
<L>Seem'd wondrously vs herein to transcend,</L>
<L>But that they wanted that most holy flame</L>
<L>Of <HI>zeale,</HI> which I so lately did commend,</L>
<L>And <HI>knowledge,</HI> which should guide them to their end,</L>
<L>All that they had by natures light was showne,</L>
<L>But <HI>God</HI> his <HI>holy Word</HI> to vs doth send,</L>
<L>Whereby his <HI>Will</HI> and <HI>Counsell</HI> is made knowne,</L>
<L>What fruit then ought we beare, where so good seed is sowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Eue</HI> was the first <HI>Author</HI> of <HI>Intemperance,</HI></L>
<L>Led by her eye, nice tast, and fond desire</L>
<L>Of <HI>Knowledge,</HI> with proud wicked <HI>Ignorance,</HI></L>
<L>And chang'd <HI>Gods Loue to euerlasting ire,</HI></L>
<L>The Garden loosing for eternall fire;</L>
<L>But what <HI>shee</HI> lost his <HI>Temperance</HI> doth gaine,</L>
<L>Whose aid now in mine entrance I desire</L>
<L>Who from all food, did fortie dayes abstaine,</L>
<L>And all's Life from <HI>intemperate,</HI> thought, word, deed, refraine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="22" REF="15"/>
This <HI>Vertue</HI> some doe make so <HI>Cardinall,</HI></L>
<L>That all the rest, in her they would imply,</L>
<L>As <HI>Loue, Peace, Concord, Pudour Virginall,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Gentlenesse, Meekenesse, Liberalitie,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Thrift, Silence, Friendship, Goodnesse, Grauitie,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Honesty, Purenesse,</HI> all true <HI>moderation,</HI></L>
<L>Which doth withhold from <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Vanitie,</HI></L>
<L>And bringeth vnto true humiliation:</L>
<L>Most happy <HI>Mother</HI> of so faire a Generation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But in some limits that I may her bound,</L>
<L>I <HI>her define</HI> to be a <HI>moderation</HI></L>
<L>Of such <HI>desires,</HI> as are within vs found</L>
<L>In <HI>Diet, Actions, Words,</HI> and <HI>Affectation;</HI></L>
<L>For with these <HI>fow'r</HI> I bound my <HI>Meditation;</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Diet</HI> shee requires <HI>Sobrietie,</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Actions,</HI> true vnfain'd <HI>humiliation,</HI></L>
<L>Her <HI>Words</HI> she graceth aye with <HI>Modesty,</HI></L>
<L>And her <HI>affections</HI> charmes with <HI>Meeknesse; Chastity.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>See in her <HI>Diet,</HI> first <HI>Sobrietie,</HI></L>
<L>In words and actions true <HI>humiliation,</HI></L>
<L>Accompany'd with precious <HI>Modesty;</HI></L>
<L>Last <HI>Continence</HI> from <HI>Lust,</HI> and angry <HI>Passion,</HI></L>
<L>The cause of all is <HI>prudent Moderation;</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>aged Palmer, Spencer, Guyons</HI> trustie guide,</L>
<L>That stands against all <HI>stubborne perturbation,</HI></L>
<L>By whose sage helpe, secure and safe we slide,</L>
<L>By whirle-pooles, and deepe gulfes which gape for vs so wide.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For all through this worlds boistrous Sea must passe,</L>
<L>Before we at our quiet Hav'n arriue,</L>
<L>The <HI>Boate</HI> our Body is, as brittle glasse,</L>
<L>Our <HI>Steeres-man▪ Temperance,</HI> it right doth driue,</L>
<L>Besides the Rocks, that threat this Boat to riue;</L>
<L>Are many <HI>Gulphes,</HI> and <HI>Whirle-pooles</HI> of decay</L>
<L>Which wait th' <HI>Affections,</HI> and the <HI>Senses</HI> fiue</L>
<L>By force and sweet Allurements to assay,</L>
<L>Some fall by rage and diet, some by lustfull play.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="23" REF="15"/>
But in that Body where doth reason sway,</L>
<L>And <HI>Sense</HI> and <HI>Passion</HI> be obedient,</L>
<L>There the <HI>affections</HI> all behold you may</L>
<L>In happy peace, and goodly gouernment:</L>
<L>There <HI>Temperance</HI> adornes her glorious Tent,</L>
<L>With vertues all to make it shine most bright,</L>
<L>The mirrour of Gods workes most excellent,</L>
<L>And to them all such bounteous banquets dight,</L>
<L>As may be best for <HI>Health, Praise, Profit,</HI> and <HI>Delight.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Most <HI>glorious frame</HI> of <HI>nature!</HI> which shee built,</L>
<L>The whole world in one point t'epitomize,</L>
<L>Iust, pure, and perfect, till <HI>intemprate guilt,</HI></L>
<L>Her Makers Hests by Pride did foule misprise,</L>
<L>Since that shee learned to belowly, wise,</L>
<L>And not obey intemperate desire,</L>
<L>Thus shee her <HI>glorious house</HI> reedifies,</L>
<L>And most of all doth lowly Cells admire,</L>
<L>The loftiest is no place for <HI>temperate retire.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Shee therefore neuer comes in company,</L>
<L>Of such as swim in pride, and bathe in blisse,</L>
<L>Wasting their dayes in ease and luxury,</L>
<L>For in such ease, men easily doe amisse,</L>
<L>But hee whose mind in studie watchfull is,</L>
<L>Whose limbs are toyl'd with labour, mind, with paine;</L>
<L>Shee these as her sweet darlings deare doth kisse,</L>
<L>The idle life cannot to her attaine;</L>
<L>Before <HI>her Gate,</HI> high God <HI>employment</HI> did ordaine!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Excesse doth make the minde of beastly man,</L>
<L>Forget his first created excellence;</L>
<L>That pure estate in which his <HI>Life began,</HI></L>
<L>And as a <HI>Beast</HI> that wants intelligence,</L>
<L>'Twixt <HI>sense</HI> and <HI>reason</HI> put no difference,</L>
<L>But like a <HI>Brute</HI> of base and swinish kind;</L>
<L>Delights in filth and foule incontinence,</L>
<L>For <HI>Lust</HI> and Wine so far transforme the minde,</L>
<L>Affections beare the sway, and <HI>royall reason</HI> binde.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="24" REF="16"/>
Thus <HI>Bacchus Fountain's</HI> turn'd to <HI>puddle lake,</HI></L>
<L>Wherein like filthy beasts base men lie drown'd,</L>
<L>And <HI>Swines</HI> of <HI>Gods faire Images</HI> doe make;</L>
<L>This <HI>vice</HI> hath now with vs such footing found,</L>
<L>As Drunkennesse with glory doth abound,</L>
<L><HI>Pure Liber,</HI> wont to be the <HI>Muses</HI> friend,</L>
<L>All <HI>musing, Wit</HI> and <HI>Learning</HI> doth confound,</L>
<L>The <HI>Flemings</HI> this did first to vs commend,</L>
<L>But herein we them and all Nations now transcend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>No better stratageme doth <HI>Satan know,</HI></L>
<L>(I alwayes must except base drunkennesse)</L>
<L>Then gaming all our youth to ouerthrow,</L>
<L>The <HI>fruict Intemperate</HI> of Idlenesse</L>
<L>Oh horrible, infernall wickednesse:</L>
<L>To heare a wretch, his Makers name blaspheme,</L>
<L>When Dice or Carding crosse his good successe,</L>
<L>And eu'n his <HI>Soule,</HI> which <HI>Christ's bloud</HI> did redeeme;</L>
<L>With his estate, to hazard to a <HI>dyes esteeme.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Intemprate, drinking, Play, smoake,</HI> in excesse</L>
<L>Is now our gallants onely occupation,</L>
<L>The poisoning fruits of their loose Idlenesse,</L>
<L>Base <HI>Gourmandizing,</HI> filthy <HI>Fornication</HI></L>
<L>Is turn'd from foule reproach to commendation,</L>
<L>Now vse of <HI>Armes and manly exercise,</HI></L>
<L>Are held a <HI>toile</HI> and not a <HI>recreation;</HI></L>
<L>Who so is <HI>moderate, chast, valiant, wise,</HI></L>
<L>Him as precise and cynicall they doe despise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh foolish <HI>Man!</HI> learne <HI>Temperance</HI> of thy Dog,</L>
<L>Thine Horse and Hawke, wherein thou tak'st delight,</L>
<L>Which when they should shew sport, thou dost not clog</L>
<L>And fill with food, their greedie appetite;</L>
<L>Thou them dost diet, that they may be light,</L>
<L>And keepst from Lust, their courage to prolong,</L>
<L>One dulls the Body, th'other kills the Sprite,</L>
<L>But <HI>Abstinence</HI> doth make both swift and strong,</L>
<L>The <HI>temperate</HI> mans dayes are happy healthfull long.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="25" REF="16"/>
And may vnto <HI>Pauls Pilote</HI> be compar'd,</L>
<L>Whose vessell with exceeding tempest tost,</L>
<L>Vnlades, and lightens, hauing most regard,</L>
<L>To saue his <HI>Life,</HI> though all his goods be lost;</L>
<L>Eu'n so the <HI>temperate</HI> man in this world crost,</L>
<L>With baits of <HI>appetite, lust, anger, pride,</HI></L>
<L>Makes vse of those that for his vse are most,</L>
<L>But needlesse things, wherewith his vessels cloid,</L>
<L>With his owne hands doth to the hungry, fish diuide.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>When I behold the stately Firmament,</L>
<L>Adorn'd with glorious <HI>Lamps</HI> of heau'nly fire;</L>
<L>The Stars with their appointed roomes content,</L>
<L>And neither other to supplant desire;</L>
<L>Their <HI>Temperance</HI> in Heau'n, I doe admire:</L>
<L>But then I view the anbitious sparkes below,</L>
<L>Who to possesse the whole Earth doe aspire;</L>
<L>And all poore Cottages to ouerthrow,</L>
<L>That stopt their prospect, great alone on earth to grow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Nature</HI> with small, no plentie <HI>Lust</HI> can bound,</L>
<L>Vnlimited desires here satisfie,</L>
<L>No Gold, nor Siluer can, though they abound,</L>
<L>Like stones amongst the <HI>wise Kings vanitie:</HI></L>
<L>Though <HI>Iesses Sonne</HI> haue such varietie</L>
<L>Of <HI>Wiues</HI> and <HI>Maids,</HI> yet comes the <HI>stranger, Lust,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Vrias</HI> onely <HI>Lamb</HI> for him must dye,</L>
<L>No home-bred fare, can satisfie base dust;</L>
<L>But strange rare cates from forraine nations haue we must.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>temprate</HI> man, I to a Brooke compare,</L>
<L>Contented with sweet Fountaines of her owne;</L>
<L>Which runs most pleasant, pure, delightfull, cleere:</L>
<L>But if with flouds her channels once be flowne,</L>
<L>Then streight her troubled waters foule are growne.</L>
<L>So whil'st we <HI>Temperance</HI> with vs retaine,</L>
<L>And no excesse of Diet's in vs knowne,</L>
<L>Our heart from ire, our bed is free from staine:</L>
<L>But cease from <HI>Temperance,</HI> and all is foule againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="26" REF="17"/>
And as pure Streames continue sweet and cleere,</L>
<L>Whil'st they within their Channells swiftly flow,</L>
<L>Refreshing all the plants and flowers neere,</L>
<L>But if they idlely stand, or run but slow,</L>
<L>Then thicke and foule like idle lake they grow:</L>
<L>Ev'n so the man that doth his minde aduance,</L>
<L>His Makers heau'nly will to doe and know,</L>
<L>To honour shall be rais'd aboue all chance,</L>
<L>But he that idle grow's falls to <HI>Intemperance.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Shee is a short, but a most pleasant way,</L>
<L>Wherein small labour is but much delight,</L>
<L>The <HI>Empresse</HI> that doth our affections sway,</L>
<L>The <HI>Genus</HI> of all other <HI>vertues</HI> hight,</L>
<L><HI>Piller of Fortitude,</HI> The <HI>Helmet bright,</HI></L>
<L>Against <HI>Lasciuiousnesse,</HI> The <HI>eyes best guide,</HI></L>
<L>Bond of <HI>goodwill,</HI> of <HI>cogitations light,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Restraint;</HI> The <HI>Enemy</HI> of <HI>Lust</HI> and <HI>Pride,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Soules chast counsellour,</HI> her vow' and prayers to guide.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Of <HI>Prudence</HI> and true <HI>Wisdome</HI> the foundation,</L>
<L>To him that hath her, can no ill befall,</L>
<L>No greater wealth can be then Contentation,</L>
<L>Who hath her, hath that, who lacks that, wants all,</L>
<L>Who nothing need; eu'n Gods the Heathen call.</L>
<L><HI>Fortune</HI> may bring vs wealth and royall fare,</L>
<L>But <HI>Temperance</HI> must giue content withall,</L>
<L>By her we freed from perturbations are,</L>
<L>And hauing <HI>daily bread,</HI> doe take no farther care:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For from her <HI>Temper</HI> shee receiues her name,</L>
<L>As being of extreames the moderation,</L>
<L>The <HI>golden meane</HI> that doth affections frame,</L>
<L>Actions and Words to natures ordination,</L>
<L>Vnspotted pure as at our first Creation:</L>
<L>Thus wee abstaine from <HI>Lust</HI> and Violence,</L>
<L>And though on earth is yet our Conuersation,</L>
<L>Wee hope ere long to be receiued hence,</L>
<L>Meane while, our Life's a sacrifice of Continence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="27" REF="17"/>
Thus see our <HI>protoplasts</HI> first cloth'd in skins</L>
<L>The greene <HI>herbe</HI> of the field their onely <HI>meate,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Beasts</HI> their <HI>Conuiues,</HI> and the <HI>Woods</HI> their <HI>Inns,</HI></L>
<L>To shield from cold, and saue from scorching heate,</L>
<L>And all this must be got with toile and sweate,</L>
<L>No liuing thing was then allowed good;</L>
<L>For, as the learned thinke, man might not eate,</L>
<L>Of any liuing creature till the Floud,</L>
<L>But since, as the greene herbe, God gaue them all for food.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>How often did the Fathers pray and fast,</L>
<L>And some from women, some from wine abstaine,</L>
<L>Till sixtie yeeres they keepe their bodies chast,</L>
<L>A <HI>Temprate</HI> and chast seed here to obtaine:</L>
<L>When <HI>Ruth</HI> at <HI>Booz</HI> feet, all night had laine</L>
<L>He ladeth her with corne and sends away,</L>
<L>From lawlesse Lust he doth himselfe containe,</L>
<L>Though he had dranke, and cheer'd his heart that day,</L>
<L>An habite of true <HI>Temperance</HI> see here you may.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Ioseph</HI> would not against his Maker sinne,</L>
<L>For <HI>Pharoahs</HI> Stewards Ladies soft embrace,</L>
<L>Yet easier 'tis a walled towne to winne,</L>
<L>Than to resist temptations vile and base,</L>
<L>Nought sooner doth our liues with <HI>Lust</HI> disgrace,</L>
<L>Than bathe in ease and swim in foule excesse,</L>
<L>Had <HI>Dauid</HI> beene at warre in <HI>Ioabs</HI> place</L>
<L>He had not falne into such wickednesse,</L>
<L><HI>Adultery,</HI> the fruit of fulnesse, Idlenesse.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh tell me <HI>Dauid,</HI> where was then become,</L>
<L>Thy fasting wont thy soule to humble so,</L>
<L>That it was wont to thy reproach to come,</L>
<L>And weakned so thy knees, thou couldst not goe?</L>
<L>Thy teares which did to such great plentie grow,</L>
<L>They were thy meat and drinke, both day and night,</L>
<L>All watering thy couch, so they did slow,</L>
<L>That eu'n my <HI>Muse</HI> weepes at thy piteous plight,</L>
<L>Yet had thy soule therein vnspeakeable delight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="28" REF="18"/>
I cannot but admire the <HI>Temperance,</HI></L>
<L>Of that <HI>great Monarch;</HI> mightie <HI>Phillips</HI> Sonne,</L>
<L>Who when he had vnto his gouernance,</L>
<L><HI>Darius</HI> Empire, <HI>Wife</HI> and <HI>Daughters</HI> wonne,</L>
<L>Their beautie would by no meanes looke vpon;</L>
<L>Esteeming it a most vnworthy deed,</L>
<L>When he so many men had ouercome,</L>
<L>To be of one weake woman conquered,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Temperance</HI> of so yong a Prince I neuer read.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Not that the Heathens <HI>Temper</HI> I compare,</L>
<L>To those that haue beene truely sanctifide,</L>
<L>Of which <HI>Iob</HI> is to vs a patterne rare;</L>
<L>Who least his eyes should draw his heart aside,</L>
<L>Did couenant they on no Maid should glide:</L>
<L>How infinite are watchings, fastings, cold,</L>
<L>Which to subdue the flesh <HI>Paul</HI> did abide,</L>
<L>But aboue all th'examples I haue told,</L>
<L>The <HI>Locust-eater</HI> and's Disciples liues behold.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And though whilst that the <HI>Bridegroome</HI> pleas'd to stay,</L>
<L>The <HI>children</HI> of <HI>Bride-chamber</HI> did not fast,</L>
<L>Yet when from them he taken was away,</L>
<L>Behold they then did pay for all was past,</L>
<L>And oft did hunger, whip, and prison tast;</L>
<L>No <HI>Poets</HI> quill ere able was to faine,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Temp'rance</HI> of pure Lamb most temprate chast,</L>
<L>Reuiled, scoffed, scorned, scourged, slaine;</L>
<L>Yet opn'd not his mouth to scoffe, or speake againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh shall the <HI>King</HI> of Angels and of Men,</L>
<L>Abus'd by workmanship of his owne hand,</L>
<L>Endure such wrongs, and neuer turne agen:</L>
<L>Whose one word could haue call'd th'whole heau'nly Band,</L>
<L>The Fury of these wretches to withstand;</L>
<L>And shall the <HI>Lord of Life</HI> so meekly dye,</L>
<L>For our <HI>intemperate</HI> affections; and</L>
<L>Shall not we them all with him crucifie,</L>
<L>And fleshly members of our Body's mortifie?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="29" REF="18"/>
But we like <HI>Foxes</HI> build a stately hall,</L>
<L>And like the <HI>Birds</HI> in stately cedars nest,</L>
<L>When <HI>Hee</HI> that did of nothing make them all,</L>
<L>Had not a place to lay his <HI>head to rest;</HI></L>
<L>Wee see his glorious members here distrest,</L>
<L>Want lodging, food, and raiment for the cold,</L>
<L>Whil'st we abound in meates, and fill our chest</L>
<L>With change of raiment, and with store of gold,</L>
<L>And in birds softest plumes, our looser limbs infold.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Alas how many hunting worlds gay showes,</L>
<L>By base <HI>Intemperances</HI> sweetned baite,</L>
<L>And vile <HI>Ambition</HI> which downe headlong throwes,</L>
<L>Are brought to ruine most infortunate;</L>
<L>Oh grant that I may liue in meane estate,</L>
<L>And my freed soule with Contemplation please;</L>
<L>My clothing warme, my diet <HI>temperate,</HI></L>
<L>Freed from all tempests of worlds raging seas,</L>
<L>Which tosse poore sailing soules, in dangerous disease.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Most happy who with little is content,</L>
<L>That though he want, yet neuer doth complaine;</L>
<L>Ne wisheth more his sorrow to augment,</L>
<L>Knowing that he by heaping wealth doth gaine,</L>
<L>Nothing but care, vexation, and paine:</L>
<L>What more than daily bread here doe I need?</L>
<L>What need of forraine cates or feathers vaine?</L>
<L>Let fields my food; my flocke my clothing breed,</L>
<L>No other would I weare, no other would I feed.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In vaine doe foolish men the Heau'ns accuse</L>
<L>Of sad misfortunes, paines, and iniuries,</L>
<L>Which doe (if we knew truely them to vse)</L>
<L>To eu'ry man what's fittest for him size,</L>
<L>That's not the best estate which most we prize,</L>
<L>Nor that the worst, which most men seeke to shun,</L>
<L>Each as he list his fortunes may deuise,</L>
<L>Which wishes, no man happinesse hath wun,</L>
<L>Such wishers cease to liue, before their life begun.</L>
<PB N="26" REF="19"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="27" REF="19"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="28" REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="29" REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="30" REF="21"/>
It is mans mind that maketh good or ill,</L>
<L>Wretched or happy, sad, glad, rich or poore,</L>
<L>He hath abundantly all things at will,</L>
<L>That hauing little, yet desires no more,</L>
<L>When he that's drown'd in wealth, &amp; swims in store,</L>
<L>Doth liue in want to satisfie desire,</L>
<L>Which neuer hath enough, fond fooles therefore,</L>
<L>Are they that feed <HI>Lusts</HI> and <HI>Ambitions</HI> fire,</L>
<L>Which like base <HI>Auarice,</HI> doth more and more require.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>When first I saw the glory of the <HI>Great,</HI></L>
<L>I then them onely happy men did hold,</L>
<L>For sumptuous houses, lodging, rayment, meat,</L>
<L>Honour, Attendance, Iewells, Siluer, Gold,</L>
<L>But when the cares and dangers I behold,</L>
<L>Of those whom Fortune doth so high aduance,</L>
<L>How to dissembling slattery some are sold;</L>
<L>Lust, Fulnesse, Idlenesse, Intemperance;</L>
<L>My life I happy deeme, in quiet lowly chance.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus of late folly's, I though late complaine,</L>
<L>And that sweet <HI>Peace,</HI> which doth not there appeare,</L>
<L>Now in mine <HI>homely Cell</HI> I entertaine,</L>
<L>Which by her want I learne to loue more deare;</L>
<L>Sweet holy quiet life! where meanest cheare</L>
<L>To hungry stomocks, is a daily feast,</L>
<L>Where thirst like <HI>Nectar,</HI> makes fresh cooling beere;</L>
<L>Where in a cabbin is more quiet rest,</L>
<L>Than on Downe <HI>Persian beds,</HI> with Gold and Feathers drest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In this estate I no man doe enuie,</L>
<L>Nor would enuied be of any one;</L>
<L>Great store of wealth, doth store of cares supply,</L>
<L>That little that I haue is still mine owne,</L>
<L>I reape with Ioy the crop, that I haue sowne,</L>
<L>Without least care but onely to attend it,</L>
<L>The <HI>Lambs</HI> I weane, are daily <HI>greater</HI> growne:</L>
<L>What haue I but to praise him that doth send it?</L>
<L>And with a cheerefull heart vnto the poore to lend it.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="31" REF="21"/>
But least corrupt my mind, or body grow</L>
<L>with too much ease, or wanton Idlenesse;</L>
<L>My mind I set my <HI>Makers Will</HI> to know,</L>
<L>His <HI>Wisedome, Power, Truth,</HI> and <HI>Holinesse;</HI></L>
<L>I often ride or walke to wearinesse,</L>
<L>The members of my body to subdue</L>
<L>And <HI>Temper</HI> 'gainst <HI>Lust</HI> and <HI>Laciuiousnesse,</HI></L>
<L>Thus by sweet contemplation, oft I view,</L>
<L>Such high transcendent things, as yet I neuer knew.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus rapt with contemplation I find,</L>
<L>That all these worlds-gay show's which men admire,</L>
<L>Are but <HI>vaine shadow's,</HI> to the <HI>ioy's of mind</HI></L>
<L>Of those, that lead their liues in safe retire;</L>
<L>Whose onely happinesse and hearts desire,</L>
<L>Is here the talents God hath lent to spend</L>
<L>Vnto his glory, as he doth require,</L>
<L>And vsing <HI>Temperately</HI> what he doth send;</L>
<L>Thus grant that I may liue, Thus grant that I may end.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. IIII. <HI>of</HI> BOVNTIE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>NOw will I raise faire <HI>Alma's</HI> stately tower,</L>
<L>On <HI>Temperance,</HI> her strong and soundest frame;</L>
<L>And goodly deck <HI>Dame Bounty's</HI> dainty bower,</L>
<L>Whereby all Princes gaine immortall fame:</L>
<L>Some call her <HI>Alma,</HI> some her <HI>Bounty</HI> name,</L>
<L>The trusty <HI>Almner</HI> of <HI>Loues Royall</HI> Court;</L>
<L>Who beares the bag to giue to blind and lame,</L>
<L>And Suitors all that thither doe resort</L>
<L>Rewards most <HI>bounteously,</HI> and feeds in seemely sort.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="32" REF="22"/>
For on this heau'nly <HI>Dame</HI> the eyes of all</L>
<L>Looke vp, that of her liberalitie</L>
<L>They may receiue, and shee againe lets fall,</L>
<L>Vpon them needfull things most plenteously,</L>
<L>Her bounteous hand shee opens willingly,</L>
<L>With blessings eu'ry creature full to fill,</L>
<L>To those that <HI>Knowledge</HI> seeke, abundantly,</L>
<L>Shee giueth <HI>Wisdome, Vnderstanding, Skill,</HI></L>
<L>To know their <HI>Makers Bountie, Maiestie,</HI> and <HI>Will.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Most glorious <HI>Alma!</HI> when as <HI>Temperance</HI></L>
<L>Controlls the noble Plentie of her Hall,</L>
<L>And with her Staffe keepes out <HI>Intemperance,</HI></L>
<L>Which doth abuse her <HI>Grace</HI> and <HI>Bountie</HI> all;</L>
<L>For where most Plentie is, there most doe fall</L>
<L>By want of <HI>Temperance</HI> to Lust and Sin,</L>
<L>Till they be brought low as the <HI>Prodigall,</HI></L>
<L>For he that will true Praise by <HI>Bountie</HI> win,</L>
<L>Must first of all at home with <HI>Temperance</HI> begin.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For <HI>Temperance</HI> with watchfull <HI>diligence,</HI></L>
<L>Are like two springs which <HI>waters</HI> doe supply,</L>
<L>To open handed free <HI>Beneficence,</HI></L>
<L>And her discernes from <HI>Prodigalitie,</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Diligence</HI> we get sufficiencie</L>
<L>By <HI>Temperance,</HI> what we haue gotten, spare</L>
<L>To minister to <HI>Liberalitie,</HI></L>
<L>For these two, <HI>Lady-Bounty's</HI> handmaids are,</L>
<L>And for her, iust, and truly, store of wealth prepare.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But they that liue in <HI>sloth and foule excesse,</HI></L>
<L>Though they may seeme to be most liberall,</L>
<L><HI>Oppression,</HI> and <HI>Extortion</HI> mercilesse,</L>
<L>Are <HI>Lakes,</HI> from whence their <HI>Bounty's streamed</HI> doe fall,</L>
<L>And thus they rob the poore, that therewithall</L>
<L>They may themselues, rich friends, and children feast,</L>
<L>Blaspheming their great Maker, Lord of all,</L>
<L>And imitating basest sauage beast,</L>
<L>Which fawnes vpon the great, But doth deuoure the least.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="33" REF="22"/>
<HI>God of all Bountie, King most Liberall;</HI></L>
<L>Who to thy vassall Man at his Creation,</L>
<L>Didst subiect make, Fish, Fowle, Beasts, creatures all,</L>
<L>And of thine handy works gau'st domination;</L>
<L>Who by thy prouidence and ordination</L>
<L>Him needfull things not onely dost prouide,</L>
<L>But for his health, delight and contentation,</L>
<L>That he may plentie to the poore diuide,</L>
<L>My <HI>Muse</HI> to sing, heart, hands, to practise <HI>Bountie</HI> guide.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Bountie, Beneficence, Benignitie,</HI></L>
<L>In name though diuers, one in substance be,</L>
<L><HI>Beneuolence</HI> and <HI>Liberalitie,</HI></L>
<L>Make <HI>actions,</HI> and <HI>affections</HI> agree,</L>
<L>If as they are, in God you wish to see,</L>
<L>They like his <HI>Goodnesse</HI> are vnlimitted,</L>
<L>And as his <HI>Mercy, Loue,</HI> and <HI>Grace</HI> are free,</L>
<L>Which on his creatures are abundant shed,</L>
<L>But by my shallow <HI>Muse</HI> their depth cannot be read.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>They are too high to reach, too deepe to sound,</L>
<L>For all the earth is filled therewithall:</L>
<L>In heau'n aboue Gods <HI>Goodnesse</HI> doth abound,</L>
<L>The <HI>Bountie of his Grace</HI> is ouer all;</L>
<L>Of all the <HI>Meditations</HI> which call</L>
<L>My mind, to holy <HI>Ioy</HI> and admiration,</L>
<L>None lets more comfort than Gods <HI>Bountie</HI> fall,</L>
<L>Both for my being and my preseruation,</L>
<L>But most in that he shed his bloud for my <HI>Saluation.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Here could I wish my <HI>Muse</HI> might euer dwell,</L>
<L>In viewing Gods great <HI>Goodnesse, Bountie, Loue,</HI></L>
<L>Which three to th'holy <HI>Trinitie</HI> I well</L>
<L>May here ascribe; For <HI>Goodnesse</HI> first doth moue</L>
<L>The <HI>Father,</HI> to beget <HI>Eternall Loue,</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>Loue</HI> and <HI>Goodnesse, Bountie</HI> doth proceed:</L>
<L>Yet all these <HI>three,</HI> as one in God doe proue,</L>
<L>In <HI>substance</HI> one, although <HI>distinguished</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>working!</HI> But this height my reach doth far exceed.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="34" REF="23"/>
And therefore rauish't now with contemplation,</L>
<L>Beyond the compasse of my feeble eye,</L>
<L>My soule amaz'd falls downe to adoration</L>
<L>Of this misterious holy <HI>Trinitie,</HI></L>
<L>And from <HI>diuine</HI> come to <HI>benignitie:</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>bountie</HI> which should be in men below,</L>
<L>A <HI>habit</HI> wee of <HI>liberalitie;</HI></L>
<L>Her call and good <HI>affection</HI> we should show</L>
<L>In <HI>thought, heart, word,</HI> and <HI>deed,</HI> to eu'ry one we know.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And must from <HI>goodnesse</HI> and true <HI>loue</HI> proceed,</L>
<L>The onely cause of true <HI>benignitie;</HI></L>
<L>Wherefore, except these be in vs indeed,</L>
<L>Our <HI>bounty</HI> is but <HI>prodigalitie:</HI></L>
<L>Or some like <HI>froth</HI> of <HI>superfluitie.</HI></L>
<L>The crums and leauings of <HI>Intemperance,</HI></L>
<L>Which oft are dealt out with an euill eye,</L>
<L>More for vaine credit, or base circumstance,</L>
<L>Then for goodwill, or care Gods glory to aduance.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For eu'ry act hath then her true effect,</L>
<L>Which from true ground right aymeth at her end,</L>
<L>As when both <HI>loue</HI> and <HI>goodnesse</HI> doth direct</L>
<L>What <HI>bounty</HI> truly gets, aright to spend:</L>
<L>Loe thus doth heau'nly <HI>grace</HI> and <HI>Bounty</HI> send</L>
<L>Her blessings temporall alike to all;</L>
<L>But doth for greater <HI>benefits</HI> intend,</L>
<L>To those that on Gods name aright doe call,</L>
<L>And in this heau'nly sort, ought we be liberall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh! then th' effects of <HI>bounty</HI> glorious are,</L>
<L>When <HI>Prouidence</HI> with true <HI>Frugality,</HI></L>
<L>Doe seeke by <HI>Iustice</HI> to prouide and spare</L>
<L>Fit <HI>sustenance</HI> for <HI>liberality;</HI></L>
<L>Behold that heau'nly <HI>bounteous Maiesty,</HI></L>
<L>Sends raine and fruitfull seasons whereby store</L>
<L>Of Blessings, th'earth may to his hand supply,</L>
<L>And many hidden treasures vp doth store</L>
<L>For to exalt the rich, and to refresh the pore.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="35" REF="23"/>
Then humane <HI>bounty</HI> like her Makers is,</L>
<L>When as shee labours to doe good to all;</L>
<L>But most of all to bring poore soules to blisse,</L>
<L>And fill their hearts with food spirituall:</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Grace</HI> Diuine? <HI>Bounty Angelicall;</HI></L>
<L>With <HI>spirituall loaues in Wildernesse</HI> to feed</L>
<L>Gods Saints, when spirituall hunger them doth gal;</L>
<L>The ignorant which pine with inward need,</L>
<L>Diuine sweet comforts to their fainting soules to reade.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>True <HI>Bounty's</HI> knowne, best by her company,</L>
<L>For shee in <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Mercy</HI> takes delight;</L>
<L><HI>Faith, Iustice, Temperance, Humility,</HI></L>
<L>And is withall <HI>Loues graces</HI> richly dight,</L>
<L>Herein appeares her glorious heau'nly Sp'rite:</L>
<L>Shewing that shee of seed diuine is borne,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Loue</HI> and <HI>Goodnesse,</HI> not of <HI>Vaine delight,</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>Fame</HI> and <HI>Praise of men,</HI> when shee doth scorne</L>
<L>To seeke feign'd bounteous shewes, her <HI>goodnes</HI> to adorn.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For thus th' <HI>ambitious</HI> man is <HI>bountifull,</HI></L>
<L>Thus belly-gods in plentie take delight,</L>
<L><HI>Deceit</HI> with <HI>gifts</HI> his neighbour seekes to gull,</L>
<L>The couetous bribe large to conquer right;</L>
<L>From such false <HI>Bounty,</HI> Truth is banish't quite,</L>
<L><HI>Humility, Faith, Knowledge, Temperance,</HI></L>
<L>Nor any of <HI>Loues Graces</HI> in her sight,</L>
<L>May suffered be their ensignes to aduance,</L>
<L>There dwells <HI>Contention, Pride, Oppression, Ignorance.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As <HI>daughters</HI> of the <HI>horse-leech,</HI> still doe cry,</L>
<L>Giue giue: as Graue and Hell be neuer full,</L>
<L>So nought the couetous eye can satisfie,</L>
<L>But he that's liberall and bountifull</L>
<L>Is like full clouds, which doe most plentifull</L>
<L>Water the earth, and poure downe store of raine,</L>
<L>Yet are not emptie; for the mercifull</L>
<L>And liberall shall greater plentie gaine,</L>
<L>And he that scattereth shall find increase againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="36" REF="24" MS="y"/>
That hand is neuer emptie of reward,</L>
<L>Where as goodwill the hearts chest filleth full,</L>
<L>And <HI>bountie</HI> neuer is so much afear'd,</L>
<L>Causlesse to giue, As not be bountifull</L>
<L>Where need requires; His face is beautifull</L>
<L>Where sweet Goodwill both heart and lookes haue Ioyn'd;</L>
<L>But th'enuious and malitious doe pull,</L>
<L>On wrinkles: And a man shall euer find,</L>
<L>The beautie of the face to alter with the mind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Bountie</HI> is like vnto the glorious Sun,</L>
<L>Which as a <HI>Bridegroome</HI> doth from chamber glide,</L>
<L>And as a <HI>Gyant</HI> ioy's his course to run</L>
<L>From <HI>East</HI> to <HI>West,</HI> most swiftly he doth ride,</L>
<L>Nothing from's fertile heat it selfe can hide;</L>
<L>He doth not looke that one him vp should call:</L>
<L>So <HI>bountie</HI> deales her Graces far and wide,</L>
<L>And Blessings without asking sends to all;</L>
<L>Expecting not vaine praise, where shee lets graces fall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As some faire glorious garment, which we weare</L>
<L>Vpon our shoulders, reaching to the ground,</L>
<L>Couers all spots, and Naeues that on vs are:</L>
<L>So where this noble <HI>bounty</HI> doth abound,</L>
<L>It couereth all faults that can be found,</L>
<L>For as <HI>Loue</HI> couers, so doth <HI>Bounty</HI> hide</L>
<L>A multitude of sins, and doth confound,</L>
<L>By her bright Beames, <HI>Detraction, Enuy, Pride;</HI></L>
<L>Alas these are to weake where <HI>Bounty's</HI> on our side.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Shee's like vnto the Lamp of glorious day,</L>
<L>Which doth diuide the darknesse from the light,</L>
<L>For whereas <HI>Bountie</HI> doth her beames display,</L>
<L>Behold bright day: without them there is night;</L>
<L>The King that by his <HI>bountie</HI> doth inuite,</L>
<L>His subiects hearts to Loue and Honour due,</L>
<L>Sleepes more secure, than he that doth by might</L>
<L>And feare, strong forts and walled townes subdue,</L>
<L>And for his guard's encompassed with armed crue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="37" REF="24"/>
Bountie and Benefits are eu'n the Bands,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Concord,</HI> and as fire doth quickly dye,</L>
<L>That is not fostered with coles or brands;</L>
<L>So dies true Loue with men: Except supply</L>
<L>Be made by gifts and liberalitie:</L>
<L>Who doth the wandring soule direct aright,</L>
<L>Though with him he doth deale most bounteously;</L>
<L>Yet doth he but his fellowes candle light,</L>
<L>And to another giues, yet loseth selfe no light.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>True <HI>bounty</HI> seekes <HI>high God</HI> to imitate,</L>
<L>Who to the most vnthankfull is most free,</L>
<L><HI>Sol</HI> doth his light to Theeues participate</L>
<L>And without tempests, Pirates saile on Sea,</L>
<L>The Heau'ns of all good things the Authors bee,</L>
<L>Faire fortunes to vngratefull fooles doe send,</L>
<L>As onely seeking to doe good: so we</L>
<L>(Though oft in vaine our <HI>bountie</HI> we doe spend)</L>
<L>To the vnthankfull must, as to the thankfull lend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Gods <HI>bounty's</HI> like to incense and perfume,</L>
<L>Cast on an heart inflam'd with holy <HI>zeale,</HI></L>
<L>Which praises vp, like cloudes of smoake doth sume,</L>
<L>And sweetest odours round about doth deale:</L>
<L><HI>Man's Bounty</HI> is like widowes cruse or meale,</L>
<L>Which spent vpon the <HI>Prophet</HI> growes to more,</L>
<L>Like Surgeons skill, which as he more doth heale,</L>
<L>Doth grow more cunning than he was before,</L>
<L>The diligent and bounteous hand want neuer store.)</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As many fruits doe faire encrease and grow,</L>
<L>Not so much by the nature of the ground,</L>
<L>As by the <HI>bounty,</HI> which from Heau'n doth flow,</L>
<L>And temperate aire that is about them found,</L>
<L>So all good <HI>Arts</HI> in noblest wits abound,</L>
<L>More by some <HI>Princes liberalitie,</HI></L>
<L>And high regard they haue of <HI>Muses</HI> sound,</L>
<L>Than their owne nature, strength, and industry,</L>
<L>Best friends to <HI>Arts</HI> are <HI>Bounty</HI> and <HI>Humanity.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="38" REF="25"/>
Should I but here recount the names of all,</L>
<L>Whom <HI>bountifull</HI> in holy Writ I find,</L>
<L>I of your patience should be prodigall,</L>
<L>And my short time for this discourse assign'd,</L>
<L>Let me their names vp in a bundle bind;</L>
<L>Which if you please to ope as sweetly smell,</L>
<L>As <HI>Camphires bush:</HI> my <HI>Muse</HI> is now inclin'd,</L>
<L>Of some prophane examples here to tell,</L>
<L>Which seeme in noble <HI>Bounty</HI> others to excell.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Than treasure <HI>Cyrus</HI> more his friends esteem'd,</L>
<L>Whereof he multitudes by <HI>bounty</HI> won:</L>
<L>And <HI>Alexander</HI> greatest glory deem'd,</L>
<L>By <HI>bounty</HI> neuer to be ouercome;</L>
<L>A King of <HI>Egypt</HI> thought it better done,</L>
<L>His subiects coffers, than his owne to fill:</L>
<L>When as <HI>Alphonsus</HI> heard <HI>Titus Vespasians</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Accounted that day lost, when for goodwill</L>
<L>He had giu'n nought; said, I ne're spent a day so ill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Behold! these fiue examples liue in one,</L>
<L>The <HI>bounteous Monarch,</HI> that our Scepter sways,</L>
<L>Esteemes his friends' boue gold, or precious stone,</L>
<L>And ouercomes eu'n all that him obay's,</L>
<L>By soueraigne <HI>Bounty,</HI> to's immortall praise,</L>
<L>No King so fills his subiects chests with gold,</L>
<L>His <HI>bounteous deeds</HI> in number passe his day's:</L>
<L>Ah! how then dare my niggard rimes be bold,</L>
<L>The sacred <HI>bounty</HI> of my Soueraigne to vnfold.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Who hoards not vp his wealth in Caue or Tower,</L>
<L>Nor into prisons darke condemnes his gold:</L>
<L>But as on him from heau'n all Blessings shower,</L>
<L>So are his to vs Subiects manifold:</L>
<L>As from thicke clouds, we numberlesse behold,</L>
<L>Large streames of fruitfull raine on earth to fall:</L>
<L>So is his largesse to his seruants told,</L>
<L>Who entring poore, returne rich from his hall,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Tagus</HI> golden sands, his hands are liberall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="39" REF="25"/>
Vouchsafe, oh <HI>bounteous Soueraigne!</HI> heare thy thrall,</L>
<L>After thy cloud, a subiects drop'd to sing;</L>
<L>Whom thou didst to deserued honour call,</L>
<L>And was in name and bountie as a <HI>King:</HI></L>
<L>Who in thy bounteous steps thee following,</L>
<L>Did from obscurity my <HI>Fortunes</HI> raise,</L>
<L>Without desert or my least offering,</L>
<L>He now in Heau'n his <HI>bounteous</HI> King doth praise,</L>
<L>As he with <HI>bounty</HI> honour'd him here all his day's.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And let vs all his <HI>bounteous</HI> praises sing,</L>
<L>Whose <HI>bounty</HI> vs from Hell and Death doth raise,</L>
<L>Our blessed <HI>Sauiour, Prophet, Priest,</HI> and <HI>King,</HI></L>
<L>Who here in <HI>bounteous deeds</HI> spent all his day's;</L>
<L>Casting out Deuills, sauing soules alway's,</L>
<L>Healing the sicke, giuing the blind their sight;</L>
<L>Mournes for our sins, for enemies he pray's;</L>
<L>Comforts the rich, and feeds the hungry wight,</L>
<L>And still in doing good, doth set his whole delight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>How could malicious heart of enuious man,</L>
<L>Consent to murther such a <HI>bounteous</HI> King?</L>
<L>Scourge, scorne, deride, despight him what they can,</L>
<L>Still in his bounteous deeds perseuering;</L>
<L>Yea when vnto the Crosse they him doe bring,</L>
<L><HI>Father they know not what they doe,</HI> he cry's;</L>
<L>And when his body hangs their torturing,</L>
<L>He to the Thiefe not Paradise denyes;</L>
<L>Thus doing good he liues: Thus doing good he dyes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>What doth the <HI>Lord of Life eternall dye?</HI></L>
<L>Which vnto vs eternall life doth giue;</L>
<L>See his large <HI>bounty,</HI> and <HI>benignity?</HI></L>
<L>Hee gaue his life for vs, that we might liue,</L>
<L>What heart of stone doth not here melt, or riue</L>
<L>But with his <HI>Life,</HI> his <HI>Bounty</HI> doth not end,</L>
<L>He by his Will, and Testament doth giue</L>
<L>Vs Heau'n, yea more the Comforter doth send,</L>
<L>With millions of <HI>Angells,</HI> on vs to attend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="40" REF="26"/>
Who can of this his <HI>Sauiours Bountie</HI> tast?</L>
<L>And to his members not be <HI>bountifull,</HI></L>
<L>If thou want wealth, and coine giue what thou hast,</L>
<L>And let our hearts be alwaies mercifull,</L>
<L>And like the fertile ground yeeld plentifull</L>
<L>Encrease, of all the seeds which thereon grow,</L>
<L>'Tis <HI>Bountie</HI> that doth fill our garner's full,</L>
<L>He sparing reapes, that sparingly doth sowe,</L>
<L>True <HI>Bounty's</HI> noble hand no want did euer know.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But ah too many couetous of Praise</L>
<L>And Glory doe by fraud and rapine spoile;</L>
<L>Other's, that they thereby there names may raise,</L>
<L>And some goods gotten by much care and toile,</L>
<L>Spend on their pleasures, and thereby beguile,</L>
<L>Their poore and needy neighbour of his right,</L>
<L>Drinking and surfetting in ease the while,</L>
<L>And spending frankly on some base delight,</L>
<L>Like Brutes are bountifull to their owne appetite.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Some onely by their <HI>Bountie</HI> seeke for fame,</L>
<L>And these are onely to <HI>Ambition</HI> free,</L>
<L>Some Patrons now aday's such Shepheards name,</L>
<L>To feed the Flocke, as loose and Idle Bee,</L>
<L>Wealth vnto wealth to adde they all agree:</L>
<L>Mo man respects the needy and the poore,</L>
<L>The emptie vessels, emptie still we see;</L>
<L>They that are full, to them is added more,</L>
<L>Dry <HI>hills want water,</HI> when the <HI>valley's swim</HI> with store.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As <HI>Knights</HI> which of the noble Order are</L>
<L>Of <HI>Garter,</HI> that they better may be knowne,</L>
<L>A golden <HI>George</HI> about their necke they weare,</L>
<L>Nor doe the same at any time lay downe,</L>
<L>Whereby their noblenesse should be vnknowne:</L>
<L>So <HI>Nobles</HI> alwaies weare <HI>Benignitie,</HI></L>
<L>Whereby whose <HI>Sonnes</HI> you are yee may be showne,</L>
<L>For nothing proues you <HI>Sonnes of the most High,</HI></L>
<L>More than your <HI>Bountie</HI> and true <HI>Liberalitie.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="41" REF="26"/>
But of <HI>salse bountie</HI> you doe vainely boast,</L>
<L>Delighting in vaine pastime, oyle and Wine,</L>
<L>And gluttons feed for glory to your cost,</L>
<L>Whil'st at your doores, the poore may sterue and pine,</L>
<L>You welcome such as you inuite to dine;</L>
<L>But scarce afford the poore scraps, at your gate;</L>
<L>Which shew that all your <HI>bountie</HI> is to Ioyne</L>
<L>Credit and Glory to your great estate,</L>
<L>And but for Crowes and Kites, or Daw's do lay a Baite.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>You for a million at a cast will play,</L>
<L>And hazard all your fortunes at a game,</L>
<L>And grudge not for one daintie bit to pay</L>
<L>A thousand, and then glory in the same,</L>
<L>With gold you tricke and trim vp some loose Dame,</L>
<L>The sinke that sucks vp all your <HI>Liberalitie,</HI></L>
<L>Thus lauish you to your eternall shame,</L>
<L>All that your Fathers got by their <HI>Frugalitie,</HI></L>
<L>And left to you to spend in <HI>bounteous hospitalitie.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Braue <HI>Alexanders</HI> deeds for ay commends</L>
<L>His wondrous confidence, and <HI>bountie</HI> rare;</L>
<L>Who dealing out amongst his faithfull friends,</L>
<L>Lands, houses, townes, he gold and all did share,</L>
<L>When one besought him wisely to forbeare,</L>
<L>For what, said he, alas! is left the <HI>King?</HI></L>
<L>New hopes of gaming more, said he, there are,</L>
<L>Thus on his fate and fortunes venturing</L>
<L>The Heau'ns propitious seem'd, to him, in eu'ry thing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But ah! poore Prince! thy <HI>hopes</HI> are all but vaine,</L>
<L>As were the <HI>Benefits</HI> thou didst expose;</L>
<L>But we are certaine of eternall <HI>gaine,</HI></L>
<L>If <HI>bounteously Gods</HI> blessings we dispose:</L>
<L>Ah! what is it if worldly things we loose!</L>
<L>And thereby gaine vs an <HI>Eternall Crowne,</HI></L>
<L>Which heau'nly <HI>Bountie</HI> layeth vp for those,</L>
<L>That their owne glory willingly lay downe,</L>
<L>And what they reape by <HI>Bountie bounteously</HI> haue sowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="42" REF="27"/>
Such all within most gloriously shall shine,</L>
<L>Their vestiments shall be of twined Gold;</L>
<L>They shall of Hony tast, and spiced Wine;</L>
<L>And all the Bridegroomes fruits both new and old,</L>
<L>He gently will such in his armes infold;</L>
<L>And satisfie their sense with pleasing smell,</L>
<L>No eare hath heard, no tongue hath euer told,</L>
<L>The <HI>Ioy</HI> and <HI>Bounty</HI> that with him doe dwell,</L>
<L>But more of these, where next of heau'nly <HI>Ioy</HI> I tell.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>MEDITAT. V.</HI> Of Spirituall and Heau'nly <HI>IOY.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>HOw should a heart opprest with worldly cares,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Spirituall inward Ioy</HI> now rightly sing;</L>
<L>Since none her knowes, but who her image beares,</L>
<L>And feeles the <HI>Spirits inward witnessing:</HI></L>
<L>All sacred stuffe I to this building bring</L>
<L>No helpe, but he that <HI>Abba Father</HI> cry's,</L>
<L>Can teach my <HI>Muse</HI> to touch this golden string,</L>
<L>I therefore here forbeare prophane supply's,</L>
<L>My Spirit wholly on the <HI>holy Spirit</HI> rely's.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Well, said the King, All worldly things are vaine,</L>
<L>And trauell which beneath the Sun he found</L>
<L>Compared to left drop or minutes gaine,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Spirituall Ioy</HI> did to his heart propound;</L>
<L>No reach of <HI>Wisards</HI> skill, no wit profound,</L>
<L>Is able this true <HI>Ioy</HI> to comprehend,</L>
<L>This Musicke wholly to the Saints doth sound,</L>
<L>The inward man can onely apprehend,</L>
<L>Sweet liuely <HI>Spirituall Ioy,</HI> which neuer shall haue end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="43" REF="27"/>
No <HI>Muses</HI> darling euer yet did dreame,</L>
<L>Of this sweet wind, which where it lists doth blow;</L>
<L>This onely is sweet <HI>Israels</HI> Singers theame,</L>
<L>Which he by heau'nly influence did show;</L>
<L>And then most, when the outward man brought low,</L>
<L>By paine of body, or by griefe of mind,</L>
<L>Did from his pen diuinest comforts flow,</L>
<L>Most heau'nly <HI>Ioy's,</HI> which he was wont to find,</L>
<L>To grow more strong within, as he without declind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh <HI>Ioy</HI> of ioy's? vnspeakeable delight,</L>
<L>Eu'n when our soules the powers of hell doe shake,</L>
<L>And vs with Iustice and due vengeance fright,</L>
<L>When as our guilty conscience is awake,</L>
<L>That all with terrour tremble, horrour quake;</L>
<L>That then our gentle <HI>beame</HI> of heau'nly <HI>Grace,</HI></L>
<L>Not onely shall from vs this horrour take,</L>
<L>But in <HI>Loues armes</HI> vs in an instant place,</L>
<L>They onely know this <HI>Ioy,</HI> that haue beene in this case.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>If euer I receiued strength and skill</L>
<L>From Heau'n, to scale the hill of <HI>contemplation,</HI></L>
<L>I now doe hope Gods <HI>gracious Spirit</HI> will,</L>
<L>Me fill with Ioy for his sweet meditation;</L>
<L>Oh, <HI>blessed Spirit!</HI> who by sweet inspiration,</L>
<L>Directest eu'ry <HI>holy Prophets quill,</HI></L>
<L>Enlighten mine, by heau'ns illumination,</L>
<L>That most diuine sweet <HI>Ioy's</HI> it may distill</L>
<L>Into the Readers heart, and Mine with comfort fill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>No tongue could euer tell, no heart conceiue,</L>
<L>Therefore no Art is able to define</L>
<L>What is the <HI>inward Ioy</HI> which we receiue,</L>
<L>By <HI>peace of conscience,</HI> and <HI>Grace diuine:</HI></L>
<L>But sure it is, that speciall marke or signe,</L>
<L>Which on our soules the <HI>holy Spirit of Grace</HI></L>
<L>Most gently doth imprint, and liuely line,</L>
<L>Whereby we doe behold Gods cheerefull face,</L>
<L>And spiritually feele, our <HI>Bridegroomes</HI> sweet embrace.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="44" REF="28"/>
There is a <HI>naturall</HI> and <HI>carnall Ioy,</HI></L>
<L>Besides this <HI>inward Ioy spirituall,</HI></L>
<L>By one we common blessings here enioy,</L>
<L>By th'other we in Sin and errour fall;</L>
<L>Those be partakers of <HI>Ioy naturall,</HI></L>
<L>That health of body haue, and worldly store,</L>
<L>The <HI>carnall Ioy</HI> we sinfull pleasures call,</L>
<L>Excesse of meate, and wine, Lips of a whore,</L>
<L>And all mans vaine delights 'gainst rule of heau'n lore.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These <HI>Ioy's,</HI> which with false pleasures vs deceiue,</L>
<L>Are not of kin to <HI>Ioy spirituall;</HI></L>
<L>For that they alway's doe our hearts bereaue</L>
<L>Of inward <HI>Ioyes</HI> pure food <HI>Angelicall;</HI></L>
<L>Gods goodnesse is th'efficient cause of all,</L>
<L>And though each person in the <HI>Trinitie,</HI></L>
<L>May seeme to haue a working seuerall,</L>
<L>Yet all in one, and one in all agree,</L>
<L>With <HI>Ioy</HI> here to begin mans true felicitee.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There many causes are materiall,</L>
<L>Why we this <HI>inward Ioy</HI> in vs should haue▪</L>
<L>Gods <HI>freest grace,</HI> which doth most surely call,</L>
<L>All those that he elected hath to saue;</L>
<L>The <HI>Peace of conscience,</HI> which <HI>Ioy</HI> vs gaue,</L>
<L>And eke the <HI>Ioy</HI> of our <HI>Sanctification:</HI></L>
<L>Whereby eu'n heauens inheritance we craue,</L>
<L>And certainly expect <HI>glorification,</HI></L>
<L>And are inuited guests to heau'ns <HI>participation.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As are Gods gifts and graces infinite,</L>
<L>So causes are of <HI>Ioy spirituall;</HI></L>
<L>It fills my soule with infinite delight,</L>
<L>When all his benefits to mind I call;</L>
<L>But none like this that's <HI>Sonne</HI> should saue vs all;</L>
<L>By that great secret of his Incarnation,</L>
<L>Which made the <HI>Babe</HI> into <HI>Ioy's passion</HI> fall,</L>
<L>At <HI>blessed Mothers</HI> heau'nly Salutation,</L>
<L>And made blind <HI>Simeons</HI> soule, reioyce in his Saluation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="45" REF="28"/>
This made the <HI>Mother</HI> of the <HI>Babe</HI> to sing,</L>
<L>And her sweet little <HI>Lord</HI> to magnifie</L>
<L>Her <HI>Sauiour,</HI> which shee in her armes did bring;</L>
<L>This made in heau'nly Host such melody,</L>
<L>When newes was brought of his <HI>Natiuity;</HI></L>
<L>Oh <HI>Ioy of Ioy's!</HI> to you is borne this day</L>
<L>A <HI>Sauiour,</HI> God from all eternitie:</L>
<L>This made the Wise-men from the East to stray,</L>
<L>And offer to him gifts, that in a cradle lay.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This made the holy King, propheticall,</L>
<L>Though many pleasant Lay's to Harpe hee sing,</L>
<L>Straine none so high, and so patheticall,</L>
<L>As those of his <HI>Sonne, Sauiour, Lord,</HI> and <HI>King:</HI></L>
<L>Oh then each stroake, hee strikes, to heau'n doth ring.</L>
<L>His heart reioyceth; and his tongue is glad,</L>
<L>Such Ioy doth hope of resurrection bring,</L>
<L>That though his flesh be with corruption clad,</L>
<L>His heart shall neuer faint, nor soule be euer sad.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>We for this <HI>hope,</HI> it count exceeding <HI>Ioy</HI></L>
<L>When we doe fall, on many sore temptations,</L>
<L>And when afflictions most abound, we <HI>Ioy</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Trialls, Sufferings,</HI> and <HI>Tribulations:</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Angells</HI> in their holy habitations,</L>
<L>At our conuersions wondrous <HI>Ioy</HI> receiue,</L>
<L>What passing <HI>Ioy</HI> will be and delectations,</L>
<L>When all the <HI>members</HI> to their <HI>head</HI> shall cleaue,</L>
<L>And for short Sorrowes, endlesse recompence receiue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>My <HI>Muse</HI> her selfe eu'n out of breath now fly's,</L>
<L>Rais'd vp so high by <HI>Ioy Spirituall;</HI></L>
<L>Yet by <HI>Ioy's obiects,</HI> she must higher rise,</L>
<L>To <HI>Father, Sonne,</HI> the <HI>Holy Ghost,</HI> and all:</L>
<L>What greater <HI>Ioy,</HI> than on the <HI>Father</HI> call;</L>
<L>And how did <HI>Abraham</HI> reioyce to see?</L>
<L>The day of his <HI>Redeemers</HI> nuptiall;</L>
<L>Ah what more <HI>Ioy</HI> vnspeakeable can bee?</L>
<L>Than feele the <HI>holy Spirit of Grace</HI> to dwell in thee.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="46" REF="29"/>
Oh happy Host, such guests to entertaine,</L>
<L>With <HI>peace of conscience,</HI> their continuall feast,</L>
<L>Open you euerlasting doores againe,</L>
<L>Open, <HI>The King</HI> stands knocking ready prest;</L>
<L>The <HI>King of Glory,</HI> to come in and rest:</L>
<L>Downe from the fig-tree speedily then come,</L>
<L>And entertaine thy <HI>Sauiour</HI> in thy brest,</L>
<L>To day Saluation is to thee come home,</L>
<L>With <HI>Faith, Hope, Loue,</HI> and <HI>Truth</HI> perfume thou eu'ry rom.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For without these, true <HI>Ioy</HI> will neuer stay,</L>
<L>With her must all the <HI>heau'nly Graces</HI> bide,</L>
<L><HI>Long-suffering, Mercy, Peace,</HI> desire to <HI>Pray,</HI></L>
<L>God these hath ioyn'd, no man may them diuide,</L>
<L>False <HI>Ioy's</HI> without these into vs may slide,</L>
<L>As stony ground, which did receiue the seed;</L>
<L>Did flourish faire, and Branch on eu'ry side;</L>
<L>But this did <HI>Faith,</HI> but <HI>temporary</HI> breed,</L>
<L>And we this but a <HI>momentany Ioy</HI> areed.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There are besides this friendly seeming <HI>Ioy,</HI></L>
<L>Other that are professed enemy's;</L>
<L>As those which worldly happinesse enioy,</L>
<L>And liue in pleasures, ease, and jollity's:</L>
<L>Against these th'author of true ioy reply's,</L>
<L>Woe vnto you that laugh, for you shall waile,</L>
<L>Lament and howle for your iniquity's,</L>
<L>When Iudgement comes, and all mens hearts shal faile,</L>
<L>What then shall all your worldly pleasures you auaile.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Another <HI>Ioy</HI> against true <HI>Ioy</HI> I find,</L>
<L>When in true cause of Ioy we so delight,</L>
<L>That we omit from Lusts, to clense our mind,</L>
<L>And valiantly 'gainst base affections fight,</L>
<L>Ah! how can <HI>heau'nly true Ioy</HI> take delight,</L>
<L>Amongst our grosse corruptions here to dwell,</L>
<L>Sure this <HI>Reioycing</HI> is not good and right,</L>
<L>A little <HI>Leuen</HI> makes the <HI>whole lump</HI> smell,</L>
<L>Our boastings vaine: This water's not from liuing well.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="47" REF="29"/>
There is a counterfett, and feign'd delight,</L>
<L>Shew'd in the face, but comes not from the heart,</L>
<L>Whom I may call, <HI>A merry Hypocrite,</HI></L>
<L>Others reioyce so in their owne desert,</L>
<L>In their redemption they will beare a part:</L>
<L>These are the men, whom workes must iustifie,</L>
<L>Alas! poore wretch! remember what thou art,</L>
<L>And whence thou hast receiued thy supply,</L>
<L>And thou shalt soone from this thy <HI>proud reioycing</HI> slye.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Proud slesh and bloud! that dares of merits boast,</L>
<L>When in thy Makers presence thou do'st stand,</L>
<L>And hopest to regaine what <HI>Adam</HI> lost,</L>
<L>By thine <HI>inherent Iustice:</HI> thou do'st band,</L>
<L>Directly 'gainst thy Makers glory; and,</L>
<L>Seek'st to reioyce in Iustice of thine owne,</L>
<L>Presume not 'boue thy strength to vnderstand,</L>
<L>But merry be and glad in <HI>God</HI> alone,</L>
<L>Who is all <HI>Worthinesse,</HI> but in thy selfe is none.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As those which vaine applause of men regard,</L>
<L>And at their doing almes a trumpet blow;</L>
<L>Gaine onely praise of men, for their reward,</L>
<L>But <HI>God</HI> no such good-workes will euer know;</L>
<L>So those in whom these boasting merits flow,</L>
<L>And in their meritorious workes delight,</L>
<L>God neuer them doth this sound comfort show,</L>
<L>They may awhile seeme goodly in mans sight,</L>
<L>But neuer feele true inward <HI>Ioy</HI> and sound delight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As those which onely see the Stars and Moone,</L>
<L>But neuer saw faire <HI>Phaebus</HI> glorious light,</L>
<L>Beleeue no cleerer lights haue euer shone;</L>
<L>Than those faire Lamps, which doe adorne the night;</L>
<L>So those that neuer knew this <HI>true delight,</HI></L>
<L>Those <HI>heau'nly Ioy's</HI> to holy Saints confin'd,</L>
<L>Thinke there most <HI>Ioy,</HI> where flesh doth most delight:</L>
<L>But tast they once sweet inward <HI>Ioy</HI> of mind,</L>
<L>In all these <HI>worldly Ioy's</HI> they no content can find.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="48" REF="30"/>
This <HI>heau'nly Ioy</HI> by no similitude,</L>
<L>In Heau'n or Earth can truly be exprest,</L>
<L>Yet is shee felt; as oft in simple rude,</L>
<L>As in the most profound, deepe learned breast;</L>
<L>None know her, till they be of her possest.</L>
<L>For as we feele the winde when it doth blow,</L>
<L>But whence it comes, or where it meanes to rest,</L>
<L>No wit of man ere able was to show;</L>
<L>So many feele these <HI>Ioy's,</HI> but know not whence they flow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As in the <HI>Incarnations mysteries,</HI></L>
<L>The blessed Virgin ouer-shadowed</L>
<L>By th' <HI>Holy Ghost,</HI> and power of the most High;</L>
<L>Perceiu'd her fruitfull womb replenished,</L>
<L>But knew not whence, till th' <HI>Angell</HI> it aread;</L>
<L>So wee this <HI>Babe</HI> of <HI>Ioy spirituall,</HI></L>
<L>Oft feele in vs most liuely quickened;</L>
<L>But know not how, nor whence the same doth fall,</L>
<L>Till that same <HI>Spirit of Truth,</HI> to vs reuealeth all.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And as no creature able is of man,</L>
<L>The <HI>Spirit</HI> to discerne, but man alone,</L>
<L>So of this <HI>Spirituall Ioy,</HI> no spirit can</L>
<L>Conclude, but this sweet spirituall holy One:</L>
<L>Some would it liken to the glorious Sunne,</L>
<L>Which by his liuely beames doth Life inspire;</L>
<L>Where they an obiect fit to light vpon,</L>
<L>But I forbeare too nicely to inquire,</L>
<L>And rather in mine heart, to feele her <HI>beames</HI> desire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh <HI>Sunne of Light! Bright Glory</HI> of thy <HI>Sire,</HI></L>
<L>Who when thou left'st the earth, thy Spirit didst send,</L>
<L>Into our hearts sweet comforts to inspire,</L>
<L>And with vs to abide till world's last end:</L>
<L>Some good examples to my <HI>Muse</HI> commend,</L>
<L>Of holy men, which tooke so much delight</L>
<L>In heau'nly <HI>Ioy's,</HI> they holy them intend,</L>
<L>And banish all vaine worldly pleasures quite</L>
<L>Shining like <HI>glorious Lamps</HI> in worlds obscurest night.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="49" REF="30"/>
This <HI>inward heate,</HI> this <HI>holy heau'nly fire,</HI></L>
<L>Most what concealed vnder ashes ly's</L>
<L>Which one, till into flames they doe respire,</L>
<L>At home more easie, than aborad descry's:</L>
<L>Because it selfe within best testify's,</L>
<L>In <HI>Abraham</HI> appear'd this holy flame;</L>
<L>When as he saw his <HI>Sauiour</HI> with his eyes</L>
<L>Who of his blessed seed long after came,</L>
<L>For <HI>Abram</HI> saw <HI>Christs day</HI> and ioyed in the same.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Vp <HI>Miriam</HI> vp, thou merily canst sing;</L>
<L>Now through the Red Sea thou art safely past,</L>
<L>Hereby our Baptisme then prefiguring,</L>
<L>That when <HI>Repentance</HI> vs with teares hath wash't,</L>
<L>With <HI>Ioy</HI> wee <HI>Egypts Bondage</HI> of should cast:</L>
<L>But neuer did more <HI>Ioyfull musicke</HI> sound,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Dauids:</HI> when he of this <HI>Ioy</HI> did tast,</L>
<L>Restore mee to those wonted <HI>Ioy's</HI> I found,</L>
<L>And euer let thy <HI>holy Spirit</HI> in me abound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh blessed <HI>Bridegroome</HI> of the fairest <HI>Bride,</HI></L>
<L>How often when shee seeketh thee by night,</L>
<L>Doest thou thy <HI>Ioyfull presence</HI> from her hide?</L>
<L>That wanting, shee in thee may more delight:</L>
<L>How oft againe, when thou do'st her inuite?</L>
<L>Rise my belou'd, and ope to mee the doore,</L>
<L>Such is her nicenesse, and her sluggish sprite;</L>
<L>Shee will not rise to let thee in, before</L>
<L>Thou thence art gone; And then thy losse shee doth deplore.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These are the <HI>apples, odours, nuts,</HI> and <HI>wine,</HI></L>
<L>Which comfort her, when shee is sicke of <HI>Loue;</HI></L>
<L>These <HI>Christs embraces</HI> that doe her entwine,</L>
<L>The <HI>kisses</HI> which he giues his <HI>Turtle Doue:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Milke, spice, pomegranats,</HI> which shee so doth loue,</L>
<L>All these are <HI>inward Ioy's</HI> the <HI>Bride</HI> hath here,</L>
<L>Whereof she with the <HI>Bridegroomes</HI> friends doth proue;</L>
<L>And eates and drinkes with <HI>Ioy</HI> and <HI>merry cheere,</HI></L>
<L>Yea drinkes abundantly with her <HI>beloued deare.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="50" REF="31"/>
This was the <HI>Ioy,</HI> that him was set before,</L>
<L>That did endure the <HI>Crosse,</HI> despise the <HI>shame,</HI></L>
<L>And Lord of all, became low, naked, pore,</L>
<L>Enduring death vs to excuse from blame!</L>
<L>His <HI>Martyrs</HI> and <HI>Apostles</HI> in the same</L>
<L>Suffrings and crosses him haue followed;</L>
<L>And trode the <HI>Wine-presse</HI> as their order came,</L>
<L>Where some in scorching flames more Ioy's haue red,</L>
<L>Than wearied Limbs could find, in softest downy bed.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This 'twas the <HI>Kingly Prophet</HI> so admir'd,</L>
<L>When loathing all worlds pompe and glory vaine,</L>
<L>He this one onely thing of God desir'd,</L>
<L>For euer in his <HI>Temple</HI> to remaine,</L>
<L>To view the Beautie of that <HI>heau'nly traine:</HI></L>
<L>This made him leaue his purple Crowne and Throne,</L>
<L>And in a linnen <HI>Ephod</HI> dance amaine:</L>
<L>For this would <HI>Constantine</HI> be rather one</L>
<L>Of <HI>Christ his members,</HI> then the <HI>Empires</HI> head alone.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But why seeke I for witnesses without,</L>
<L>Since 'tis the <HI>Spirit within</HI> that testify's,</L>
<L>Our Soule that without wauering or doubt,</L>
<L>With <HI>Peace of Conscience, Abba Father Cry's:</HI></L>
<L>Vnto whose Soule this <HI>Spirit</HI> eke reply's,</L>
<L>Be glad and Ioyfull, I am thy saluation</L>
<L>Be not afraid-My <HI>Grace</HI> shall thee suffice</L>
<L>To conquer <HI>Hell;</HI> And to resist temptation,</L>
<L>And yeeld the soundest <HI>Ioy</HI> in greatest tribulation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I will make glad thy soule, delight thine heart,</L>
<L>And with a cheerefull countenance will smile,</L>
<L>For <HI>I am thine</HI> and <HI>mine</HI> againe thou art;</L>
<L>And though afflictions here thee square and file,</L>
<L>No power in Earth or Hell shall thee beguile</L>
<L>Of those sweet <HI>Ioy's,</HI> which are for thee prepar'd:</L>
<L>Oh tarry thou my leasure but a while,</L>
<L>And thy petitions all, I will regard,</L>
<L>Delight in mee, I am thy hope, and iust reward.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="51" REF="31"/>
Oh! who can heare these Ioyous inuitations,</L>
<L>These blessed promises, and yet complaine,</L>
<L>That hee's afraid of crosse, or tribulations:</L>
<L>Oh! neuer let these worldly pleasures vaine,</L>
<L>Make me so great a looser for their gaine;</L>
<L>And let me here all worldly griefes endure,</L>
<L>Lord onely free me from eternall paine,</L>
<L>This inward <HI>Ioy</HI> shall euer me assure,</L>
<L>And on thy merits I in all, will rest secure.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Who would not rather couet there to dwell,</L>
<L>Where <HI>fulnesse is of Ioy</HI> for euermore,</L>
<L>Than in false vaine delights, which leads to Hell</L>
<L>Voluptuous Diet, flatt'rings of a Whore;</L>
<L>I rather had with <HI>Dauid</HI> keepe a dore</L>
<L>Where inward <HI>Ioy,</HI> may in my soule abound;</L>
<L>Than swim in pleasures and preferments store,</L>
<L>In Princes Courts, where vaine delights are found,</L>
<L>Which like faire flowers fade, and quickly fal to ground.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But I confesse, this prouerb true I find,</L>
<L>That where <HI>Gods Church</HI> is raising, there to build,</L>
<L>His <HI>Chappell</HI> is the <HI>Deuill</HI> most inclin'd,</L>
<L>And where best seed is sowne in Ground well till'd,</L>
<L>He with most <HI>tares</HI> and <HI>weeds</HI> it alway's fill'd:</L>
<L><HI>Vaine pleasures,</HI> are his <HI>tares,</HI> true <HI>Ioy's</HI> our <HI>wheate,</HI></L>
<L>Till haruest both together grow in field,</L>
<L>Then will the <HI>Lord of Haruest</HI> surely beat,</L>
<L>The cockle from pure corne, at his owne board to eate.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Fountaine</HI> of <HI>Ioy!</HI> oh set thy whole delight;</L>
<L>Into thy Lawes and Statutes to enquire;</L>
<L>To meditate thereon both day and night,</L>
<L>My soule than Gold doth more these <HI>Ioy's</HI> desire.</L>
<L>Let others honour, wealth, and wine admire;</L>
<L>Lift, Lord, on me thy louing countenance,</L>
<L>Thy <HI>louing fauour,</HI> shall my Soule raise higher,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Princes</HI> highest <HI>fauours</HI> can aduance,</L>
<L>To heau'nly <HI>spirituall wealth,</HI> not subiect vnto chance.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="52" REF="32"/>
In holy Writ, I many places find,</L>
<L>From whence doe flow these <HI>Ioy's spirituall,</HI></L>
<L>But no where faster, than within my mind,</L>
<L>Oh Lord! Thou know'st; not I; from whence they fall:</L>
<L>God of all <HI>Peace,</HI> and <HI>Ioy perpetuall;</HI></L>
<L>Let not my <HI>Ioy A temporary</HI> proue,</L>
<L>But with her in mine heart thy <HI>Graces</HI> all</L>
<L>Infuse, <HI>Faith, Mercy, Patience, Peace,</HI> and <HI>Loue;</HI></L>
<L>To passe by things below, and seeke for things aboue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Of endlesse <HI>Ioy</HI> how should I make an end?</L>
<L>My <HI>Muse</HI> is neuer weary of delight;</L>
<L>Since I this <HI>Meditation</HI> did intend,</L>
<L>I neuer scarce could sleepe by day or night.</L>
<L>So doth the pleasing matter me inuite;</L>
<L>So full of <HI>rimes,</HI> and so the <HI>numbers</HI> run:</L>
<L>That I in shorter time haue finish't quite,</L>
<L>This tast of <HI>Ioy,</HI> than I haue earst begun</L>
<L>Some other <HI>Graces:</HI> But my hower-glasse hath done.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="32"/>
<P>THE BRIDES ORNAMENTS, <HI>Viz.</HI> Fiue Diuine and Morall MEDITATIONS.</P>
<P>1. Prudence. 2. Obedience. 3. Meekenesse. 4. Gods Word. 5. Prayer.</P>
<Q><BIBL>IOB 28. 28.</BIBL>
<HI>The feare of the Lord is wisdome, and to depart from euill is vnderstanding.</HI></Q>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM STANSBY. 1625.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="33"/>
<HEAD>TO MY MOST TRVE, WOR∣THY, LOVING FRIEND, AND dearest Brother, RICHARD CRA∣KANTHORPE, Doctor of Diui∣nitie, and one of his Maiesties Chaplens in Ordinarie.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>Ot <HI>Nature, Order,</HI> or <HI>Affinity</HI></L>
<L>Can <HI>Friendships sacred knot</HI> so surely tye</L>
<L>As <HI>choice:</HI> For euer there we find the <HI>ground</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Loue</HI> and <HI>Friendship</HI> most entirely sound;</L>
<L>As their Desires are like, so one there end,</L>
<L>Which is to be, and haue a faithfull friend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I, that vnto mine owne defects am conscious,</L>
<L>Of such an honour durst not be ambitious,</L>
<L>Tell thou wert pleas'd to call mee Friend and Brother,</L>
<L>(I know not that thou deign'st it any other)</L>
<L>Wherefore whil'st <HI>Time</HI> Life to my <HI>Lines</HI> shall giue,</L>
<L>Our <HI>Friendships memory</HI> in them shall liue,</L>
<L>Who of true <HI>Friendship</HI> know no other end,</L>
<L>Than here to haue and bee</L>
</LG>
<P><HI>A</HI> faithfull Friend.</P>
<P>ROBERT AYLET.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="33"/>
<HEAD>THE BRIDES ORNAMENTS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. I. <HI>Of</HI> WISDOME <HI>and</HI> PRVDENCE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HE first degree to <HI>Wisdome</HI> is the misse</L>
<L>Of <HI>Folly:</HI> For as <HI>Darknesse</HI> the priuation</L>
<L>Is of <HI>Lights</HI> Being, But no Being is,</L>
<L>So <HI>Folly</HI> is of <HI>wise illumination:</HI></L>
<L>And as in <HI>Chaos</HI> rude, at first Creation</L>
<L>There was all <HI>Darknesse</HI> by the want of <HI>Light:</HI></L>
<L>So in all men before their renouation</L>
<L>Are <HI>Folly's</HI> mists, and errours blackest night,</L>
<L>Till there the <HI>Spirit moue,</HI> which all things doth inlight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>Poets</HI> which did wondrously transcend</L>
<L>In making <HI>Mystery's</HI> by <HI>Fictions</HI> plaine,</L>
<L>All other <HI>Graces</HI> as diuine commend,</L>
<L>But <HI>Wisdome</HI> they to be a <HI>Goddesse</HI> faine;</L>
<L><HI>Minerva,</HI> who proceedeth from the braine</L>
<L>Of <HI>Iupiter;</HI> whom they the <HI>Mistris</HI> hight</L>
<L>Of all the <HI>Graces</HI> and the <HI>Muses</HI> traine,</L>
<L>To whom shee oft descends for her delight,</L>
<L>Weary'd with toile of <HI>Gouernment,</HI> and <HI>Martiall fight.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus her of <HI>Warre, Peace, Politie,</HI> and <HI>Arts</HI></L>
<L>They <HI>Goddesse</HI> make, as if they should her call</L>
<L>The <HI>Wisdome God</HI> the <HI>Father</HI> thus imparts</L>
<L>Vnto the <HI>Sonne,</HI> to make rule, order all;</L>
<L>With <HI>God</HI> the <HI>Father</HI> Coessentiall,</L>
<L>As all his <HI>Attributes, Power, Truth,</HI> and <HI>Loue,</HI></L>
<L>For on the <HI>Persons Consubstantiall</HI></L>
<L>No <HI>accident</HI> can fall or thence remoue,</L>
<L>This Soules faint eye conceiues of <HI>Wisdome</HI> from aboue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="56" REF="34"/>
Which is vnto my <HI>minds</HI> obscured <HI>eye,</HI></L>
<L>As to my <HI>Body's Sunne</HI> in Firmament,</L>
<L>The farther off, the easier to descry,</L>
<L>For neerenesse breedeth but astonishment,</L>
<L>Oh glorious <HI>Wisdome, Sun</HI> most orient;</L>
<L>Into my soule, with <HI>Folly</HI> clouded shine,</L>
<L>Some clearer <HI>beames</HI> of wisdome excellent,</L>
<L>The whil'st I sing these radiant rayes of thine,</L>
<L>Which make a <HI>mortall</HI> wight seeme gloriously <HI>diuine.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>What and how great is wisdomes heau'nly skill,</L>
<L>No heart of man is able to conceiue,</L>
<L>Much lesse expresse by any tongue or quill,</L>
<L>For none but <HI>Wisdome, wisdome</HI> can perceiue:</L>
<L>The cause vnknowne of nothing shee doth leaue,</L>
<L>A <HI>Numen</HI> of such wondrous excellence,</L>
<L>Shee doth no <HI>good</HI> but from her selfe receiue;</L>
<L>Being her owne <HI>end, ayme,</HI> and <HI>recompence,</HI></L>
<L>No <HI>good</HI> in Heau'n or Earth, but flow's from <HI>Sapience.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And therefore call'd the proper <HI>Good of Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Which though to <HI>Men</HI> and <HI>Angells</HI> hee dispence</L>
<L>In wise proportion, yet from him doth moue</L>
<L>All wisdome, and to him hath reference;</L>
<L>For as in <HI>Power</HI> so in <HI>Sapience,</HI></L>
<L>He doth all other heau'nly <HI>Powers</HI> transcend,</L>
<L>For <HI>Wisdome</HI> Ground is of <HI>Omnipotence,</HI></L>
<L>And as we <HI>Mortalls</HI> on her <HI>hests</HI> attend,</L>
<L>So neerer io diuine perfection we ascend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Such is true <HI>Wisdom's</HI> glory, that eu'n they</L>
<L>Seeme much to doubt, who doe her most admire;</L>
<L>Whither we properly possesse her may,</L>
<L>And by continuall industry acquire;</L>
<L>Or that the Heau'ns her secretly inspire:</L>
<L>In briefe, no price or gold can her obtaine,</L>
<L>Shee seemes to be some flame of heau'nly fire</L>
<L>In <HI>Adam</HI> breath'd, before by <HI>Folly</HI> slaine,</L>
<L>Which therefore we must seeke to haue from heau'n againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="57" REF="34"/>
Schooles her to be the <HI>knowledge</HI> doe define</L>
<L>Of things <HI>diuine,</HI> and <HI>humane,</HI> which in breast</L>
<L>Of <HI>Mortalls,</HI> if it pure and liuely shine</L>
<L>Makes him, like God, vnmou'd and stable rest:</L>
<L>For as no chance of <HI>Fortune</HI> can molest</L>
<L>The <HI>Power</HI> diuine, So <HI>wisemen</HI> doe enioy</L>
<L>Within themselues, by <HI>Wisdome, Peace,</HI> and <HI>Rest;</HI></L>
<L>Nothing that is without can them annoy,</L>
<L>All seeming Miseries giue place to Inward Ioy.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet falls this <HI>Wisdome</HI> short of that Diuine,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Adam</HI> did possesse before his fall:</L>
<L>And as Sun-beames through clouds, so doth she shine</L>
<L>Through our corruptions, scarse discern'd at all,</L>
<L>Wee <HI>common</HI> and more <HI>exquisite</HI> her call;</L>
<L>That see things that are past, and things in sight,</L>
<L>This things which in succeeding times may fall;</L>
<L>Wee her, as shee guides mens affayres aright,</L>
<L>Call <HI>Prudence;</HI> Wisdome, as shee doth in God delight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Wisdome</HI> and <HI>Prudence</HI> in an humane breast,</L>
<L>Are one same <HI>Grace,</HI> though diuers by relation:</L>
<L><HI>Wisdome</HI> referres to God, <HI>Prudence</HI> doth rest,</L>
<L>Most in a wise and vpright moderation</L>
<L>Of <HI>States</HI> and <HI>Men</HI> by <HI>Law's</HI> administration:</L>
<L>By <HI>Wisdome</HI> here we see the <HI>life of Grace,</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Prudence</HI> in a <HI>ciuill conuersation;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Prudence</HI> amongst the heathen had a place,</L>
<L>True <HI>heau'nly wisdome</HI> only <HI>Gods elect</HI> doth grace.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This heau'nly <HI>wisdome,</HI> whereby we conuerse</L>
<L>With God, and take delight in holy things,</L>
<L>Doth our affections all, and wills peruerse</L>
<L>Set right, and neere diuine perfection brings;</L>
<L>Shee first, like good <HI>Musitian,</HI> tunes the strings,</L>
<L>And then sends forth a most harmonious sound:</L>
<L>First lifts our Soules to heau'n vpon her wings,</L>
<L>Next orders all by <HI>Prudence</HI> on the ground,</L>
<L>Like Leach who ere he others cure, himselfe makes sound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="58" REF="35"/>
She first <HI>within</HI> in order sets the heart,</L>
<L>Next is for <HI>outward</HI> things most prouident,</L>
<L>No <HI>Grace</HI> more <HI>Good</HI> to <HI>Mortalls</HI> doth impart,</L>
<L>Nor none more <HI>euills</HI> here on earth preuent,</L>
<L>She shew's her <HI>inward Graces</HI> God hath lent;</L>
<L>By outward manners, habit, graue attire;</L>
<L>Few words, pure hands, in all such complement,</L>
<L>Such gesture publike, and in her retire,</L>
<L>As all her for a heau'nly patterne doe admire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But most of all a <HI>wiseman</HI> striues to tame</L>
<L>Both in himselfe, and others Sin and Lust:</L>
<L>For hee that Good from Ill discern's, doth blame</L>
<L>False varnish't show's defil'd with inward rust:</L>
<L>He <HI>Pride, Pompe, Boasting, Scorne</HI> away doth thrust,</L>
<L>And from a pure <HI>Serenity</HI> of mind</L>
<L>A paterne draw's of Life most quiet, iust;</L>
<L>Far from opinions false, and errour blind,</L>
<L>And guides at sterne, as in a calme, so in the wind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In Warre most valiant, in Iudgement iust;</L>
<L>Ill, vnto Good, things hurtfull, turn's to sound;</L>
<L>Will's still the same, because the best, no Gust</L>
<L>Of fate oppresleth him, if Wealth abound,</L>
<L>Or Pouertie, he still the same is found;</L>
<L>And doth with pleasing <HI>Constancy</HI> endure</L>
<L>All Fortunes changes, which doe others wound;</L>
<L>True, innocent, sincere, iust, simple, pure,</L>
<L>And as his <HI>Life,</HI> his <HI>Death</HI> is ioyfull, sweet, secure.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>Poets</HI> faine that in the <HI>golden Age,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Graue, wise, experienc'd</HI> men bare all the sway,</L>
<L>And the <HI>vnexpert,</HI> young, not yet growne sage,</L>
<L>To <HI>learne Law's rules</HI> first practis'd to obey,</L>
<L>For <HI>Prudence</HI> all by <HI>leuell</HI> orders ay,</L>
<L>And by a long <HI>Experience</HI> doth discerne,</L>
<L>How she prouide for future changes may,</L>
<L>By <HI>precept,</HI> and <HI>example</HI> much we learne;</L>
<L>But that imprints most deepe, which doth our selues concern.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="59" REF="35"/>
<HI>Examples, Precepts,</HI> and <HI>Experience,</HI></L>
<L>Are euer ready at a <HI>Wisemans</HI> hand,</L>
<L>To teach him <HI>Iudgement, Counsell, Prouidence,</HI></L>
<L>Of which we alway's here in need doe stand:</L>
<L>By <HI>Counsell</HI> we the Grounds doe vnderstand</L>
<L>Of things we ought to doe, or leaue vndone:</L>
<L><HI>Iudgement</HI> our <HI>Wills</HI> and <HI>Senses</HI> doth command,</L>
<L>What things we ought embrace, and what to shun,</L>
<L>And <HI>Prouidence</HI> prouides for things that are to come.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I praise not here that cunning <HI>Politie,</HI></L>
<L>Which maketh of anothers <HI>Folly,</HI> gaine;</L>
<L>This comes of <HI>Malice, Guile,</HI> and <HI>Subtiltie,</HI></L>
<L>Which generous braue <HI>Prudence</HI> doth disdaine:</L>
<L>Such alway's euill counsell entertaine,</L>
<L>The <HI>Apes of Prudence, Reasons</HI> deprauation,</L>
<L>Whose <HI>minds</HI> (as <HI>hands</HI> grow hard by taking paine)</L>
<L>Are by base plots, and subtill magination</L>
<L>Inured vnto others wrongs and supplantation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As <HI>Quicknesse</HI> wit, As <HI>Soundnesse</HI> memory,</L>
<L><HI>Graue lookes the Face,</HI> and <HI>Plainnesse speech</HI> commend;</L>
<L>So <HI>Iudgements</HI> praise is in <HI>Equalitie,</HI></L>
<L>Without least doing wrong to Foe or Friend:</L>
<L>And as salt sauours, so doth Iudgement bend</L>
<L>Eu'n all our <HI>words, thoughts, workes,</HI> to good or ill;</L>
<L>Without this <HI>Iudgement, Prudence</HI> doth intend</L>
<L>Nothing; for shee is <HI>Mistresse</HI> of her <HI>Will,</HI></L>
<L>Which she with all her power labours to fulfill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Counsell</HI> and <HI>Iudgement</HI> are the very eyes</L>
<L>And <HI>Lamps</HI> here, to direct a prudent mind;</L>
<L>Which they who want, or foolishly misprise,</L>
<L>Walke on in <HI>Folly,</HI> and in <HI>Errour</HI> blind:</L>
<L>We many ignorant vaine <HI>Fooles</HI> doe find,</L>
<L>So wise in their conceit and estimation;</L>
<L>They thinke all <HI>wisdome</HI> in their breasts confin'd,</L>
<L>These being bound by double obligation</L>
<L>To Folly, there's no hope of any reformation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="60" REF="36"/>
<HI>Prudence</HI> and <HI>Folly,</HI> in the Soule of man,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Health</HI> and <HI>Sicknesse</HI> in his Body are;</L>
<L>As <HI>Health</HI> the Body keepes, so. <HI>Prudence</HI> can</L>
<L>The Soule deliuer from the <HI>Deuills</HI> snare:</L>
<L>And as <HI>Diseases</HI> here the thread doth share</L>
<L>Of <HI>Body's</HI> Life; So <HI>Folly</HI> soone doth rend</L>
<L>The <HI>Soule</HI> with <HI>pleasures</HI> vaine, and <HI>worldly care:</HI></L>
<L>For as strong men within a Fort defend;</L>
<L>So <HI>Prudent</HI> Thoughts our soules from <HI>Satans</HI> fury shend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And as, among the noble <HI>senses</HI> fiue,</L>
<L>The Sight doth all the rest in worth excell,</L>
<L>Because all doe their Light from her deriue,</L>
<L>And shee all that offends them doth repell:</L>
<L>So <HI>Prudence</HI> all the <HI>vertues</HI> doth precell;</L>
<L>Because, by Light God sends her from aboue,</L>
<L>Shee counsells all the <HI>Graces</HI> to do well;</L>
<L>For without her no <HI>Grace</HI> aright can moue</L>
<L><HI>Prudence</HI> of all the rest the Gouernour doth proue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Vlisses Prudence, Aiax</HI> Fortitude;</L>
<L>Whil'st they each other doe accompany</L>
<L>Win City's, conquer men, and monsters rude:</L>
<L>But if they square for Gaine or Dignity,</L>
<L>And <HI>Aiax</HI> leaues <HI>Vlisses</HI> company,</L>
<L>His valour turnes to <HI>Folly</HI> or to rage:</L>
<L>So men of greatest <HI>magnanimity,</HI></L>
<L>When they the <HI>Guidance</HI> leaue of <HI>Prudence</HI> sage,</L>
<L>Grow <HI>beastly, mad,</HI> or <HI>foolish</HI> in their later age.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I may her liken to the <HI>Prince</HI> of Day,</L>
<L>From whom all lesser <HI>Lamps</HI> doe borrow Light;</L>
<L>Who when he doth his glorious <HI>Beames</HI> display,</L>
<L>The rest all seeme to be extinguish't quite:</L>
<L>So when as <HI>heau'nly Wisdome,</HI> wondrous bright,</L>
<L>Her selfe amongst the <HI>Graces</HI> doth disclose,</L>
<L>They all doe seeme to vanish in her sight,</L>
<L>As all the <HI>Glory</HI> that they haue arose (dispose.</L>
<L>From those bright Beames, which <HI>wisdome</HI> doth on them</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="61" REF="36"/>
As <HI>God</HI> the <HI>world,</HI> The <HI>Emperour</HI> his <HI>host,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Gouernour</HI> his <HI>Ship,</HI> the <HI>Sunne</HI> the <HI>day,</HI></L>
<L>And as the <HI>Body's</HI> ruled by the Ghost,</L>
<L>So doth faire <HI>Prudence</HI> all the <HI>vertues</HI> sway:</L>
<L>And as these, like good Guides, direct the way</L>
<L>Vnto their charge, to reach their proper end:</L>
<L>So doth <HI>true wisdome,</HI> all that her obey</L>
<L>To endlesse happinesse and pleasure send;</L>
<L>Most happy man who doth her holy hests attend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>May his heart die like <HI>Nabals</HI> churle and foole,</L>
<L>Or like <HI>Achitophel</HI> end with a string;</L>
<L>Laugh in the stocks, cleaue to the scorners stoole,</L>
<L>That listens not to heau'nly counselling</L>
<L>Of <HI>Wisdome,</HI> and her sweet admonishing,</L>
<L>Shee hath prouided <HI>victualls,</HI> powr'd out <HI>wine,</HI></L>
<L>Sent out her <HI>Maids</HI> vs to the <HI>feast</HI> to bring,</L>
<L>To bid those that seeke <HI>Knowledge</HI> come and dine;</L>
<L>And those that <HI>Prudence</HI> want to tast her <HI>grapes</HI> diuine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For shee's the <HI>Vine,</HI> whose <HI>grapes</HI> yeeld pleasing smell,</L>
<L>Whose <HI>Fruit</HI> and <HI>Flowers, Wealth, Life, Honour</HI> are;</L>
<L>The <HI>Garden</HI> where <HI>Christ dearest Spouse</HI> doth dwell,</L>
<L>Planted with all the <HI>Herbs</HI> and <HI>Spices</HI> rare,</L>
<L>Which to adorne his <HI>Church</HI> he doth prepare:</L>
<L>Would thou one word which should her worth containe</L>
<L><HI>He hath true Wisdome, who the Lord doth feare,</HI></L>
<L>And who know's holy things doth entertaine</L>
<L>Right <HI>vnderstanding,</HI> without this the rest are vaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>She as the <HI>Prince</HI> or <HI>Generall</HI> doth guide</L>
<L>All other <HI>Graces</HI> in <HI>Loues</HI> sacred band,</L>
<L>Doth order, marshall, and for them prouide,</L>
<L>As th' <HI>Eye,</HI> which all the members doth command:</L>
<L>The Gouernours of Men, of Cities, and</L>
<L>Of Families, and each mans priuate state,</L>
<L>She orders <HI>wisely</HI> by her <HI>prudent</HI> hand,</L>
<L>And they that duely on <HI>Discretion</HI> waite,</L>
<L>Command the <HI>Stars,</HI> and rule eu'n ouer <HI>Time</HI> and <HI>Fate.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="62" REF="37"/>
As <HI>shadow's</HI> more directly opposite</L>
<L>To <HI>Sunnes</HI> bright <HI>Rayes,</HI> seeme short by being neere,</L>
<L>When those, which are much farther from the light,</L>
<L>More goodly faire and long by farre appeare:</L>
<L>So who small <HI>Knowledge</HI> haue attained here,</L>
<L>Thereof doe alway's make a greater show</L>
<L>Than those, whose vnderstanding shining cleare,</L>
<L>Doe all the Paths of <HI>heau'nly wisdome</HI> know,</L>
<L>For with true <HI>Wisdome</HI> alway's <HI>Humblenesse</HI> doth grow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And as Gods <HI>Wisdome</HI> doth no lesser seeme</L>
<L>In <HI>smallest</HI> creatures, as a <HI>Gnat</HI> or <HI>Fly,</HI></L>
<L>Than <HI>Greater;</HI> so we ought no lesse esteeme</L>
<L><HI>Wisemen</HI> in low <HI>degree</HI> then <HI>Dignitie:</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Snaile</HI> a mirrour is of <HI>Politie,</HI></L>
<L>Who with her hornes keepes alway's sentinell,</L>
<L>And neuer commeth out before shee try,</L>
<L>If things without be all in Peace and well</L>
<L>Else she, retyring home, liues quiet in her shell.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh sonnes of men that you could but behold!</L>
<L>The wondrous <HI>Beauty</HI> of this heau'nly <HI>Peare;</HI></L>
<L>But nought on earth her <HI>Beauty</HI> can vnfold</L>
<L>Her Glory in the Heau'ns doth shine most cleare;</L>
<L>In all Gods workes her splendour doth appeare,</L>
<L>She first from Heau'n vouchsafed to descend</L>
<L>To liue in <HI>Iudah,</HI> with her chosen deare:</L>
<L>But now her <HI>Beames</HI> more ample doe extend,</L>
<L>To all the Nations of the earth she light doth lend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>She taught our <HI>Father</HI> that was made alone,</L>
<L>To raise himselfe to Glory from his fall;</L>
<L>But Enuy turn'd from her his foolish sonne,</L>
<L>And made by <HI>Fratricide</HI> and <HI>Fury</HI> fall:</L>
<L>Loe when the Floud the world destroyed all,</L>
<L>She it preserues by one <HI>wise</HI> worke of <HI>Wood:</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>dead Sea</HI> yet is the memoriall</L>
<L>Of foolish <HI>City's fiue,</HI> which there erst stood,</L>
<L>Where she sau'd <HI>Lot</HI> from fire, as <HI>Noah</HI> from the sloud.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="63" REF="37"/>
To tell what wonders haue beene by her wrought,</L>
<L>Were too to long for this short meditation;</L>
<L>They in Gods Booke are easily found, if sought,</L>
<L>For there indeed is <HI>Wisdom's</HI> commendation;</L>
<L>Where she vs doth, with wary obseruation,</L>
<L>Vnto the <HI>Cony</HI> and the <HI>Pismire</HI> send,</L>
<L>To learne to get our food and habitation,</L>
<L>Whose meaner Wisdome if we must attend,</L>
<L>Much more wise <HI>Heathens</HI> sayings most diuinely pend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>One being asked, who was most wise, reply'd</L>
<L>He that sinn'd least; when one of them desir'd</L>
<L>To learne who was for youth the trustiest <HI>Guid:</HI></L>
<L>He answer'd, <HI>Prudence:</HI> And in's sonne requir'd</L>
<L>Only three things, which he in <HI>youth</HI> admir'd:</L>
<L>In his <HI>tongue silence; Prudence</HI> in his <HI>mind;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Shamefastnesse</HI> in his <HI>Face:</HI> when one requir'd</L>
<L>How he the <HI>greatest</HI> in the <HI>least</HI> might find;</L>
<L>He answer'd, <HI>prudent thoughts</HI> in <HI>humane</HI> breast confin'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This was an <HI>Ethnick:</HI> But how doth she shine,</L>
<L>When she is ioyn'd with pure <HI>simplicitie?</HI></L>
<L>When as that <HI>holy wisdome serpentine,</HI></L>
<L>Combines with <HI>doue-like</HI> true <HI>sincerity:</HI></L>
<L>Oh thus the Saints by holy subtilty,</L>
<L>Walke safe amongst worlds crooked generation:</L>
<L>Thus walk'd our <HI>Sauiour</HI> in <HI>Humilitie,</HI></L>
<L>And though the wicked plot his condemnation,</L>
<L>Yet neuer could they touch him, but by subornation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh how should we that haue this mirrour bright!</L>
<L>This <HI>Sun</HI> of <HI>Wisdome</HI> labour here to shine</L>
<L>Like Stars, which from the <HI>Sun</HI> receiue their light,</L>
<L>And to <HI>sincerity</HI> true <HI>columbine,</HI></L>
<L>Ioyne this wise <HI>holy Prudence serpentine:</HI></L>
<L>Vs to conduct through this worlds wildernesse,</L>
<L>And a most safe and perfect way out line</L>
<L>Through <HI>Iordans waues,</HI> to <HI>Land</HI> of <HI>Happinesse,</HI></L>
<L>Where <HI>Mansions</HI> ready built, we shall for ay possesse.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="64" REF="38"/>
And <HI>Vineyards</HI> planted, whence the <HI>Cananite,</HI></L>
<L>For wicked <HI>Treason</HI> 'gainst his <HI>Maiesty,</HI></L>
<L>God hath expell'd to <HI>Hell,</HI> and darkest night,</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Lucifer</HI> and all his company:</L>
<L>Oh why should'st thou aduance base dust so high!</L>
<L>Whose <HI>earthly Mansion</HI> keepes his <HI>Spirit</HI> low,</L>
<L>And will not let his <HI>vnderstanding</HI> flye</L>
<L>To see what goodly <HI>clusters</HI> there doe grow,</L>
<L>In heau'nly <HI>Canaan,</HI> where <HI>Milke</HI> and <HI>Hony</HI> flow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>We hardly here of things below discerne,</L>
<L>And with great <HI>paines</HI> what is before vs find;</L>
<L>Ah how shall we than able be to learne</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Wisdome,</HI> which no limits haue confin'd:</L>
<L>Thy Spirit onely can into our mind</L>
<L>These hidden mysteries, in Christ reueale,</L>
<L>In which the Princes of the world were blind;</L>
<L>For from man naturall thou dost conceale</L>
<L>This <HI>Wisdome spirituall,</HI> which thou to thine do'st deale.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For as none know's the <HI>Spirit</HI> of a man,</L>
<L>But that same <HI>Spirit</HI> that within doth dwell:</L>
<L>So nothing apprehend this <HI>Wisdome</HI> can</L>
<L>But that wise <HI>Spirit</HI> that all <HI>Truth</HI> doth tell,</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Sacred Spirit of Truth!</HI> my heart compell</L>
<L>This <HI>holy Sapience</HI> to entertaine,</L>
<L>Thou only giu'st to drinke of <HI>Wisdom's</HI> Well;</L>
<L>Mans <HI>wisdom's wickednesse,</HI> his <HI>thoughts</HI> are <HI>vaine,</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>knowledge</HI> is but <HI>errour,</HI> and his <HI>pleasure paine.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thou didst create eu'n all things by thy <HI>Word,</HI></L>
<L>And by thy <HI>heau'nly Wisdome</HI> didst ordaine</L>
<L><HI>Man</HI> of thy handy workes to be the <HI>Lord,</HI></L>
<L>That he in <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Equitie</HI> might raigne,</L>
<L>And with an vpright heart the right maintaine:</L>
<L>Oh therefore downe thine <HI>heau'nly wisdome</HI> send,</L>
<L>Me in all <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>vprightnesse</HI> to traine,</L>
<L>She shall my Words and Works to thee commend,</L>
<L>And bring my small <HI>beginnings</HI> to a <HI>perfect end.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="65" REF="38"/>
And here with <HI>Praise</HI> and <HI>Prayer</HI> I will end,</L>
<L>Oh who aright can <HI>know</HI> or <HI>vnderstand,</HI></L>
<L>Except thou <HI>Wisdome</HI> from thy <HI>Throne</HI> do'st send,</L>
<L>To giue vnto him what thou dost command:</L>
<L>Then grant me <HI>Wisdome</HI> alway's to withstand</L>
<L><HI>Hells</HI> subtill <HI>Plots,</HI> and <HI>Worlds</HI> base <HI>Blandiments,</HI></L>
<L>Let <HI>sacred Prudence</HI> euer be at hand,</L>
<L>Still to direct my <HI>words, acts,</HI> and <HI>intents,</HI></L>
<L>To yeeld <HI>Obedience</HI> to thy Commandements.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. II. <HI>Of</HI> OBEDIENCE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>WHen first th' Almighty, by his only Word,</L>
<L>Had fashion'd all within the Firmament:</L>
<L>He made Man last, to be their King and Lord,</L>
<L>That he to him might be obedient:</L>
<L>But Man not with this <HI>Monarchy</HI> content,</L>
<L>Diuide <HI>his homage</HI> to <HI>omnipotence;</HI></L>
<L>And hauing but one <HI>small Commandement,</HI></L>
<L>Transgressed it by Disobedience:</L>
<L>The <HI>easier</HI> the Command, the <HI>greater</HI> the Offence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This all the <HI>Sonnes of Adam</HI> doe deriue</L>
<L>From him, and call it guilt Originall,</L>
<L>Which by th' <HI>Eternall Law</HI> did vs depriue</L>
<L>Of all Gods Benefits, and did enthrall</L>
<L>To endlesse Bondage, till <HI>Christ</HI> for this Fall,</L>
<L>The price of his most precious bloud did pay,</L>
<L>Which vs recouers from <HI>Sins actuall,</HI></L>
<L>And by obeying Gods whole <HI>Law,</HI> doth stay</L>
<L>His wrath, And merits Heau'n for all that him obay.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="66" REF="39"/>
For as by <HI>first mans Disobedience</HI></L>
<L>On all men commeth Death and Condemnation;</L>
<L>So by the <HI>seconds</HI> true <HI>Obedience,</HI></L>
<L>We haue eternall Life, and sure <HI>Saluation:</HI></L>
<L>Thus Disobedience, by deriuation</L>
<L>From <HI>Adam,</HI> bringeth endlesse wretchednesse,</L>
<L>And true Obedience, by imputation</L>
<L>Conuay's from <HI>Christ</HI> eternall Happinesse;</L>
<L>So by the <HI>first</HI> comes <HI>sin,</HI> by <HI>second Righteousnesse.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The glorious robe of perfect <HI>Righteousnesse,</HI></L>
<L>Which they that are obedient onely weare,</L>
<L>To couer that foule shame and wickednesse,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Adams Disobedience</HI> layed bare:</L>
<L>Ah! let a <HI>Disobedient Sinner</HI> dare,</L>
<L>The aid of the <HI>Obedient Lamb</HI> desire,</L>
<L>My Will and Actions, Tongue and Heart to square,</L>
<L>In due proportion to his heau'nly squire,</L>
<L>Whil'st I of true <HI>Obedience</HI> prayses doe enquire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Deuoutest <HI>Lady!</HI> Handmaid to the <HI>Queene</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>heau'nly Loue,</HI> And so in duty bound,</L>
<L>That shee's alway's prest and ready seene,</L>
<L>To doe what thing soeuer she propound:</L>
<L>Her heart, words, will and deeds all one are found,</L>
<L>Seruing for <HI>Loue,</HI> and not for <HI>Feare</HI> or <HI>Gaine,</HI></L>
<L>No Subiect merits better to be crown'd;</L>
<L>For who can best obay, he best can raigne,</L>
<L>And she is shortly sure, eternall <HI>Crownes</HI> to gaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>If I may square Her by the Rules of Art,</L>
<L>I her define to be our <HI>Wills subiection</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>Him,</HI> that ought to rule both will and heart,</L>
<L>And by his will disposeth our best affection:</L>
<L>The rule of Reason may be our direction,</L>
<L>How our superiours Statutes we obay;</L>
<L>But when the Lord commands, there's no election</L>
<L>Nor doubting, what we ought to doe or say,</L>
<L><HI>Gods will's the rule of Right,</HI> which none may <HI>disobey.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="67" REF="39"/>
Here in two Branches, I might her diuide,</L>
<L><HI>Obedience</HI> first to <HI>God,</HI> and secondly</L>
<L>To our <HI>Superiours,</HI> that on earth abide,</L>
<L>But all is but to one Authority:</L>
<L>For there's no Power or precedency,</L>
<L>But that which highest Power doth ordaine;</L>
<L>Who therefore doth resist mans Soueraignty,</L>
<L>Gods ordinance resisteth, and againe</L>
<L>Who duly it obay's, Gods Statutes doth maintaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus must our hearts, eares, hands be all attent</L>
<L>His Word and Will in all things to obey,</L>
<L>Who ouer vs hath lawfull <HI>Regiment,</HI></L>
<L>Which is one God, eternall, blest for ay;</L>
<L>Whose <HI>seruants</HI> all we are, And therefore may</L>
<L>Not chuse a <HI>Lord,</HI> or <HI>Master</HI> whom we will,</L>
<L>Nor serue two <HI>masters,</HI> least we disobay</L>
<L>The one, when we the others mind fulfill,</L>
<L>For that which pleaseth <HI>one,</HI> doth crosse the <HI>others</HI> will.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus our <HI>obedience</HI> is only due</L>
<L>To him, that all did for his seruice make;</L>
<L>And 'tis a firme position sound and true;</L>
<L><HI>God only for himselfe;</HI> But <HI>for his sake,</HI></L>
<L><HI>All that from him Authoritie doe take</HI></L>
<L><HI>We truly and sincerely ought obey:</HI></L>
<L>Or else our bounden dutie we forsake,</L>
<L>As those which doe their Princes disobey,</L>
<L>When they their lawfull Officers commands gainsay.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For this whole <HI>world</HI> is like a <HI>family,</HI></L>
<L>In all things well and iustly ordered;</L>
<L>Where <HI>God</HI> hath the supreame authority,</L>
<L>And <HI>Rulers</HI> theirs from him deliuered,</L>
<L>By which they doe command as in his stead;</L>
<L>Who then to them are <HI>disobedient,</HI></L>
<L>They may be said to disobey the <HI>Head:</HI></L>
<L>For whil'st they rightly vse their gouernment,</L>
<L>We ought them to obey in things indifferent.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="68" REF="40"/>
Indeed all ought regard the <HI>Supreme Will,</HI></L>
<L>As <HI>first commanding cause,</HI> and <HI>end</HI> of all;</L>
<L>Which all that Being haue, ought to fulfill,</L>
<L>From which as all things rise, so all must fall;</L>
<L>Here therefore first, we into mind will call:</L>
<L>To whom that will commands vs to obay,</L>
<L>For in <HI>obeying</HI> their commands we shall</L>
<L>Obey that <HI>Supreme Will:</HI> This is the way</L>
<L>To make <HI>Gods Will</HI> the Cause, of all we doe or say.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To Him; we must be subiect, <HI>first</HI> of all,</L>
<L>To whom all Power in Heau'n and Earth is lent;</L>
<L>The <HI>Sonne of God begotten, naturall,</HI></L>
<L>Next to his <HI>Ministers,</HI> which he hath sent:</L>
<L><HI>Apostles, Pastors, Doctors,</HI> here are meant;</L>
<L>Which by his Word doe teach their <HI>Masters Will,</HI></L>
<L>And rule his <HI>Church,</HI> by godly Gouernment,</L>
<L>And those, which <HI>heare these, his commands</HI> fulfill,</L>
<L>And those which them <HI>despise, despise</HI> his heau'nly Will.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As <HI>Kings,</HI> which with great Honour doe conuay</L>
<L>Princes <HI>Ambassadours,</HI> it doe intend</L>
<L>Vnto their <HI>Lords,</HI> So we our <HI>Lord obay</HI></L>
<L>When we <HI>obey</HI> the <HI>Legates</HI> he doth send:</L>
<L>The <HI>second</HI> Power is that which God doth lend</L>
<L>To Kings and Princes, for to delegate</L>
<L><HI>Iudges,</HI> to punish those which doe offend,</L>
<L>And to maintaine the Life, Peace, and estate</L>
<L>Of eu'ry member, that maintaines the Bodies state;</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To this all Subiects owe <HI>Obedience;</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>third</HI> obedience is, which wife doth owe</L>
<L>Vnto her Head, who due Beneuolence</L>
<L>For Dutie, ought vnto his wife to shew:</L>
<L>For as the <HI>Church,</HI> so ought the Wife to know</L>
<L>Her due Subiection vnto her <HI>Head,</HI></L>
<L>And as our <HI>Christ</HI> directs his Church below:</L>
<L>So wiues must be by husbands ordered,</L>
<L>But this of wiues is better knowne, then practised.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="69" REF="40"/>
So is th' <HI>obedience,</HI> which Children owe</L>
<L>Vnto their Parents, by Commandement</L>
<L>And promise, they shall long, and good day's know,</L>
<L>If they to them will be obedient.</L>
<L>The fift and last is <HI>Masters</HI> Gouernment,</L>
<L>And <HI>Seruants</HI> Duty which they should them beare,</L>
<L>Which ought to be with single true intent,</L>
<L>Not for eye-seruice, wages, or for feare;</L>
<L>But as they would obey eu'n <HI>Christ</HI> their <HI>Master</HI> deare.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus ought we to obey these fiue degrees,</L>
<L>Set ouer vs: Because we so obay</L>
<L>The highest Power, And if their iust decrees</L>
<L>We sleight, that highest Power we disobay:</L>
<L>Far wide then disobedient <HI>spirits</HI> stray,</L>
<L>Which by Religion, would all reuerence</L>
<L>Exclude, due vnto <HI>Magistrates,</HI> and say</L>
<L>They vnto no man owe obedience,</L>
<L>A false excuse of <HI>Schisme</HI> and all vnreuerence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Obedience</HI> preserueth <HI>Vnity,</HI></L>
<L>And helpeth to this great worlds conseruation,</L>
<L>As Heau'ns and Earth doe by due Obsequy</L>
<L>Obey their glorious Makers Ordination;</L>
<L>Behold how all things in this worlds Creation,</L>
<L>Doe by their Makers order stand or moue;</L>
<L><HI>Earth</HI> keepes her <HI>Center</HI> for mans preseruation,</L>
<L>The <HI>Heau'ns</HI> turne all in motion round aboue,</L>
<L>Without <HI>Obedience</HI> one would out another shoue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And thus we may <HI>Obedience</HI> obserue,</L>
<L>To hold our <HI>members</HI> in due motion ay,</L>
<L>Whil'st one doth to another member serue,</L>
<L>And all vnto the <HI>Spirit</HI> doe obay,</L>
<L>The <HI>Soule of man,</HI> which doth by reason sway</L>
<L>Eu'n all the <HI>members,</HI> to their preseruation,</L>
<L>And if the least of them doe disobay,</L>
<L>Shee either seekes their better reformation,</L>
<L>Or one endangers all, to endlesse condemnation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="70" REF="41"/>
For whilst man here doth on the earth remaine,</L>
<L>Sin and corruption in his Body dwell:</L>
<L>Seeking therein as <HI>Lord</HI> and <HI>King</HI> to raigne,</L>
<L>But <HI>Grace</HI> doth striue by force them to expell:</L>
<L>If <HI>bondslaues</HI> we our selues to <HI>Sin</HI> doe sell,</L>
<L>And giue our members here Lusts to obay,</L>
<L>We yeeld vnto such Lusts as lead to Hell;</L>
<L>But if that <HI>Grace</HI> our <HI>Soule</HI> aright doth sway,</L>
<L>Then all the <HI>members</HI> follow Her the <HI>narrow way.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Remoue this Vertue of <HI>Obedience</HI></L>
<L>From Soule or Body, Subiect, City, Towne,</L>
<L>Or from the Creatures wanting life and sense,</L>
<L>And all vnto Confusion tumble downe:</L>
<L>The Tower of <HI>Babel</HI> might to Heau'n haue growne,</L>
<L>Had all obay'd with mutuall diligence:</L>
<L>But suddainly we see it ouerthrowne,</L>
<L>When to <HI>obay</HI> they want intelligence,</L>
<L>For without <HI>vnderstanding</HI> no <HI>Obedience.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As to maintaine Heau'ns perfect vnitie,</L>
<L>All to one <HI>surpeame Trinity</HI> obay;</L>
<L>So all that haue with it Affinitie,</L>
<L>Subiect themselues to that one <HI>God</HI> for ay:</L>
<L>No wonder if those that him <HI>disobay,</HI></L>
<L>To many <HI>Errours, Schismes,</HI> and <HI>Sects</HI> doe fall,</L>
<L>For one <HI>true Vnity</HI> they doe gainsay,</L>
<L>When they resist his Ordinances shall,</L>
<L>And <HI>disobey</HI> Gods Word, that here directeth all.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Mee thinkes my <HI>Muse</HI> could here her selfe transcend,</L>
<L>By musing of th' <HI>obedience</HI> aboue,</L>
<L>Which from the <HI>Sonne</HI> to <HI>Father</HI> doth ascend,</L>
<L>And <HI>Angells,</HI> who <HI>obeying</HI> Feare and Loue,</L>
<L>Alas what can th' eternall Power moue!</L>
<L><HI>Obedience</HI> of poore wretches to require,</L>
<L>But vs to ioyne to <HI>Christ</HI> our Head in <HI>Loue,</HI></L>
<L>As he is ioy'nd to God in due desire,</L>
<L>Vnto no other end <HI>Obedience</HI> doth aspire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="71" REF="41"/>
For as when in a wild and fruitlesse stocke</L>
<L>We doe some noble impe inoculate;</L>
<L>The fruit erst base and wild, like to the Blocke,</L>
<L>Is made as goodly, faire, and delicate</L>
<L>As <HI>Tree</HI> which first this imp did generate:</L>
<L>So the least imp of <HI>Christs Obedience,</HI></L>
<L>In vs ingraft, doth vs regenerate;</L>
<L>And makes vs beare fruit of like excellence,</L>
<L>As <HI>liuely tree,</HI> from which it first had influence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For all that from stocke of first <HI>Adam</HI> come,</L>
<L>Beare those sowre fruits of <HI>Disobedience;</HI></L>
<L>But all, that doe ingraft againe become</L>
<L>In second <HI>Adams</HI> true <HI>Obedience,</HI></L>
<L>Bring forth sweet fruits, like liuely tree, from whence</L>
<L>They haue receiued first their sap to spring;</L>
<L>Swee liuing <HI>Vine!</HI> whose sacred influence,</L>
<L>Vs makes <HI>obedient</HI> to our Lord and King,</L>
<L>Ah! who the praises of thy noble fruit can sing?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>It did aduance that holy <HI>Prophets</HI> quill,</L>
<L>When He in <HI>volume of the booke</HI> did find,</L>
<L>Written, that thou shouldst Gods whole Law fulfill,</L>
<L>Whereto thou wert withall thine heart inclin'd:</L>
<L>And when the time was come thereto assign'd,</L>
<L>Thou wert <HI>obedient</HI> to all <HI>Gods</HI> will,</L>
<L>Performing it with all thine heart and mind,</L>
<L>Ev'n till the <HI>Iewes</HI> thee on the <HI>Crosse</HI> did kill,</L>
<L>When thou resisted'st not, though they thy bloud did spill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Obedient Lamb!</HI> this was the <HI>sacrifice,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>offering</HI> God did for sin require;</L>
<L>Thus We must offer vp to God, likewise</L>
<L>Our Soules and Body's, with like <HI>zealous</HI> fire</L>
<L>To dye, if not <HI>indeed,</HI> yet in <HI>desire:</HI></L>
<L>Quick, holy, acceptable Offering,</L>
<L>To pacifie Gods <HI>Iustice</HI> and his Ire,</L>
<L>Is when to him obedient hearts we bring</L>
<L>And crucifie those Lusts, which from our Flesh doe spring.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="72" REF="42"/>
As from the boundlesse <HI>Ocean</HI> doe run</L>
<L>All streames which doe returne into the <HI>Maine,</HI></L>
<L>So from one <HI>paterne of Obedience</HI> come</L>
<L>All ours, and thither doth returne againe;</L>
<L>The <HI>Lamb</HI> that was from worlds beginning slaine</L>
<L>Gaue the first blow to <HI>Disobedience,</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>Isaack</HI> imitates when he is laine,</L>
<L>On Altar to be sacrificed thence,</L>
<L>Whom truly <HI>Abram</HI> offer'd by <HI>Obedience.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This was that <HI>quiet sauour</HI> God did smell,</L>
<L>When offring one of each cleane bird and beast,</L>
<L>The good old <HI>Noah</HI> pleas'd the Lord so well;</L>
<L><HI>Obedience</HI> was the Seasoning to the feast:</L>
<L>What made the <HI>Lord Sauls</HI> sacrifice detest?</L>
<L>But that he did his Word then disobey,</L>
<L>When he did spare of <HI>Amalec</HI> the best,</L>
<L>To offer vp: But therein did obay</L>
<L>His own corrupt inuentions, not what God did say.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Better then <HI>Sacrifice</HI> is to obay,</L>
<L>And then the <HI>fat of Rams</HI> to giue good eare,</L>
<L>Happy though we doe all the world gaine say,</L>
<L>If we obay our <HI>Lord</HI> and <HI>Master</HI> deare:</L>
<L>But ah! whil'st we remaine as <HI>Pilgrims</HI> here,</L>
<L>Flesh, World, and Deuill daily vs perswade</L>
<L>To follow Pleasures vaine, and to forbeare</L>
<L><HI>Obedience</HI> to the Lord, which vs hath made,</L>
<L>Whose Statutes to obey should be our onely trade.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh Sacrifice of Fooles! with tongue to pray,</L>
<L>But harbour no <HI>obedience</HI> in thine heart;</L>
<L>Who dost in word professe God to obay,</L>
<L>But by thy workes dost all his Law's peruert:</L>
<L>Behold! it is not without iust desert</L>
<L>That Beasts to thee are <HI>disobedient,</HI></L>
<L>When thou to <HI>God</HI> a faithlesse rebell art,</L>
<L>To whom obey Sun, Moone, Stars, Firmament,</L>
<L>Nor Sea against his will inuades the <HI>Continent.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="73" REF="42"/>
Whil'st I about, this sinfull Body beare,</L>
<L>Lusts and corruptions will therein remaine;</L>
<L>Yet neuer let them so much domineere</L>
<L>As here of <HI>Grace,</HI> the mastery to gaine:</L>
<L>For if I suffer Sinne in me to raigne,</L>
<L>That all my members will to sinne obay,</L>
<L>That sin whereof Saint <HI>Paul</HI> doth so complaine,</L>
<L>Oh! who me from the same deliuer may!</L>
<L>It is not I, but sin that Christ doth disobay.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>If that the Iudge by his Authoritie,</L>
<L>Inioyne me to performe or speake a thing,</L>
<L>Against the will of <HI>Soueraigne Maiestie,</HI></L>
<L>Here my Deniall no Offence doth bring;</L>
<L>And if I be commanded by the King,</L>
<L>To doe against his will, that is aboue,</L>
<L>I here no Rebell am, though suffering:</L>
<L>For I were better <HI>Crosse</HI> and <HI>Prison</HI> proue,</L>
<L>Than in <HI>Gehenna</HI> fry, from whence is no remoue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And as in all humane societies,</L>
<L>The meaner Power the greater doth obay,</L>
<L>Till to the <HI>Peramount</HI> it doth arise,</L>
<L>Which Power all inferiour powers sway:</L>
<L>So in this Power Spirituall we may,</L>
<L>Behold like order for <HI>Obedience,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Peramount</HI> is Gods high Power ay;</L>
<L>For though we doe all Powers reuerence,</L>
<L>Yet to the highest we haue alway's reference.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>What more vniust, than looke to be obay'd,</L>
<L>By our inferiours, and to disobay</L>
<L>Those God hath plac'd aboue vs for our aid,</L>
<L>Ah how, <HI>Thy will be done</HI> may we here pray,</L>
<L>As Angells doe the same in Heau'n for ay:</L>
<L>Which we so often crosse by doing ill,</L>
<L>More often then are minutes in a day</L>
<L>Oh let my Heart be ready to fulfill!</L>
<L>Mine Heart be ready Lord! to learne and doe thy will.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="74" REF="43"/>
Ready in all things lawfull to obay</L>
<L>Superiours all, to doe things iust and right,</L>
<L>To Loue my Neighbour; for mine enemy's pray,</L>
<L>Grace to embrace, and with Corruptions fight,</L>
<L>To cast off earthly things, and to delight</L>
<L>Wholly in <HI>God,</HI> and heau'nly contemplation;</L>
<L>To worke by day, to watch and pray by night,</L>
<L>To learne of <HI>Christ, Meeknesse, Humiliation,</HI></L>
<L>With trembling and with Feare to worke out my Saluation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Since I must be <HI>obedient</HI> to the end,</L>
<L>How should I end to beg <HI>Obedience?</HI></L>
<L><HI>Obedience,</HI> which to Liberty doth tend,</L>
<L>And vs restores vnto that excellence</L>
<L>Which <HI>Adam</HI> lost by <HI>Disobedience.</HI></L>
<L>Let others glory in their mightie traine,</L>
<L>And large command of many Continents;</L>
<L>By <HI>Meeknesse</HI> and <HI>Obedience</HI> I shall gaine,</L>
<L>With <HI>Meeke obedient Lamb</HI> in Heau'n for ay to raigne.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. III. <HI>Of</HI> MEEKNESSE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>AS in faire <HI>Garden,</HI> where variety</L>
<L>Of choisest Flowers, the <HI>senses</HI> to delight,</L>
<L>Are plac't by cunning hand, most curiously,</L>
<L>Their diuers colours most effect the sight,</L>
<L>That broad and fairest shew and stand vpright,</L>
<L>But oft we find low creeping on the ground,</L>
<L>An <HI>hearb,</HI> whose odour sweet doth more inuite</L>
<L>Our smells, than all the <HI>Tuslips</HI> there are found;</L>
<L>So is it with this <HI>Grace,</HI> which I doe next propound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="75" REF="43"/>
For though the goodliest <HI>Garden of the Bride,</HI></L>
<L>Like <HI>Eden</HI> is so faire embelished</L>
<L>With richest Fruits and Flowers, from side to side,</L>
<L>Their names and hues cannot be numbered,</L>
<L>Much lesse their Force and Natures be aread:</L>
<L>And though all are more glorious to be seene,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Meeknesse,</HI> which is next disciphered:</L>
<L>Yet none more pleasing to our smell I weene,</L>
<L>Nor more, than her, respected of <HI>Loues royall Queene.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Obedience, Meeknesse,</HI> and <HI>Humility</HI></L>
<L>Are Flowers, more for <HI>profit</HI> than for <HI>show,</HI></L>
<L>Pleasing the smell and taste more than the eye,</L>
<L>And lowly like sweet <HI>Thyme</HI> and <HI>Hysope</HI> grow;</L>
<L>These by the outward face we must not know,</L>
<L>Their <HI>inward vertue</HI> 'tis that we esteeme</L>
<L>Their Force is heau'nly, though their dwellings low,</L>
<L>And may the greatest <HI>Monarch</HI> here be-seeme,</L>
<L>For sure the <HI>King of Kings</HI> like these himselfe did deeme.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And vs commandeth all of him to learne</L>
<L><HI>Meeknesse</HI> and <HI>lowlinesse,</HI> which <HI>rest</HI> doth bring,</L>
<L>Eternall Rest, which doth our Soules concerne</L>
<L>Here more than any vaine and worldly thing:</L>
<L><HI>Most mighty God,</HI> and yet the <HI>meekest King?</HI></L>
<L>Fit thou my Soule for this sweet Meditation;</L>
<L>And teach me <HI>meeknesse,</HI> whil'st I <HI>meeknesse</HI> sing,</L>
<L>Which base and meane in mans vaine estimation,</L>
<L>Is with the <HI>Lord</HI> of <HI>Lords</HI> of highest valuation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Some her define to be a <HI>Moderation</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Anger:</HI> And would haue her to abstaine</L>
<L>From all reuengefull furious, enuious passion,</L>
<L>Thereby possession of her soule to gaine:</L>
<L>For who doth <HI>gentle meeknesse</HI> entertaine,</L>
<L>With her finds happy <HI>Peace,</HI> and quiet <HI>Rest;</HI></L>
<L>And who from <HI>furious rage</HI> will not refraine,</L>
<L>But harbours <HI>wrath,</HI> and <HI>malice</HI> in his Brest,</L>
<L>Possesseth not himselfe, but is by them possest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="76" REF="44"/>
<HI>Meeke, gentle, milde, soft, affable,</HI> and <HI>kind,</HI></L>
<L>In words, though diuers are, in sense the same;</L>
<L>And come from gentle habit of the mind,</L>
<L>Which like it selfe our words and acts doth frame,</L>
<L>Making wild, sauage, furious creatures tame,</L>
<L>For all are mad and wild since <HI>Adams</HI> fall,</L>
<L>And burne in furious and reuengfull flame,</L>
<L>But <HI>meeknesse</HI> mitigates appeasing all,</L>
<L>And blessed here in peace the earth inherit shall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Meeknesse</HI> which pleaseth God, and profits man,</L>
<L>For God the <HI>meeke</HI> exalteth to Saluation;</L>
<L>And those which here abstaine from Anger can,</L>
<L>In multitude of <HI>Peace</HI> haue delectation:</L>
<L>With <HI>meeke</HI> far better is humiliation,</L>
<L>Than greatest spoiles with proud ones to diuide,</L>
<L>Heau'nly <HI>Hierusalem's</HI> no habitation</L>
<L>For those, which Right by <HI>Duells</HI> doe decide,</L>
<L>But those which can with <HI>meeknesse</HI> iniury's abide.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>She <HI>ire</HI> and <HI>rancour</HI> in her heart can brooke,</L>
<L>But doth all with an equall mind sustaine;</L>
<L>Prouok'd by none, nor doth she one prouoke,</L>
<L>Though oft offended hurteth none againe:</L>
<L>She doth from all improbity abstaine,</L>
<L>Resists not euill, but the same with good</L>
<L>Still ouercomes, And doth more glory gaine</L>
<L>By gentle yeelding, than if she withstood</L>
<L>The wicked in his raging, furious angry mood.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh <HI>Grace</HI> most glorious! when God Her sends</L>
<L>To dwell in breast of some great <HI>Potentate:</HI></L>
<L>His Heart She from all Crueltie defends,</L>
<L>And though he be <HI>a Lord of Life and Fate,</HI></L>
<L>His hands with bloud doth not contaminate;</L>
<L>She such a Prince to Heau'n at length will bring,</L>
<L>Too soone for vs; though he may thinke it late:</L>
<L>Let <HI>Homer</HI> fierce <HI>Achilles</HI> praises sing,</L>
<L>Giue me a <HI>mercifull, meeke, mild,</HI> and <HI>gentle King.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="77" REF="44"/>
For <HI>Meeknesse</HI> brings more honour to a King,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Purple, Scepter, Diademe,</HI> or <HI>Crowne,</HI></L>
<L>And richer triumphs doth to <HI>Emperours</HI> bring,</L>
<L>Than winning any <HI>Castle, Fort,</HI> or <HI>Towne:</HI></L>
<L>He gets eternall Glory and renowne;</L>
<L>Who can by <HI>meeknesse</HI> bridle <HI>passions</HI> right,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Tyrants</HI> rage, and let the <HI>Fury's</HI> frowne;</L>
<L>They can no more a good <HI>meeke</HI> man affright,</L>
<L>Than Arrow's hurt the water that thereon doe light.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Inhumane <HI>cruelty's</HI> taught in the schoole</L>
<L>Of <HI>Satan;</HI> who would like himselfe haue all;</L>
<L>But he whose seats in Heau'n, and his footstoole</L>
<L>Vpon the earth; Before whose presence fall</L>
<L>Downe all the Angells, and him Maker call,</L>
<L>Bids vs like to himselfe be <HI>meeke</HI> and <HI>low,</HI></L>
<L>For he that turn'd to sweet that cup of gall,</L>
<L>Can make the <HI>meeke</HI> and lowly highest grow,</L>
<L>And with one blast the proud and cruell ouerthrow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I labour not to keepe downe or depresse,</L>
<L>That humane natures high <HI>sublimitie,</HI></L>
<L>Without which creatures beare no <HI>awfulnesse</HI></L>
<L>Nor due respect vnto the <HI>Maiesty</HI></L>
<L>God hath annexed to mans <HI>Soueraignty:</HI></L>
<L>I seeke to suit his mind and <HI>conscience,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto his outward <HI>Grace</HI> and <HI>Dignity,</HI></L>
<L>And raise him by an inward confidence</L>
<L>Of wel-knowne worth, to an angelike excellence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet not by this <HI>sublimity</HI> to swell</L>
<L>Beyond the bounds of Mortalls, He that's wise</L>
<L>Will, as his worth and due deserts excell,</L>
<L>Be still more <HI>low</HI> and <HI>humble</HI> in's owne eyes:</L>
<L>And as his State and Honour here doe rise,</L>
<L>Hee is more modest, <HI>gentle, meeke,</HI> and <HI>kind,</HI></L>
<L>Preferring not himselfe in any wise</L>
<L>Before his equalls: thus he grace doth find,</L>
<L>By gentle <HI>manswetude,</HI> with God and all mankind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="78" REF="45"/>
For whilst by an obsequious conuersation,</L>
<L>And by ingenuous manners, pleasing, sweet;</L>
<L>Far from base <HI>flattery,</HI> as vaine <HI>ostentation</HI></L>
<L>Hee doth <HI>inferiours, equalls, betters</HI> greet,</L>
<L>By loosing of his owne; Lo he doth get,</L>
<L>In others thoughts the highest estimation;</L>
<L>His Head's in heau'n, though on the earth his feet;</L>
<L>And by anothers vertues veneration,</L>
<L>He getteth of his owne all loue and admiration.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh happy man to whom heau'ns <HI>King</HI> hath sent,</L>
<L>This <HI>Grace</HI> to be the glory of the rest;</L>
<L>What can that mind molest or discontent,</L>
<L>That harbours gracious <HI>meeknesse</HI> in his brest:</L>
<L>They that can <HI>contumely</HI> faire disgest,</L>
<L>If any them deride or reprehend,</L>
<L>Streight of themselues take more seuere inquest,</L>
<L>If ought be iustly blam'd, they soone amend,</L>
<L>If false, it neuer them shall anger or offend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Meeke, gentle, patient,</HI> bearing right or wrong;</L>
<L>From inward free, as outward perturbation,</L>
<L>Reuenge is not a thing that doth belong</L>
<L>To her; she finds far greater contentation</L>
<L>In wrongs dissembling, and their tolleration:</L>
<L>The wants, which she within her selfe doth find,</L>
<L>Her more depresse by modest moderation,</L>
<L>Than all her <HI>vertues</HI> eleuate her mind,</L>
<L>As <HI>salt</HI> she sauours all the <HI>vertues</HI> in their kind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is the same, or very like the <HI>Grace,</HI></L>
<L>Which we doe call <HI>Christian Humilitie</HI></L>
<L>Without which other vertues haue no place,</L>
<L>All are in her as in an <HI>Vnitie:</HI></L>
<L>She is the surest way to <HI>Dignitie,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>center</HI> where all vertues lines doe meet,</L>
<L>Most <HI>honour'd</HI> when she most doth <HI>vilifie</HI></L>
<L>Her selfe, And when she stoops to wash <HI>Saints</HI> feet,</L>
<L>The highest <HI>King</HI> of <HI>Kings,</HI> with kisses her doth greet.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="79" REF="45"/>
Yet none of worldlings is esteem'd more vile,</L>
<L>They it account a thing too meane and base,</L>
<L>Here to discend vnto so low a stile;</L>
<L>They thinke that <HI>meeknesse valour</HI> doth disgrace:</L>
<L>But oh absurd, presumptuous, mortall race;</L>
<L>So high and proud in thine owne estimation,</L>
<L>What thing's created in more wretched case?</L>
<L>Weake vaine precipite, and on each occasion,</L>
<L>Ready to fall from highest hopes to desperation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>What is thy Body but fraile quickned clay?</L>
<L>Thy Soule's so clouded with obscurity;</L>
<L>It is most ready, prone, precipite ay,</L>
<L>To fall to basenesse, errour, vanity:</L>
<L>Happy who sees his owne infirmity;</L>
<L>Thus By discending only we ascend</L>
<L>Vnto the highest humane dignity:</L>
<L>First step to honour is to vilipend</L>
<L>Our selues: Let others thee and not thy selfe commend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>None seekes to pull his foot out of the mire,</L>
<L>Vntill he feeles and know's that it is in,</L>
<L>Nor none to wash the durt off doth desire,</L>
<L>Vntill he sees it cleaue vnto his skin:</L>
<L>So till this <HI>Grace</HI> vs shew's our selues within,</L>
<L>We neuer seeke those heau'nly remedies,</L>
<L>To purge our soules from error and foule sinne;</L>
<L>This was of all the Oracles most wise,</L>
<L>First, <HI>know thy selfe:</HI> that is thine owne infirmities.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus comes the purest wheat from foulest ground,</L>
<L>So it be first well till'd and harrowed,</L>
<L>And thus the ignorant, grow men profound,</L>
<L>When they their folly haue discouered,</L>
<L>Of all the vertues can be reckoned;</L>
<L>The roots are bitter, fruits most sweet doe proue,</L>
<L>Selfe Pride, and Arrogance once settled</L>
<L>In humane Brest, most hard are to remoue,</L>
<L>This worke belongs to <HI>meeknesse, humblenesse</HI> and <HI>Loue.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="80" REF="46"/>
Most pleasant fruits, which from this root do spring,</L>
<L>When weeding out base pleasures false and vaine,</L>
<L>She true delight into their roomes doth bring</L>
<L>And rich Content, for euer to remaine,</L>
<L>Happy who can this Lady's fauour gaine;</L>
<L>Shee able is and ready to defend,</L>
<L>Against Soules troubles, and the body's paine;</L>
<L>The <HI>meeke,</HI> that patiently on God attend,</L>
<L>Are sure to haue a joyfull, quiet, happy end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Nothing can his most noble mind appall,</L>
<L>Which is with such Tranquillity indude;</L>
<L>Crosses, Afflictions may him here befall,</L>
<L>But base or abiect thoughts cannot intrude</L>
<L>Into a mind of such an habitude:</L>
<L>Certaine his breast all vertues doth containe,</L>
<L>Who hath this gentle <HI>vertue manswetude</HI></L>
<L>Who wants her boasts of <HI>vertue</HI> but in vaine,</L>
<L>They are but shew's of <HI>vertue,</HI> which with him remaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>It is the height of folly to bewray</L>
<L>Desire, where we haue no power to offend:</L>
<L>So beat the Sea, if it will not obay,</L>
<L>Or winds which crosse the way thou dost intend:</L>
<L>So whom thou canst not reach his picture rend,</L>
<L>Such wounds make arrow's, when they cleane the aire;</L>
<L>Yet many thus with rage their spirits spend,</L>
<L>Were it not better farre to beare them faire,</L>
<L>But Folly cannot beare, though thou in morter bray her.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>If an Asse kicks thee, must thou kicke againe?</L>
<L>Or barks a Dog, wilt thou straight baule and cry;</L>
<L>Because one's foolish, canst thou not refraine?</L>
<L>But needs doe that is ill for company:</L>
<L>Let fooles scorne meane Birth, want, deformity;</L>
<L>This (if a fault) not thine, thy Makers is,</L>
<L>To him that's <HI>meeke</HI> no infelicity</L>
<L>Can fall by <HI>Fortunes</HI> bitter frownes or blisse,</L>
<L>He counts them not his owne, true vertue's only his.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="81" REF="46"/>
I liken <HI>Meeknesse</HI> to that peece of wood,</L>
<L>Wherewith the <HI>Prophet</HI> did the Fountaines heale;</L>
<L>And made the bitter waters sweet and good,</L>
<L>For so doth <HI>Meeknesse</HI> with <HI>Afflictions</HI> deale,</L>
<L>She all their <HI>bitternesse</HI> with <HI>Ioy</HI> doth seale,</L>
<L>Ev'n that accursed death vpon a Tree,</L>
<L>She turneth from a <HI>Curse,</HI> vnto our <HI>Weale;</HI></L>
<L>Blest are the <HI>Meeke,</HI> that for well-doing be</L>
<L>Hang'd thereupon: from thence they <HI>Paradise</HI> may see.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>A <HI>meeke</HI> mans mind's like solitary place,</L>
<L>Where all is quiet, fit for Contemplation;</L>
<L>And to behold his Makers Will and Grace,</L>
<L>Spending his time in sweetest meditation;</L>
<L>But <HI>cruell minds</HI> are full of <HI>perturbation,</HI></L>
<L>Like to a Market or tumultuous Faire,</L>
<L>Where all is fill'd with noise and molestation;</L>
<L>Durt in the streets, strong clamours in the aire:</L>
<L>Such places are vnfit, for <HI>Graces</HI> sweet repaire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>A <HI>meeke</HI> mind's like vnto <HI>Pernassus</HI> Hill,</L>
<L>Through whose pure aire shines <HI>Phoebus</HI> golden ray;</L>
<L>Whose siluer Channells purest Fountaine fill,</L>
<L>And all the meades bedeck with Lilly's gay:</L>
<L>The Gardens with faire Flowers adorned ay,</L>
<L>And when the Brookes doe murmur any sound;</L>
<L>With much delight sweet <HI>Zephirus</HI> doth play,</L>
<L>And all the Birds vpon the trees around,</L>
<L>Consort with <HI>Muses</HI> nine to make a Heav'nly sound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But a <HI>meeke</HI> mind more pleasing is then all</L>
<L>These <HI>Flowers, Fruits,</HI> or <HI>Musickes</HI> sweet delight;</L>
<L>No fit of <HI>Fury</HI> can that Heart appall;</L>
<L>For as a <HI>Dart</HI> may on the water light,</L>
<L>And hurts it not by any force or might:</L>
<L>So Force, not Fury can <HI>meeke</HI> mind offend,</L>
<L>For it giues way as doth the water light,</L>
<L>Oh happy quiet mind! that doth attend,</L>
<L>With <HI>meeknesse</HI> on Gods bounteous goodnesse to the end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="82" REF="47"/>
As when the glorious <HI>Sun-beames</HI> doe appeare,</L>
<L>All <HI>misty cloudinesse</HI> is turn'd to day,</L>
<L>So where this Grace the heart of men doth cheare,</L>
<L>All passions turbulent are driu'n away:</L>
<L>Then <HI>mecknesse</HI> most her Glory doth display,</L>
<L>When shee hath iustest cause to take offence,</L>
<L>No valour like this Dames behold we may,</L>
<L>Nor any like her modest <HI>Patience;</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>meeke</HI> and <HI>lowly</HI> mind excells all ornaments.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As when the <HI>Lord</HI> of all to vs did come</L>
<L>In humane flesh, he peace and concord bred</L>
<L>Twixt Men and Angells, and made all become</L>
<L>As one, in peace, and quiet in their head;</L>
<L>So where this <HI>meeknesse</HI> doth her Grace dispred,</L>
<L>There <HI>Nations, Neighbours, Kindred,</HI> all we find</L>
<L>Lately at Discord, now fast fettered</L>
<L>In Loue, and Friendships Bands, which firmly bind</L>
<L>No surer band of loue, than <HI>meeke</HI> and gentle mind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In <HI>golden Age,</HI> when as the <HI>Poets</HI> faine</L>
<L>Men, Beasts, Fish, Foule to be at amity,</L>
<L>This <HI>Lady Mecknesse</HI> as a Queene did raigne,</L>
<L>And vnder <HI>Loue</HI> had all Authoritie:</L>
<L>But since the <HI>Iron Age,</HI> which enmity</L>
<L>Hath rais'd in eu'ry Riuer, Towne, and Field,</L>
<L>Shee hath resign'd her place of Soueraigntie</L>
<L>To <HI>Iustice,</HI> and delights now more to yeeld,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Scepters</HI> in age so turbulent to weel'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And for she know's the noble <HI>gentle mind</HI></L>
<L>Most sensible of <HI>wrong</HI> and <HI>iniury:</HI></L>
<L>And few or none can here so <HI>constant</HI> find,</L>
<L>As to dissemble foule indignity</L>
<L>She all requests that loue her company,</L>
<L>Occasions to auoid and not inuite;</L>
<L>Which may prouoke least <HI>iarre</HI> or <HI>simulty,</HI></L>
<L>Aed not like teachy Curres to barke and bite,</L>
<L>Or Frogs, which Poets faine with Bulrushes to fight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="83" REF="47"/>
If thus they cannot, as who ay can here?</L>
<L>Auoid some iniury's of them that reigne,</L>
<L>They must dissemble, and with pleasing cheere,</L>
<L>What they can no wayes shift, faire entertaine:</L>
<L>One ask'd, how such old age he did attaine</L>
<L>In Court; reply'd by bearing Iniury's,</L>
<L>Sometimes remitting, and sometimes againe,</L>
<L>For them gaue thankes, thus surely he that's wise,</L>
<L>By suffring beares, and not prouokes indignities.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And since no earthly Power's so great and firme,</L>
<L>But <HI>Iniury</HI> sometimes will dare to smite,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Wisdom's precepts</HI> so thee ay confirme,</L>
<L>Thou neuer swerue from rules of <HI>Reason</HI> right:</L>
<L>So arm'd the wrongs which on thine armor light,</L>
<L>Shall backe on him that sent the same rebound;</L>
<L>But whom vnarm'd she can prouoke to fight,</L>
<L>Though happily they thinke her to confound,</L>
<L>They sure are to receiue a deepe and festring wound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>He stands not right, whom <HI>Iniury</HI> can bow,</L>
<L>Who ill beare old, doe on them new inuite;</L>
<L>But he that beares the old with <HI>Patience:</HI> how</L>
<L>Shall any new be able him to smite?</L>
<L>He that is <HI>wise</HI> and <HI>valiant</HI> scornes her might,</L>
<L>And by <HI>braue bearing</HI> doth her spite confound,</L>
<L>He best o'recomes that sets by her most light,</L>
<L>Who by <HI>impatience,</HI> addes, is like him found,</L>
<L>That doth, by rending make incurable his wound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In many wrongs 'tis better to be mute,</L>
<L>Than by repeating them, oft very small,</L>
<L>To cause long trouble or a tedious suit,</L>
<L>Whilst all the shame doth on th'auenger fall:</L>
<L>Such better were not mentioned at all:</L>
<L>Inuoke the helpe of <HI>constant Patience,</HI></L>
<L>Whose presence doth all <HI>Iniury's</HI> appall,</L>
<L>And with an equall mind beares all offence,</L>
<L>Or doth despise them in her guiltlesse conscience.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="84" REF="48"/>
Thus many, offring, doe no Iniury's,</L>
<L>Because they are not so conceiv'd or taken;</L>
<L>Oh happy who all wrong can so despise,</L>
<L>With sense thereof ne're to be ouertaken;</L>
<L>Whose vnmov'd <HI>constant</HI> mind is neuer shaken;</L>
<L>So farre from muttring or least murmuring,</L>
<L>He laughs and smiles to see them so mistaken,</L>
<L>Nor's only easie in their <HI>pardoning;</HI></L>
<L>But passeth by them without least <HI>acknowledging.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>He is aboue the reach of <HI>Iniuries,</HI></L>
<L>Who can represse reuenges curst desire,</L>
<L>And to the full repay's his enemies,</L>
<L>Who thus can quench wraths hot iniurious fire.</L>
<L>Yet <HI>holy meeknesse</HI> leads vs a step higher:</L>
<L>Happy who can ascend vnto such height</L>
<L>It is the <HI>summity,</HI> which all admire,</L>
<L>Of highest <HI>vertue,</HI> when we take delight</L>
<L>All <HI>Iniury's</HI> with <HI>Benefits</HI> here to requite.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The jest is lost, if it no laughter moue,</L>
<L>So's Contumely if it be neglected;</L>
<L>He neuer will a valiant Souldier proue</L>
<L>To beare <HI>hot Blow's,</HI> that is with <HI>words</HI> affected:</L>
<L>He sooner is with noisome smells infected,</L>
<L>Who them with open nose doth entertaine;</L>
<L>Than he that stops it, or beares some selected</L>
<L>Preseruatiue for to defend his braine:</L>
<L>So 'tis to stop or ope our eares to proud Disdaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Poets paint <HI>Scylla</HI> with a womans <HI>face,</HI></L>
<L>But like a Dog in neather <HI>parts</HI> and <HI>taile,</HI></L>
<L>Whom <HI>Hercules,</HI> th' <HI>Idea</HI> of all <HI>Grace</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Vertue,</HI> did amongst the monsters quaile,</L>
<L>You giue her Life, if you will heare her raile:</L>
<L>But shut her mouth with patient suffering,</L>
<L>Or stop thine eares, and soone her breath will faile:</L>
<L>Here <HI>Mecknesse</HI> ends, and here I cease to sing,</L>
<L>Shee doth more quiet Rest than all the Vertues bring.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="85" REF="48"/>
<HEAD>MEDITAT. IIII. GODS WORD.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>SO mighty are the <HI>weapons</HI> manifold,</L>
<L>Wherewith our <HI>spirituall Foes</HI> doe vs assaile;</L>
<L>So many stratagems vs to infold,</L>
<L>So many terrours vaine, our hearts to quaile,</L>
<L>That neither <HI>Brestplate, Helmet, Shield</HI> or <HI>Maile</HI></L>
<L>Vs helpe against their Forces can afford;</L>
<L>For if they close with vs, they will preuaile,</L>
<L>Therefore we must vnsheath our <HI>keenest Sword:</HI></L>
<L>Our <HI>weapon spirituall,</HI> ev'n <HI>Gods most holy Word.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Which those that able are to wield aright,</L>
<L>Of farre more Force, and liuely Power find,</L>
<L>Than all the weapons whereof Poets write,</L>
<L>To haue beene wondrous pow'rfull in their kind:</L>
<L>What <HI>Homer</HI> of <HI>Achilles Speare</HI> hath coyn'd,</L>
<L>I not vnfitly to this <HI>Sword</HI> apply;</L>
<L>Whose wounds to heale, no <HI>Balme</HI> could be assign'd,</L>
<L>The <HI>Speare</HI> that hurt, must only remedy;</L>
<L>So whom this <HI>Sword</HI> doth kill, this <HI>Sword</HI> must viuifie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Of wondrous weapons <HI>Heathen Poets</HI> tell</L>
<L>Of <HI>Stygian</HI> Armour, and enchanted Swords;</L>
<L>Whereby small Knights, did monstrous Gyants quell,</L>
<L>Subdude, and raigned ouer them as Lords,</L>
<L>Such fiction to vs good aduice affords,</L>
<L>Against these <HI>Gyants spirituall</HI> to fight,</L>
<L>Our <HI>Fleshly Lusts,</HI> and for to bind in Cords,</L>
<L>Our vaine affections here that take delight,</L>
<L>In doing that is wrong, and leauing that is right.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="86" REF="49"/>
God of all might, that hast vs giu'n this <HI>sword,</HI></L>
<L>Not only <HI>spirituall Battailes</HI> here to fight,</L>
<L>But dost engraue in it, as on record</L>
<L>Thy Rules, whereby we <HI>muster</HI> may aright;</L>
<L>The <HI>Lanthorne</HI> to our paths, our feets best light,</L>
<L>Direct my <HI>Muse</HI> to sing I humbly pray</L>
<L>Of this thy <HI>Word,</HI> by <HI>holy Words</HI> insight,</L>
<L>For but by it, none can aright display</L>
<L>That <HI>Swords</HI> eternall Power, which <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Hell</HI> dismay.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>That <HI>Word,</HI> which in Beginning, by a word</L>
<L>Of Nothing made, Heau'n, Earth, and Creatures all,</L>
<L>And was from all Beginning <HI>God</HI> and <HI>Lord,</HI></L>
<L>Doth not within my <HI>Muses</HI> compasse fall:</L>
<L>That <HI>Word</HI> whereof now meditate I shall,</L>
<L>Is that <HI>reuealed written veritie,</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>first</HI> and <HI>second Testament</HI> we call:</L>
<L>Both which were first declared mightily</L>
<L>By wonders, signes, and miracles from God on high.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For as the <HI>Lord</HI> most mighty wonders wrought,</L>
<L>By him, that publikely did first record</L>
<L>This <HI>sacred Word;</HI> And by his Hand forth brought</L>
<L>His Sonnes from Bondage of a cruell Lord:</L>
<L>So those to whom he did this Grace afford,</L>
<L>Of publishing his <HI>later Testament,</HI></L>
<L>Wrought mighty wonders by this mighty <HI>Word,</HI></L>
<L>To all Beholders great astonishment,</L>
<L>Confirming thus, that they from God aboue were sent.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From whom this Word hath all Authority,</L>
<L>For by the holy Spirits inspiration,</L>
<L>Came <HI>Law,</HI> and <HI>Gospell, Prophets, History,</HI></L>
<L>And all Canonicall wise ordination:</L>
<L>The sacred <HI>Light,</HI> that giues illumination</L>
<L>Vntill the <HI>Day-starre</HI> in our Hearts arise:</L>
<L>Whose heau'nly Wisdome breedeth Admiration</L>
<L>In all their Hearts, that are diuinely wise,</L>
<L>But folly seemes to such as sinne doth blind their ey's.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="87" REF="49"/>
And sure it is a mighty pow'rfull <HI>Word,</HI></L>
<L>If that the sense thereof be right apply'd,</L>
<L>More keene than any sharpe two edged sword,</L>
<L>And eu'n the Soule and Spirit doth diuide:</L>
<L>By it are all our Hearts intents descry'd,</L>
<L>The ioynts and marrow it doth smite in sunder,</L>
<L>No Creature from her sight it selfe can hide,</L>
<L>All high exalted things it bringeth vnder:</L>
<L>And 'gainst all disobedience soundeth out like thunder.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This was the <HI>Sword,</HI> wherewith our valiant <HI>Head,</HI></L>
<L>When he was tempted in the Wildernesse,</L>
<L>And with a six-weekes-fast sore weakened,</L>
<L>Did free himselfe from Hells malitiousnesse:</L>
<L>When first on him his <HI>Enemy</HI> did presse,</L>
<L>He vs'd the <HI>hilts</HI> himselfe for to defend,</L>
<L>But when he could not thus his Foe represse;</L>
<L>Loe he the point, against his Breast doth bend;</L>
<L><HI>Behind me, Satan,</HI> All, Gods worship must attend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Those, that will vse aright this <HI>holy Word,</HI></L>
<L>Must not the <HI>letter,</HI> but the <HI>sense</HI> apply;</L>
<L>Or else they vse the <HI>Scabbard</HI> for the <HI>Sword,</HI></L>
<L>Wherewith none euer wun the Victory:</L>
<L>It is the <HI>Mystery of Iniquitie,</HI></L>
<L>To take the <HI>letter,</HI> and to leaue the <HI>sense,</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>forge</HI> of <HI>Antichrists Idolatry,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>feigned Rocke,</HI> the <HI>Key's</HI> of Heau'n from whence</L>
<L>He claimes to <HI>vniuersall</HI> Power, Obedience.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>A multitude of words, but all one <HI>sense,</HI></L>
<L>And tending all to that grand mystery,</L>
<L>To which all mysteries haue reference,</L>
<L>Mans personall vnion with the <HI>Deity:</HI></L>
<L>The which to God was knowne infallibly</L>
<L>In his election, ere the worlds Foundation,</L>
<L>And all the Bookes it seemes to typifie</L>
<L>From <HI>Genesis</HI> vnto the <HI>Reuelation,</HI></L>
<L>Sublime, transcendent mystery's of mans Saluation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="88" REF="50"/>
How should my <HI>Muse</HI> these hope to comprehend,</L>
<L>In this short fainting breath of meditation;</L>
<L>Which doth all humane wit and skill transcend,</L>
<L>Whose each <HI>word</HI> hath an hid signification:</L>
<L>Each <HI>letter, pricke,</HI> and <HI>point,</HI> an obseruation,</L>
<L>All fauouring of Wisdome, true, diuine,</L>
<L>And far beyond mans weake inuestigation,</L>
<L>In it such rare profound deepe Learning shine,</L>
<L>A Volume is not able to expound a Line.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Fie then on those, that swolne with vaine ambition</L>
<L>To sway all <HI>Kingdomes</HI> with materiall sword;</L>
<L>Preferre before this <HI>Word,</HI> their vaine <HI>tradition,</HI></L>
<L>Which nought but vainnesse, like themselues afford:</L>
<L>Their names be wiped out of the Record</L>
<L>And Booke, which all thy <HI>Saints</HI> names doth containe;</L>
<L>That thus doe seeke to vilifie this <HI>Word,</HI></L>
<L>Which to accomplish Gods owne <HI>Sonne</HI> was slaine,</L>
<L>And thousand <HI>Martyrs</HI> spent their bloud it to maintain.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>So deale with Prophets, that to hide conspire</L>
<L>From simple people, Food spirituall;</L>
<L>Which they, as new borne Babes do milke desire,</L>
<L>That they may grow vp to be strong and tall:</L>
<L>I grant as <HI>Mothers breasts</HI> doe, best of all</L>
<L>Nourish the <HI>Child,</HI> so doth <HI>Gods holy Word,</HI></L>
<L>Which from our <HI>Mother-Churches</HI> breasts doth fall,</L>
<L>Best nourishment vnto her Babes afford;</L>
<L>So as it be sincere: Else be it all abhor'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>True Angells <HI>Food!</HI> sweet <HI>Manna,</HI> pure, diuine,</L>
<L>My <HI>Spirits dayly bread,</HI> and nourishment,</L>
<L>Which wanting <HI>shee</HI> doth hunger, statue and pine,</L>
<L>And yeeld to Body's sleshly Regiment:</L>
<L>My Soule with <HI>fat</HI> and <HI>marrow</HI> is content,</L>
<L>When I with ioyfull lips thy praises sing,</L>
<L>And feed upon thy Lawes great wonderment;</L>
<L>Which to subiection doth my Body bring,</L>
<L>And makes the <HI>Spirit</HI> rule, and order like a King.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="89" REF="50"/>
The <HI>Spirit</HI> it compares to <HI>Looking Glasse,</HI></L>
<L>Where we our Faces Spots may all behold;</L>
<L>But soone out of our memory they passe,</L>
<L>Like to a Dreame or Tale that's idlely told:</L>
<L>But who his <HI>mind</HI> thereon doth daily hold,</L>
<L>Doth walke in perfect Law of <HI>Liberty,</HI></L>
<L>Which to him doth apparantly vnfold</L>
<L>His Soule and Fleshes least deformity,</L>
<L>And sheweth him the meanes the same to rectifie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Eu'n as the <HI>Raine</HI> indiffereutly doth fall,</L>
<L>Vpon the fruitfull, and the barren ground;</L>
<L>So preached is this <HI>Heau'nly Word</HI> to all,</L>
<L>Though to the faithlesse, it be fruitlesse found,</L>
<L>Oh! where this <HI>Word</HI> doth powerfully sound,</L>
<L>The strongest holds of sin it shatters downe;</L>
<L>And things most high exalted doth confound,</L>
<L>It's smallest-Seed in lowly Valley sowne,</L>
<L>Est suddenly is to a mighty Cedar growne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>It is reported of the siluer Doue,</L>
<L>She neere the purest Streames doth most delight;</L>
<L>In which <HI>Shee</HI> may espy the shadow moue,</L>
<L>Of towring Faulcon, or the rauenning Kite;</L>
<L>Whereby she is forewarn'd to scape by flight,</L>
<L>From cruell Hawkes, that seeke her for a pray!</L>
<L>So if in spirituall streames we take delight,</L>
<L>Our spirituall Foes we there discouer may,</L>
<L>That so our Soules forewarn'd, like Doues might flye away.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Most glorious Sun-shine! where it doth enlight,</L>
<L>More comfortable Light hath showne;</L>
<L>But when <HI>Shee</HI> doth withdraw her Beames, is night</L>
<L>And darknesse spirituall, far grosser growne,</L>
<L>Than that which three day's was to <HI>Pharaoh</HI> knowne;</L>
<L>Hard-hearted <HI>Pharaoh,</HI> thou that didst despise,</L>
<L>This Word and all the wonders by it showne,</L>
<L>Eu'n all thy plagues light on them that deuise,</L>
<L>To hide this <HI>heau'nly Light;</HI> from simple peoples ey's.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="90" REF="51"/>
It is the <HI>doore,</HI> whereby the pastours may</L>
<L>Spiritually ascend into their Fold,</L>
<L>Those that doe enter in another way</L>
<L>We doe as rauenning wolues and robbers hold:</L>
<L>This <HI>Word's a touchstone,</HI> which doth try from Gold</L>
<L>All mettalls base, Inuentions of mans braine,</L>
<L>Of which such store at <HI>Latium</HI> now are sold,</L>
<L>Not for the <HI>Flocks,</HI> but for the <HI>Shepheards</HI> gaine,</L>
<L><HI>Masse, Dirges, Pardons, Trentalls,</HI> and <HI>Traditions</HI> vaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Nothing describe her nature better will,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Touchstone:</HI> th'vse of which simplest may learne,</L>
<L>But one had need of cunning Gold-smiths skill;</L>
<L>True <HI>Touchstone</HI> from a false one to discerne,</L>
<L>Oh how did those noble <HI>Berreans</HI> earne!</L>
<L>To try those things that <HI>Paul</HI> deliuered,</L>
<L>The things which our Saluation did concerne,</L>
<L>By that which in the <HI>Scriptures</HI> they had read,</L>
<L>The <HI>Scriptures</HI> that the Spirit had canonized.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Who from the simple people these doe hide,</L>
<L>Deale as with <HI>Israel</HI> did the <HI>Cananite,</HI></L>
<L>Who no <HI>Smith</HI> suffer'd in their Coasts t'abide,</L>
<L>To make a weapon for an <HI>Israelite:</HI></L>
<L>Therfore no speare, nor sword when they should fight,</L>
<L>But in <HI>Sauls</HI> hands and <HI>Ionathans</HI> were found,</L>
<L><HI>Chams</HI> hellish pollicy, most deu'lish sleight,</L>
<L>To hold in Ignorance and Bondage bold,</L>
<L>By taking way such helpes as Liberty propound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As first, God by his <HI>Word</HI> and <HI>Spirit</HI> wrought,</L>
<L>And fashion'd all things in this worlds <HI>Creation,</HI></L>
<L>So by this <HI>Word</HI> and <HI>Spirit</HI> he hath brought,</L>
<L>All things to passe in this our <HI>renouation;</HI></L>
<L>And as he for our Bodyes preseruation,</L>
<L>Hath here materiall Bread and Wine prepar'd,</L>
<L>So's Word and Spirit is for sustentation</L>
<L>Of all our Soules, that rightly it regard,</L>
<L>Such neuer need of thirst and hunger be afeard.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="91" REF="51"/>
As Appetite's a <HI>Signe</HI> of Body's Health,</L>
<L>So of the Soules is hunger of his Word;</L>
<L>And as to him that seeketh <HI>store of wealth,</HI></L>
<L>A Myne can best what he desires afford:</L>
<L>So he that <HI>spirituall treasures</HI> vp would hoard,</L>
<L>Come to this <HI>sacred Word</HI> where he shall find,</L>
<L>It doth a world of mystery's record,</L>
<L>The richest jewells to adorne the mind,</L>
<L>True treasure's no where else reuealed to mankind.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For it's the <HI>Megazine</HI> where pastours haue,</L>
<L>All gems and treasures to enrich their fold;</L>
<L>The store-house, whence they all abundance craue</L>
<L>Of liuing food, their Lambs in plight to hold;</L>
<L>The <HI>armory,</HI> from whence they may he bold,</L>
<L>To fetch all armes and weapons to withstand</L>
<L>The wolues which them infest: and to vphold</L>
<L>Truth and the right, against all <HI>Satans</HI> Band,</L>
<L>Falfe Heretickes, base Lusts, and worlds encroaching hand.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But as the <HI>Manna</HI> that from Heau'n was sent,</L>
<L>Bred <HI>Wormes,</HI> if wrong, but <HI>Food</HI> if rightly vsed,</L>
<L>So breeds this <HI>Word</HI> our Soules due nourishment▪</L>
<L>But neuer-dying wormes if once abused:</L>
<L>He that for <HI>Egypts Flesh-pots</HI> hath refused,</L>
<L>This <HI>Heau'nly Food,</HI> And mans tradition vaine,</L>
<L>His base false lying Legends rather chused,</L>
<L>Shall whilst this Flesh betweene his jawes remaine,</L>
<L>Be with his great and wealthiest chosen <HI>shauelings</HI> slain.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Fountaine of liuing water!</HI> which doth more</L>
<L>And faster spring, as it is emptied,</L>
<L>Most <HI>fruitfull Vine,</HI> which bringeth still more store,</L>
<L>Of heau'nly grapes, as they are gathered.</L>
<L>Th' <HI>epistle of Heau'ns King,</HI> which rightly read,</L>
<L>Brings vs the gladsome tidings of Saluation;</L>
<L>Whose <HI>harder sense strong men</HI> may chuse as bread,</L>
<L>The plainer <HI>babes</HI> may suck for sustentation;</L>
<L>We both aright concort by heau'nly meditation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="92" REF="52"/>
The <HI>Sword</HI> that doth spiritually diuide</L>
<L>From vs, all manner of concupiscence:</L>
<L>Our <HI>youths reformer,</HI> and our ages <HI>guide,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Transcending reason,</HI> more <HI>than reason</HI> sence;</L>
<L><HI>Truths ground,</HI> the <HI>Fountaine</HI> of <HI>Intelligence;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Loues complement,</HI> the root of <HI>humblenesse;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Faiths hold,</HI> the <HI>Rule</HI> of all <HI>Obedience:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Hopes anchor,</HI> and the <HI>path of Rrighteousnesse,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>ladder</HI> which we climbe from hence to <HI>Happinesse.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Would you haue more? it is the <HI>milke sincere,</HI></L>
<L>Which can alone quench Hells eternall fire;</L>
<L>The <HI>only Daughter,</HI> to <HI>her Mother</HI> deare,</L>
<L>The mystery which <HI>Angells</HI> doe admire,</L>
<L>The <HI>sweetest song</HI> of blessed heau'nly Quire:</L>
<L>Whose Praise eu'n all the heau'nly Powers sing;</L>
<L><HI>Apostles, Prophets, Martyrs,</HI> all desire</L>
<L>With all their might to strike this lofty string,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Dauid</HI> in one Psalme a thousand times doth ring.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As <HI>Iacob</HI> with the Angell wrestled,</L>
<L>Nor let him goe without a blessing would;</L>
<L>So when words mysteries by vs are read,</L>
<L>We striue and struggle for the meaning should:</L>
<L>A goodly strife if we contending could</L>
<L>Hold out, till what we seeke we doe obtaine;</L>
<L>As <HI>Incense</HI> doth no pleasing smell vnfold,</L>
<L>Nor Spice till it be in a Morter braine,</L>
<L>So are <HI>words</HI> mysteries, till study makes them plaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This makes the lips of <HI>Christs</HI> endeared Bride,</L>
<L>Than any <HI>Hony combe</HI> to drop more sweet;</L>
<L>And vnderneath her daintiest tongue, abide</L>
<L><HI>Hony</HI> and <HI>Milke;</HI> The <HI>Hony</HI> is most meet</L>
<L>To heale the wounds Sin makes from head to feet,</L>
<L>The <HI>Milke</HI> for <HI>Babes;</HI> Loe thus her either Brest,</L>
<L>Which like two twining Roes doe equall meet,</L>
<L>Yeeld most abundant Food, if softly prest,</L>
<L>And both with <HI>Roses</HI> sweet and <HI>Lilly's</HI> faire are drest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="93" REF="52"/>
This is the <HI>Tower of Dauid,</HI> which is built</L>
<L>By th'holy <HI>Spirit,</HI> of most costly stone;</L>
<L>Whereon a <HI>thousand Shields</HI> doe hang all guilt</L>
<L>With <HI>swords</HI> and <HI>weapons</HI> for the <HI>mightiest One:</HI></L>
<L>This is the Priuie <HI>Garden,</HI> where alone</L>
<L>The <HI>Spouse</HI> with <HI>Bridgroome</HI> doth her selfe delight,</L>
<L>Planted with <HI>Nardus, Saffron, Cinamon,</HI></L>
<L>And all trees good for medicine, tast, or sight,</L>
<L>Through which doth flow a well of liuing waters bright.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Most heau'nly <HI>Paradise!</HI> where tree of Life</L>
<L>My Soule most heau'nly Fruits doth daily bring;</L>
<L>Fit for the <HI>Lamb</HI> to walke in, with his wife,</L>
<L>And for the <HI>Spouse</HI> most <HI>Angell</HI>-like to sing,</L>
<L>The Soueraigne <HI>Grace</HI> and <HI>Bounty</HI> of her <HI>King;</HI></L>
<L>Where though I often seeke to hide in vaine,</L>
<L>Mee from my Nakednesse discouering,</L>
<L>My blessed <HI>Bridegroome</HI> calleth me againe,</L>
<L>And clothes me with the <HI>Robes of Lamb</HI> most righteous slaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There <HI>Manna</HI>-like (Loe) eur'y Fruit doth tast,</L>
<L>Iust as we would; none iustly can complaine;</L>
<L>Though his vnweeded garden lieth wast,</L>
<L>God send to good and bad alike his raine:</L>
<L>Let him, where thornes and bryers doe remaine</L>
<L>Take heed, how he this heau'nly deaw accuse;</L>
<L>It is the root, thy euill heart and vaine,</L>
<L>Which doth the sweetnesse of this raine abuse;</L>
<L>Which for to water weeds and nettles doth it vse.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>How should this <HI>Word</HI> be sweet vnto the mouth?</L>
<L>Wherein is nought but Gall and Bitternesse!</L>
<L>Or how should heau'nly deaws from West or South,</L>
<L>Moisten that Heart, which by maliciousnesse</L>
<L>More hardned is, than Flint in wickednesse:</L>
<L>Alas what Corne can sweetest <HI>raine</HI> forth bring,</L>
<L>In Ground that choked is with worldlinesse,</L>
<L>Where as the thornes vp with the wheat doe spring,</L>
<L>And from the root suck vp all heau'nly nourishing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="94" REF="53"/>
Ev'n as a <HI>Lamp,</HI> without supply of Oyle</L>
<L>Being daily had, is soone extinguished;</L>
<L>So though we seeme to prosper here awhile</L>
<L>In <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Grace,</HI> all's soone abolished</L>
<L>Vnlesse that they be daily nourished,</L>
<L>With <HI>Hearing, Reading, Prayer, Meditation,</HI></L>
<L>In vaine it with our <HI>mouths</HI> is vttered,</L>
<L>Except it in our hearts makes habitation;</L>
<L>And we expresse it in our liues and conuersation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh let this holy <HI>Words</HI> most heau'nly Fire?</L>
<L>My secret, sound affections inflame,</L>
<L>And burne vp all vaine fleshly worlds desire,</L>
<L>Oh blessed <HI>Fire!</HI> like that in <HI>Bush</HI> did flame,</L>
<L>But neuer did consume or burne the same;</L>
<L>The fire whereby <HI>Gold Catholike</HI> is tride,</L>
<L>And <HI>straw,</HI> and <HI>'stubbled errour</HI> brought to <HI>shame,</HI></L>
<L>In whom this inward fire doth ay refide;</L>
<L>He well the scorching heat of outward may abide.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But as no <HI>fleshly ey's</HI> can here behold,</L>
<L>The glorious <HI>Sunne,</HI> but by that <HI>Suns</HI> sweet sight;</L>
<L>So no man <HI>vnderstanding,</HI> may be bold</L>
<L>To know this <HI>Word,</HI> but where it doth enlight.</L>
<L><HI>Lord! in thy Light, then let mee see this Light,</HI></L>
<L>Whereby I may my sinfull life amend;</L>
<L>And in thy Statutes set my whole delight,</L>
<L>And wholly in the way's of wisdome tend,</L>
<L>So shall my foot stand fast, with ioy vnto the end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For as the <HI>snow</HI> and <HI>raine</HI> from Heav'n descend,</L>
<L>But neuer thither doe returne againe</L>
<L>Till that be done; for which thou didst them send,</L>
<L>To make the fruitfull soile fit for the graine;</L>
<L>So neuer shall thy <HI>Word</HI> returne in vaine,</L>
<L>But sure accomplish what thou dost intend;</L>
<L>Then moisten daily, with this heav'nly raine</L>
<L>My hardned Heart, that all my powers may bend,</L>
<L>To glorifie thy name, who dost these showers send.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="95" REF="53"/>
How should he feare to want his <HI>daily Food,</HI></L>
<L>Who with this <HI>Word of Life</HI> is nourished;</L>
<L>Or who can thirst that drinketh of his bloud,</L>
<L>Let not this <HI>Word</HI> be vnderualued:</L>
<L>He that is with this <HI>Heau'nly Manna</HI> fed,</L>
<L>Eates of the fattest of Gods spirituall store;</L>
<L>Wherewith <HI>Christs</HI> tender <HI>Spouse</HI> is fostered,</L>
<L>Till <HI>Shee</HI> growes strong, and faire to stand before</L>
<L>Her <HI>Head,</HI> And neuer thirst nor hunger any more.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This <HI>Words</HI> Eternall, therefore hath no end;</L>
<L>I no <HI>beginning,</HI> nor <HI>conclusion</HI> find.</L>
<L>I could herein my Life and Spirits spend,</L>
<L>It doth so feed my Soule and glad my mind:</L>
<L>But now my <HI>Muse</HI> to Prayer is assign'd,</L>
<L>And bow's her <HI>knees</HI> to end <HI>her Meditation</HI></L>
<L>With <HI>Praise</HI> to <HI>Him,</HI> who <HI>first</HI> mine Heart inclin'd,</L>
<L>To seeke this Heau'nly Food of <HI>Contemplation,</HI></L>
<L>I hope vnto his <HI>Glory,</HI> and mine owne <HI>Saluation.</HI></L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>MEDITAT. V. <HI>Of</HI> PRAYER.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>AS wise experienc'd, valiant <HI>Generall,</HI></L>
<L>When's Souldier armed is from Foot to Head,</L>
<L>And hath at hand his Shield, and Sword, and all</L>
<L>His Armour, with his Belt fast buckled;</L>
<L>Yet him into the Battell will not lead,</L>
<L>Till he be taught his Sword aright to wield,</L>
<L>To take Aduantages, if offered,</L>
<L>And to defend his Body with his Sheild;</L>
<L>Then him thus taught and train'd he leads into the Field.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="96" REF="54"/>
So wee, that in these <HI>Spirituall Battells</HI> fight,</L>
<L>Not with fraile Flesh, but Principality's;</L>
<L>And powers of exceeding foce and might,</L>
<L>Besides their treason, plots, and policies,</L>
<L>Must first be taught in Armes to exercise;</L>
<L>That all in <HI>complete Armour</HI> ordered</L>
<L>And taught how to assault our enemy's,</L>
<L>They with our <HI>Sword</HI> may be discomfited,</L>
<L>And we from Hell and Bondage safe deliuered.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I of this <HI>Military Art</HI> doe know</L>
<L>No Tutor like to <HI>holy supplication;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Prayer</HI> who vse of all our Armes doth show,</L>
<L>The <HI>Serieant Maior</HI> of our <HI>Militation:</HI></L>
<L>Diuinest <HI>Prayer,</HI> holy <HI>Meditation,</HI></L>
<L>Whereby with God we haue sweet conference</L>
<L>About the mysteries of Mans <HI>Saluation;</HI></L>
<L>And call the Angells downe for our defence</L>
<L>'Gainst Flesh's, Worlds and Deuils hostile violence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Prayer,</HI> who though her knees bow in the dust,</L>
<L>Yet are her vpper parts aboue the sky;</L>
<L>And doe into th' Almighty's presence thrust,</L>
<L>To craue of all we want a new supply:</L>
<L>Which like to clouds of incense vp doe flye,</L>
<L>If offered by his Sonnes sweet mediation;</L>
<L>Whose iust requests, no <HI>Father,</HI> can deny:</L>
<L>Oh offer mine then, That this Meditation</L>
<L>May be directed by thy Spirits illumination.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>True <HI>Prayer</HI> is the opening the desire</L>
<L>Ev'n of our Heart and Soule to God aright;</L>
<L>Them powring out to him, that doth require</L>
<L>We should lay open all before his sight:</L>
<L>The <HI>Sacrifice</HI> wherein he doth delight,</L>
<L>A sure defence to him that right doth pray;</L>
<L>The <HI>Scourge,</HI> wherewith we <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Satan</HI> smite,</L>
<L>And powers all and policies gainsay,</L>
<L>Our surest <HI>Refuge</HI> in each dangerous Affray.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="97" REF="54"/>
For <HI>Christian Souldier</HI> neuer kneeleth downe,</L>
<L>And lifts his heart vp towards Heav'n to pray,</L>
<L>But all his Foes spirituall, him arowne</L>
<L>Assault and labour him herein to stay:</L>
<L>Then is it time for him about to lay,</L>
<L>With his <HI>sharp Sword</HI> to put them all to flight,</L>
<L>And for to arme each part, lest they him slay,</L>
<L>With <HI>Greaues, Belt, Brestplate, Shield</HI> and <HI>Helmet</HI> bright,</L>
<L>In <HI>Faith, Hope, Patience, Truth</HI> and <HI>Righteousnesse</HI> to fight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>By rules of Art, I <HI>Prayer</HI> may diuide</L>
<L>To these two Heads, <HI>Thankesgiuing, Inuocation;</HI></L>
<L>The second I in three doe subdiuide,</L>
<L><HI>Petition, Intercession, Deprecation:</HI></L>
<L>First seekes Gods Glory, and our owne Saluation;</L>
<L>The second doth for others make petition,</L>
<L>(So <HI>Christ</HI> doth intercede by mediation)</L>
<L>By last we doe intreat for sins remission,</L>
<L>And be deliuer'd from all ill, and superstition.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But as the <HI>Sauldier,</HI> be he ne're so strong;</L>
<L>Well arm'd, and skil'd in points of <HI>Schoole</HI>-defence;</L>
<L>If that his <HI>spirit faint,</HI> is laid along:</L>
<L>So if we in our Armes haue confidence,</L>
<L>And not relye on Gods sole Prouidence;</L>
<L>His Spirit which helpeth our infirmities,</L>
<L>And doth instruct to pray with reuerence,</L>
<L>Sending vp heart and soule by sighs and cry's,</L>
<L>For all our Armes and strength our Foes will vs surprise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For <HI>Spirit</HI> is the cause efficient,</L>
<L>Of all our <HI>prayers</HI> that to Heav'n ascend;</L>
<L>Though <HI>Faith</HI> be the <HI>Internall instrument,</HI></L>
<L>By which we all things aske, doe apprehend:</L>
<L>With <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Spirit, Prayer</HI> Heav'n doth rend,</L>
<L>And whatsoeuer shee in <HI>Christ</HI> his name</L>
<L>Doth aske, the <HI>Father</HI> downe to vs will send;</L>
<L>This <HI>Pagans</HI> saw (though otherwise to blame)</L>
<L>That <HI>Christians</HI> nothing beg, but they obtaine the same.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="98" REF="55"/>
All Blessings spirituall, and temporall</L>
<L>Publike and priuate, for our Selues and Friends;</L>
<L>All that in this life, or a better fall</L>
<L>To vs almighty God for <HI>Prayer</HI> sends:</L>
<L>When Heau'n is shut vp, that no dew descends,</L>
<L>If we forsake our sins, and pray for raine,</L>
<L>The Heau'n on vs abundant showers spends:</L>
<L>Though Foes vs captiue from our City's traine,</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Prayer</HI> makes vs Free, and brings vs home againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>If Dearth, Drowth, Pestilence be in the Land,</L>
<L>Or City's be besieg'd by enemies,</L>
<L>Then if the cause thereof, we vnderstand</L>
<L>Our sins, And seeke by <HI>Prayer</HI> remedy,</L>
<L>God will be mercifull accordingly:</L>
<L>Yea if a Stranger, of an <HI>Heathen</HI> Nation,</L>
<L>Doe call on God by <HI>Prayer</HI> heartily;</L>
<L>And of his life doe seeke a reformation,</L>
<L>His <HI>Prayer</HI> shall be heard, by <HI>Christ</HI> his mediation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus <HI>Prayer</HI> is for all things profitable,</L>
<L>If her true obiect she doe neuer misse;</L>
<L>One God, who gracious, willing is and able,</L>
<L>And of our Heart the only Searcher is:</L>
<L>All things that are in Heau'n and Earth are his,</L>
<L>We must, no person in the <HI>Deity,</HI></L>
<L>Omit, when as we pray to him for Blisse</L>
<L>All workes externall, in the Trinity</L>
<L>Are one, though their internall haue variety.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Diuinest <HI>Pater-noster!</HI> whose one Word,</L>
<L>In it more heau'nly matter doth containe;</L>
<L>Than one whole hour's babbling can afford,</L>
<L>Suddaine abortiues of an idle braine:</L>
<L>With tedious turnings, repetitions vaine,</L>
<L>Out tumbling all that in their stomach lies,</L>
<L>Which often goe beyond this <HI>Prayers</HI> straine,</L>
<L>As if they were more feruent or more wise,</L>
<L>Than he that for our <HI>patterne</HI> did it first deuise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="99" REF="55"/>
Pure <HI>Prayer</HI> made by serious <HI>meditation,</HI></L>
<L>Or by this <HI>holy patterne</HI> rightly pend;</L>
<L>Briefe spirituall, sublime ejaculation,</L>
<L>With feruent Fury doth to Heau'n ascend,</L>
<L>And to the marke like swiftest arrow tend:</L>
<L>God is in Heau'n, thou kneelest on the ground,</L>
<L>To him therefore no rash petitions send;</L>
<L>Therein let <HI>matter</HI> more than <HI>words</HI> abound,</L>
<L>And inward <HI>sighs</HI> and <HI>groanes,</HI> than outward <HI>plaints</HI> and sound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But <HI>Prayer;</HI> though by thy two mighty wings</L>
<L>Of <HI>Loue,</HI> and <HI>Meeknesse,</HI> thou to Heau'n canst sore,</L>
<L>And come in presence of the <HI>King of Kings,</HI></L>
<L>By pard'ning wrongs, and giuing to the <HI>poore;</HI></L>
<L>Presume not on thy <HI>merits</HI> ere the more</L>
<L>That Brightnesse who doth sit vpon the Throne,</L>
<L>Angells not able are to stand before;</L>
<L>Alas how dar'st thou then there stand alone,</L>
<L>Without the <HI>mediation</HI> of the <HI>Holy One.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Like <HI>birdlime merits,</HI> so thy wings besmeare,</L>
<L>That thou not able art to take thy slight</L>
<L>Aboue the Firmament, or to come neere</L>
<L>That euershining Lamp of Heau'nly Light;</L>
<L>Which ought thy <HI>Prayers</HI> to direct aright</L>
<L>In <HI>Knowledge, Meeknesse,</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI></L>
<L>By which we feele and haue and inward sight</L>
<L>Of our vnworthinesse, and misery,</L>
<L>And seeke else where, for worth and true felicity.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Eu'n to that <HI>liuely Fountaine</HI> of the <HI>Lamb,</HI></L>
<L>Which is a deepe well, wondrously profound,</L>
<L>From which, by <HI>Prayer,</HI> breaking vp the dam,</L>
<L>We draw vp waters which doe there abound:</L>
<L>The depth of this <HI>rich Well,</HI> no Grace can sound,</L>
<L>But feruent <HI>Prayer,</HI> when as <HI>Shee</HI> doth desire</L>
<L>To coole her thirst, with waters therein found,</L>
<L>wherewith if once we coole our thirst, like Fire</L>
<L>The more we drinke thereof, the hotter's our desire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="100" REF="56"/>
An Oxes lowing, barking of a Dog,</L>
<L>Grunting of Swine, doth more the Lord delight;</L>
<L>Than <HI>Prayers</HI> which the World and Flesh so clog,</L>
<L>They come not from vs with a Heart and Sprite,</L>
<L>And as no salue or medicine hath might,</L>
<L>To heale the wound which Iron doth containe:</L>
<L>So <HI>Prayer</HI> neuer profiteth that wight,</L>
<L>In whom Hypocrisie or guile remaine;</L>
<L>For these still fester deeper to the Patients paine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>God is our Soules Physitian, and know's best</L>
<L>What for her sicknesse is best remedy;</L>
<L>And therfore when we needfull things request</L>
<L>Of him, for this our lifes necessitie,</L>
<L>He, better then his Patient, can descry</L>
<L>What is most fit to keepe him from the graue,</L>
<L>And cure him of his spirituall malady,</L>
<L>Wherefore when we receiue not what we craue,</L>
<L>We know <HI>Christ</HI> better know's, than we what need we haue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Gods <HI>Word's</HI> the <HI>Sword,</HI> whereby our Lord doth sway</L>
<L>And rules his Church here as he is a King;</L>
<L>As <HI>Priest,</HI> he offers praises, and doth pray;</L>
<L>As <HI>Prophet</HI> he glad tidings vs doth bring,</L>
<L>Most wisely teaching and admonishing:</L>
<L>Thus, <HI>Aaron</HI>-like, to God he doth present</L>
<L>Our <HI>prayers, praises, tythes,</HI> and <HI>offering,</HI></L>
<L>(For <HI>Aarons</HI> Office <HI>Christs</HI> did represent)</L>
<L>And makes them giue to God an acceptable sent.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Prayer is mans best fence, the Angells ioy,</HI></L>
<L><HI>The Deuills torture, Gods sweet sacrifice,</HI></L>
<L>We by her meanes all blessings here enioy,</L>
<L>By <HI>prayer</HI> we obtaine here to be wise;</L>
<L>By <HI>prayer</HI> with th' Almighty we aduise,</L>
<L>By reading he doth answere vs againe;</L>
<L>But our <HI>Lip-labour</HI> he doth all despise,</L>
<L>Ah what doe then those simple people gaine?</L>
<L>Which in a tongue vnknowne doe mutter praiers vaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="101" REF="56"/>
Oh! when the <HI>Spirit</HI> with vnderstanding pray's,</L>
<L>And ev'n the Heart with sighs and groanes vp sends</L>
<L>To him that willing, able is alway's</L>
<L>Vs from Hell, Death and danger to defend:</L>
<L>Then, as a <HI>Bullet</HI> doth the <HI>welkin</HI> rend,</L>
<L>Blowne with the force of Powder and of Fire;</L>
<L>So doe our <HI>Prayers</HI> vp to Heau'n ascend,</L>
<L>By Zeale and Force of spirituall desire,</L>
<L>Where they of God obtaine all things they can require.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Moses</HI> gain'st <HI>Amalec</HI> doth more preuaile</L>
<L>By <HI>Prayer,</HI> and by <HI>holding vp his hands,</HI></L>
<L>Then mighty <HI>Iosuah,</HI> though he doth assaile</L>
<L>Them with his strong and most selected bands:</L>
<L>At <HI>Iosuahs</HI> short <HI>sweet Prayer</HI> the <HI>Sun</HI> still stands,</L>
<L>Till hee's auenged of his enemy's;</L>
<L><HI>Elisha</HI> all the Host of God commands</L>
<L>Him to relieue in his necessity's,</L>
<L>Ev'n Fiery Horse and Charrets keep him where he lies.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Prayer</HI> is able by plaine strength to wring</L>
<L>From <HI>hand-breadth Cloud,</HI> an <HI>Ocean</HI> of <HI>Raine;</HI></L>
<L>And Captiues out of <HI>Babylon</HI> to bring,</L>
<L>To worship in <HI>Hierusalem</HI> againe.</L>
<L>The <HI>Angell</HI> striv'd with <HI>Iacob</HI> but in vaine;</L>
<L>Without a Blessing he will not vnloose;</L>
<L><HI>Zenacharibs</HI> whole Host was spoyl'd and slaine,</L>
<L>By <HI>Hezekias Prayer:</HI> when we close</L>
<L>With <HI>God</HI> by <HI>Prayer,</HI> we our holds must neuer loose.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>Rains-horns, Trumpets,</HI> which seav'n Priests did blow,</L>
<L>Most liuely doe strong <HI>Prayer</HI> represent;</L>
<L>Which with the peoples shout did ouerthrow</L>
<L>Proud walls of <HI>Iericho,</HI> to astonishment</L>
<L>Of all the wicked, that therein are pent:</L>
<L>This was the musick <HI>Aarons</HI> sonnes did sound</L>
<L>With Trumpets, when to warre the people went;</L>
<L>When <HI>Daniel</HI> in Lyons Den was found,</L>
<L>True <HI>Prayer</HI> from their jawes him kept both safe and sound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="102" REF="57"/>
Tis not our words God lookes on, but the mind;</L>
<L>Not to the place, but to the true intent</L>
<L>In dungeon <HI>Ieremy</HI> did comfort find;</L>
<L>And <HI>Iob</HI> vpon the dunghill takes content;</L>
<L>Three Children in the fiery Fornace pent,</L>
<L>Are heard, when <HI>Praises</HI> they to God doe sing:</L>
<L>The <HI>Thiefe</HI> from <HI>Crosse</HI> as gratefull <HI>Prayers</HI> sent,</L>
<L>As from his <HI>Temple Solomon</HI> the King,</L>
<L>The <HI>Hermits Cell</HI> may oft as loud as <HI>Steeple</HI> ring.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Not that from <HI>publike Prayer</HI> I purloine,</L>
<L>Of which <HI>Gods house</HI> hath her denomination;</L>
<L>Where Priests and peoples hearts and voices ioyn,</L>
<L>To teare the <HI>skies</HI> with cryes and supplication:</L>
<L>Oh Force vnited of a Congregation!</L>
<L>In Gods owne <HI>house of Prayer</HI> gathered,</L>
<L>For <HI>Praise, Petition,</HI> or for <HI>Deprecation,</HI></L>
<L>God nought denyeth so petitioned,</L>
<L>And wee thus from all euill are deliuered.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>When <HI>Peter</HI> slept with chaines in prison bound,</L>
<L>On each side Souldiers, Keepers at the doore,</L>
<L>The <HI>Church</HI> doth pray, though <HI>hee</HI> sleepe fast and sound,</L>
<L>And <HI>God him</HI> loosed from his chaines therefore:</L>
<L>And when the Angell lighteth him before,</L>
<L>The Iron Gate opes of his owne accord:</L>
<L><HI>Pauls, Dauids, Samuells,</HI> a thousand more</L>
<L>Of <HI>Prayers,</HI> you may find vpon record,</L>
<L>All which may seem to bind toth' <HI>Peace,</HI> our angry Lord.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I all conclude with his most heav'nly one,</L>
<L>Who did in day's of his <HI>Humility;</HI></L>
<L>With <HI>loudest cry's in Spirit sigh and groane,</HI></L>
<L>For Freedome of that dire calamity,</L>
<L>Which came on him for our Iniquitie:</L>
<L>And though he <HI>Legions</HI> could of <HI>Angells</HI> call,</L>
<L>To saue him from inhumane cruelty,</L>
<L>Yet Lamb-like did before his <HI>Shearer</HI> fall,</L>
<L>Submitting to his Fathers will and pleasure all.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="103" REF="57"/>
Without vs, God will nothing for vs doe,</L>
<L>We therefore must prepare to fight alway;</L>
<L>And without God we can nor stand nor goe,</L>
<L>And therefore must be alwayes swift to <HI>pray:</HI></L>
<L>If these so pray'd when Foes did them assay,</L>
<L>When <HI>Flesh</HI> and <HI>Bloud</HI> with Flesh and Bloud did fight;</L>
<L>What shall we in this dangerous great affray,</L>
<L>When we encounter with spirituall might,</L>
<L>Which in his Agony did <HI>Christ</HI> our Head affright.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But ah! we at our first conuersion <HI>pray</HI></L>
<L>Most feruently oft, for the nouelty,</L>
<L>But after negligent, cold sleeping say</L>
<L>Our <HI>Pater-noster</HI> in security:</L>
<L>Thou sleep'st secure, but ah! thine Enemy</L>
<L>Doth watch thee thyn ev'n napping to surprise,</L>
<L>We then to God withall our hearts doe cry,</L>
<L>When as no thoughts withdraw vs otherwise;</L>
<L>Alas! but few or none pray often in this wise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh! that a man of base and filthy mould,</L>
<L>Should dare fall downe before Gods glorious Throne,</L>
<L>His wants and imperfections to vnfold,</L>
<L>And haue his heart like <HI>Nabals</HI> dead as stone;</L>
<L>When <HI>Angells</HI> that come neere that holy One,</L>
<L>Are faine their face to couer with their wings;</L>
<L>So bright his Glorious Maiesty hath showne,</L>
<L>Who is the <HI>Lord of Lords,</HI> and <HI>King of Kings;</HI></L>
<L>The searcher of our reines, and tryer of all things.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>When I no longer able am to fight,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Moses</HI> let me lift vp hands and <HI>pray</HI></L>
<L>Against the inuisible <HI>Amalekite,</HI></L>
<L>That spiritually doth seeke my soule to slay:</L>
<L>When I with <HI>Faith,</HI> two words, <HI>Our Father,</HI> say;</L>
<L>I pardon beg for Sin, Freedome from paine;</L>
<L>Gods <HI>Heyre and Sonne, Christs Brother,</HI> I that day▪</L>
<L>Am made, and gifts of <HI>Holy Ghost</HI> doe gaine,</L>
<L>Then let me neuer mumble ouer words in vaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="104" REF="58"/>
But I confesse, though I doe often proue,</L>
<L>There is no comfort like this one, to <HI>pray;</HI></L>
<L>That is bestow'd on man from Heav'n aboue,</L>
<L>Yet find I Satan prest and busie ay,</L>
<L>Mee in this holy duty to assay,</L>
<L>By wandring Thoughts, and vaine imaginations,</L>
<L>Which oft'doe lead my Mind so far astray,</L>
<L>I am bereau'd of Heav'nly cogitations,</L>
<L>And change for idle fancy's, holy meditations.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But Prayer doth so please my <HI>Muses</HI> straine,</L>
<L>That I omitted haue of <HI>Praise</HI> to sing,</L>
<L>The <HI>Sacrifice</HI> we offer here againe,</L>
<L>For all the <HI>Bounty</HI> of our heav'nly King:</L>
<L>I liken her to <HI>Prayers</HI> either wing,</L>
<L><HI>Forgiuing wrongs,</HI> and <HI>Almes vnto the poore</HI></L>
<L>Our holy liuely spirituall Offering,</L>
<L>Of Body, Soule, Heart, Tongue, and all our store,</L>
<L>With true Obedience to God for euermore.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Whilst here of <HI>Benefits</HI> no end we find,</L>
<L>How should we euer make an end of <HI>praise;</HI></L>
<L>Oh happy Bands! that vs for euer bind,</L>
<L>Ev'n when our Soules and Body's <HI>Chrisi</HI> shall raise,</L>
<L>Our <HI>praise</HI> shall be eternall like our day's:</L>
<L>He that his time in <HI>praise</HI> and <HI>hymnes</HI> would spend,</L>
<L>I him referre to <HI>Dauids</HI> heav'nly Layes,</L>
<L>Diuinely by the holy Spirit, pend,</L>
<L>My <HI>Muse</HI> now out of Breath, cannot this Mount ascend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh let my voyce and heart together ioyne!</L>
<L>God of the lips accepts not, but the heart;</L>
<L>Grant that my life in Holinesse may shine,</L>
<L>That <HI>Conscience</HI> may euer beare apart;</L>
<L>Presumptuous man! that darst thy Maker thwart,</L>
<L>To poure out fond <HI>petitions</HI> base and vaine,</L>
<L>When thou consid'rest before whom thou art,</L>
<L>Him that doth all leud <HI>lying lips</HI> disdaine.</L>
<L>And <HI>Hypocrites</HI> rewardeth with infernall paine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="105" REF="58"/>
If <HI>prayer</HI> be right, pure, sincere and meeke;</L>
<L>It neuer empty shall returne againe;</L>
<L>For God will either grant vs what we seeke,</L>
<L>Or giue vs that shall be our greater gaine:</L>
<L><HI>Mine Heart, mine heart Lord! doth reioyce amaine,</HI></L>
<L>Ay in thine House of <HI>Prayer</HI> to abide;</L>
<L>Where Swallow's build, and Sparrow's are full faine</L>
<L>To lay their young ones by thine <HI>Altars</HI> side,</L>
<L>Mee neuer let the <HI>Spirit</HI> of <HI>Prayer</HI> be deny'd!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But since I ought to <HI>pray</HI> continually,</L>
<L>How should my Pen of <HI>Prayer</HI> make an end;</L>
<L>My <HI>Sauiour praying</HI> on the Crosse did dye;</L>
<L>With <HI>Prayer Steuen</HI> his Soule to Heav'n did send,</L>
<L>But I began with <HI>Prayer;</HI> let mee end</L>
<L>With <HI>Praises</HI> to the Horne of my Saluation,</L>
<L>Who sure I hope his blessed <HI>Spirit</HI> did send,</L>
<L>To guide mee in this holy <HI>Meditation,</HI></L>
<L>Which fills my Tongue with Praise, &amp; Heart with Admiration.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="59"/>
<PB REF="59"/>
<P>VRANIA, OR THE HEAVENLY <HI>MUSE.</HI></P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM STANSBY. 1625.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="60"/>
<HEAD>TO MY EVER HONORED FRIEND, M. IOHN MAYNARD, one of the Gentlemen of his Maiesties Priuie Chamber in Ordinarie.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Y deare <HI>Vrania</HI> wilt thou now forsake</L>
<L>My <HI>Cottage,</HI> and to <HI>Court</HI> thy selfe betake?</L>
<L>Dost hope thou <HI>there,</HI> as <HI>here</HI> shalt find retire?</L>
<L>I cannot but thy simplenesse admire.</L>
<L>But since thou needs wilt goe, I'le thee commend</L>
<L>vnto the <HI>Muses</HI> most familiar Friend;</L>
<L>Who (had not his <HI>great Princes</HI> Loue and Grace</L>
<L>Him brought from <HI>Muses Groues</HI> to's <HI>Royall place)</HI></L>
<L>Might on his <HI>Front</HI> haue worne thy <HI>Crowne of Bays,</HI></L>
<L>And beene the Prince of <HI>Poets</HI> in his dayes.</L>
<L>Hee'le leaue all profit, pleasure, honour gaine,</L>
<L>The <HI>heav'nly Muse</HI> alone to entertaine;</L>
<L>Oh happy Court! most blessed Courtiers yee,</L>
<L>That from the <HI>Muses Springs</HI> transplanted bee,</L>
<L>This 'tis makes Arts, and Learning so increase,</L>
<L>Hence followeth all our happinesse and Peace:</L>
<L>The <HI>Muses</HI> needs must dance when <HI>Courtiers</HI> sing,</L>
<L><HI>All follow the example of the King.</HI></L>
</LG>
<P>Yours truly deuoted.</P>
<P><HI>R. A.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="60"/>
<HEAD>VRANIA.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Bout the <HI>Season Lawyers</HI> tongues doe rest,</L>
<L>And make for <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Haruest.</NOTE> <HI>Ceres</HI> honour long vacation;</L>
<L>I (freed from tumults which me erst opprest,)</L>
<L>Dispose my mind to holy Meditation:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And thinking how I might a <HI>subiect</HI> find,</L>
<L>Delightfull, pleasing, sweet and profitable;</L>
<L>My heart to better, and inrich my mind</L>
<L>And tongue acquaint, with Phrases delectable.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As Traueller that meets with diuers wayes,</L>
<L>I long deliberate to chuse the best</L>
<L>And fairest Path to <HI>Mount,</HI> where <HI>Lawrell Bayes</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Numbers</HI> crowne that are diuinely drest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>One while I sought in <HI>measures Comicall</HI></L>
<L>To maske the <HI>Graces</HI> all vpon the <HI>Stage;</HI></L>
<L>Or in a <HI>Tragique Scene</HI> vp <HI>Ghosts</HI> to call</L>
<L>Of <HI>Worthys</HI> slaine by cruell <HI>Tyrants</HI> rage:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Anon I would the <HI>Vnion</HI> celebrate,</L>
<L>Which made a <HI>Damaske Rose</HI> of Red and White,</L>
<L>The fairest <HI>Flower</HI> of <HI>Brittons</HI> happy State;</L>
<L>Which <HI>Roses</HI> then, now <HI>Kingdomes</HI> doth vnite.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I thought likewise to sing that happy Peace</L>
<L>Our Iland-world enioyeth by this <HI>Vnion,</HI></L>
<L>Which makes our honour, riches, strength increase,</L>
<L>And haue with Heav'nly <HI>Arts</HI> such free communion.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then I th'admired Prudence would rehearse</L>
<L>Of <HI>Brittons Scepter-swaying Solomon,</HI></L>
<L>Matter which would immortalize a Verse,</L>
<L>And saue such <HI>Splendour from</HI> obliuion:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Prone was my flesh the <HI>winged wag</HI> to sing</L>
<L>Of wanton <HI>Venus,</HI> and her Bitter-sweet,</L>
<L>That glads the <HI>Tast,</HI> but doth the Bowells wring</L>
<L>For chaster eares a Subiect far vnmeet.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="110" REF="61"/>
Whilst wauering thus in fruitlesse inquisition,</L>
<L>Yet vnresolv'd of any course I roue,</L>
<L>Behold I see an heav'nly <HI>Apparition,</HI></L>
<L>Some <HI>Herauld</HI> doubtlesse from the <HI>Queene of Loue;</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Her gesture and her grace Angelicall,</L>
<L>With wings whereby her selfe to heav'n shee reares,</L>
<L>Her countenance faire, sweet, celestiall,</L>
<L>Her voyce like Musicke of the heav'nly Spheares.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>A glorious Garland crown'd her golden head,</L>
<L>Bedeck'd with all the Flowers, sweet, and gay,</L>
<L>That could on <HI>Tempes Plaines</HI> be gathered,</L>
<L>By <HI>learned Sisters</HI> in their fairest <HI>May.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Immortall Flowers, which spring and flourish ay,</L>
<L>And ay their <HI>verdure</HI> and sweet sent retaine,</L>
<L>Like <HI>heav'nly Arts,</HI> which neuer doe decay,</L>
<L>But by their vsing greater glory gaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>On shoulders hangs her <HI>azure mantle</HI> light,</L>
<L>With siluer spangles all adorned faire,</L>
<L>Twinkling like brightest Starres in frosty night,</L>
<L>As they are moued by the gentle aire:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Her nether parts to hide from vulgar eye</L>
<L>A Kirtle like <HI>Heav'n Conopy</HI> did couer;</L>
<L>Where all the <HI>Signes</HI> of Heav'n embroidred fly,</L>
<L>And all the <HI>Graces</HI> seeme about to houer.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I, saith shee, am <HI>Vrania</HI> to thee sent,</L>
<L>From thine adored <HI>Mistresse, Queene of Loue;</HI></L>
<L>I rauish Soules aboue the Firmament,</L>
<L>That they in <HI>Numbers</HI> like the Spheres may moue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>With <HI>Siluer Key</HI> I doe vnlocke the mind</L>
<L>Of <HI>Mortalls</HI> sealed vp in Ignorance,</L>
<L>That oft their Soules aboue the Stars they find,</L>
<L>When Bodyes lye on ground as in atrance.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For I the <HI>Spirit</HI> am of <HI>Contemplation,</HI></L>
<L>Th' <HI>Ehxir</HI> of <HI>Ambrosia</HI> diuine,</L>
<L>Pure <HI>Angells food,</HI> Soules sweetest delectation,</L>
<L>The <HI>Helicon,</HI> where both the <HI>Sisters nine.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="111" REF="61"/>
<HI>Art</HI> teacheth <HI>Art, Experience Policy,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Practice</HI> guild's the tongue with <HI>Eloquence;</HI></L>
<L>But none reach lofty straines of <HI>Poesie,</HI></L>
<L>That haue them not by heav'nly insluence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Hence 'tis that Clerks which gaine immortall praise,</L>
<L>By their deepe learned Eloquence in <HI>Prose,</HI></L>
<L>Their <HI>numbers</HI> cannot to such honour raise,</L>
<L>As one that scarce the Rules of Grammer knows:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>It is beyond the reach of will or wit,</L>
<L>A holy <HI>Flame</HI> of <HI>heav'nly Loues</HI> pure fire,</L>
<L>A soaring, high, transcendent, furious fit,</L>
<L>Whose <HI>Life, light, heate,</HI> and strength loue doth inspire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Loue's</HI> her Beginning, and her End is <HI>Loue,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Loue</HI> is the Soule, and Life of <HI>Poesie;</HI></L>
<L>No Poeme without <HI>Loue</HI> did euer proue,</L>
<L>No more then Musicke without <HI>Harmony.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>Loue</HI> of Honour, and of Cheualry,</L>
<L>So rais'd the old blind Greeks Heroique quill; <NOTE PLACE="marg">Homer.</NOTE></L>
<L>Hee lifts <HI>Achilles</HI> valiant acts more high,</L>
<L>Than his that conquer'd all the world at will. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Alexander.</NOTE></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The loue of Ciuill, and Self-gouernment</L>
<L>Him taught to frame such an exact <HI>Ulisses;</HI></L>
<L>That hee who by this Patterne did inuent,</L>
<L>Roomes glorious author, such perfection misses. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Aeneas. Virgil.</NOTE></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Eglogues of Loue</HI> are <HI>Muses</HI> first delights,</L>
<L>Till thorough <HI>country pleasures</HI> shee doth come,</L>
<L>To sing in state of <HI>Honour, Armes,</HI> and <HI>Knights,</HI></L>
<L>And out of old <HI>Troys</HI> ashes raise vp <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>wanton,</HI> all whose speeches were in Verse,</L>
<L>Who sings in Fictions all <HI>Dame natures</HI> story; <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ouid.</NOTE></L>
<L>In ev'ry sentence doth his <HI>Loue</HI> rehearse,</L>
<L>But ah base Lust obscureth all his glory.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>So Loues old rigid <HI>Cato</HI> vertues lore,</L>
<L>He makes them dance the measures cunningly;</L>
<L>To loues <HI>Lucretius Dame natures</HI> store,</L>
<L>Hee turnes all <HI>Pliny</HI> into <HI>Poetry.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="112" REF="62"/>
And as the obiect of our Loue exceeds,</L>
<L>So strikes the <HI>Muse</HI> on high or lower strings;</L>
<L>Who lowly late did maske in Shepheards weeds,</L>
<L>In high Heroiques of <HI>Armes,</HI> and <HI>Honour</HI> sings. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Spencer.</NOTE></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>My <HI>Darling Bartas,</HI> who on <HI>Angells</HI> wings;</L>
<L>Beholds the Six Day's of the Worlds Creation,</L>
<L>Was so in loue with Heav'n and heauenly things,</L>
<L>Hee wholly on them fixt his Contemplation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And wen he on the Seuenth Day comes to rest,</L>
<L>He them all orders to his Makers Glory:</L>
<L>Doubtlesse he fram'd a new world in his brest,</L>
<L>Whereof he so Diuinely sings the story.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>It was this heav'nly Loue that did incite,</L>
<L>The warlike <HI>Shepheard</HI> such sweet notes to sing, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Dauid.</NOTE></L>
<L>His loue vnto Gods <HI>Statutes</HI> day and night,</L>
<L>Doe strike so loud his Harpe and Violls string.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And as <HI>Wind-Instrument</HI> to him repay's</L>
<L>That sounds it sweetest, musicke, for his breath;</L>
<L>So sings this Psalmist <HI>Hymnes,</HI> and <HI>Heav'nly Lay's</HI></L>
<L>To him that giues him <HI>Spirit,</HI> till his <HI>Death.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh heav'nly Musicke, which, the rage could quell</L>
<L>Of <HI>Cis</HI> his sonne, possest with euill Spirit</L>
<L>Pure Hymns from God, sweet mercy to compell,</L>
<L>When foulest Sins Hell-fire doe commerit.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sweet <HI>Shepheard,</HI> when thou singest forth thy Flocks,</L>
<L>The <HI>Angells</HI> all admire thy heav'nly <HI>Lay's;</HI></L>
<L>Thy musicke moues, stones, trees, and senslesse stocks,</L>
<L>When thou diuin'st of Christs most happy day's.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet those hands that so gently touch a string,</L>
<L>Can Lyons, Beares, and Wolues in peeces teare;</L>
<L>And quell the proud Philistine with a sling,</L>
<L>From whom the <HI>Host</HI> of <HI>Israel</HI> runs for feare.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Loue at his birth him dandled in her Lap,</L>
<L>Whilst all the <HI>Graces Lullaby's</HI> doe sing;</L>
<L>Shee fed him with <HI>Ambrosia</HI> for Pap,</L>
<L>And rais'd him from a <HI>Shepheard</HI> to a <HI>King.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="113" REF="62"/>
And thou my Sonne, although thy <HI>Breath</HI> be faint;</L>
<L>I cannot but commend thy good desire,</L>
<L>With their diuine <HI>Essays</HI> thy <HI>Muse</HI> acquaint;</L>
<L>Which may be fewell to thy heav'nly fire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet though thou straine <HI>Inuention, Art,</HI> and wits,</L>
<L>And fills thy Verses with thy wisest <HI>Says,</HI></L>
<L>They shall not liue, except some holy fits,</L>
<L>Thy Soule aboue the Heav'ns bright <HI>Tapers</HI> raise.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thy <HI>Soule</HI> whose <HI>Beeing</HI> is Celestiall fire,</L>
<L>Must like the <HI>Saints</HI> be rapt vp in a trance;</L>
<L>And <HI>extased</HI> with holiest desire,</L>
<L>If thou thy Verse wouldst vp to <HI>Heav'n</HI> aduance.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For as none but the Spirit of a man,</L>
<L>The secrets of that <HI>Spirit</HI> can disclose;</L>
<L>So none attaine sublimest numbers can,</L>
<L>Except a holy <HI>Fury</HI> them compose.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And as no <HI>Actor</HI> well can play the <HI>King,</HI></L>
<L>That is not one in his imagination:</L>
<L>So none can <HI>Vertues</HI> pure <HI>Ideas</HI> sing,</L>
<L>That suits his mind not to his meditation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Poets</HI> are like to <HI>Organs</HI> sounding shrill</L>
<L>With fingers touch, so long as they be full:</L>
<L>But as on empty ones; in vaine's our skill,</L>
<L>Ev'n so are Verses, without <HI>Fury,</HI> dull.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And as none on the Harpe sweet tunes can sound,</L>
<L>Till hee by Art hath set in Tune each string;</L>
<L>So none high-rapted numbers can compound,</L>
<L>Till's soule be tun'd by spheare-like rauishing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sith then to <HI>Numbers life</HI> from Heav'n is sent,</L>
<L>Oh rarest <HI>Spirits!</HI> how dare you abuse</L>
<L>Them, to dishonour him, who hath them lent</L>
<L>To's Glory, and your <HI>Chast delight</HI> to vse?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Shall your <HI>diuinest</HI> spirits stoupe so low,</L>
<L>To make your-selues base slaues to Lust and Sin;</L>
<L>And let your pure <HI>Pyrenean Fountaines</HI> flow</L>
<L>In stinking <HI>Channells</HI> all defil'd within.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="114" REF="63"/>
Still will you fawne on <HI>Fooles,</HI> and <HI>Greatnesse</HI> flatter?</L>
<L>And fill the world with wanton idle groanes?</L>
<L>Still shall your <HI>Muse</HI> like Pyes this one song chatter,</L>
<L>Of Lust, which brings corruption to the bones?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Ist not enough you burne in lustfull flame,</L>
<L>Except you eke corrupt youth prone to vice?</L>
<L>And <HI>strumpet</HI>-like hang out your <HI>signes of shame,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Passengers</HI> to folly to intice?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For numbers, notes, and tunes such power haue,</L>
<L>They soonest on the noblest Spirits seaze;</L>
<L>Whereon they doe their formes and sounds engraue;</L>
<L>As Seales on wax imprinted are with ease.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And that's the Reason, graue and wiser <HI>Sages,</HI></L>
<L>Haue banish't from their <HI>coasts</HI> lasciuious rymes,</L>
<L>When <HI>Poets</HI> chast and vertuous in all ages,</L>
<L>Haue beene as <HI>Priests</HI> and <HI>Prophets</HI> in their times.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Would you the <HI>Genius</HI> of your <HI>Fury</HI> raise,</L>
<L>And change your <HI>fleshly</HI> to <HI>spirituall Flame,</HI></L>
<L>Such matter would immortalize your praise</L>
<L>And leaue behind you a most honour'd name.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Your <HI>Verse</HI> would be admir'd, you honoured</L>
<L>As <HI>Secretarys</HI> to the <HI>King</HI> of <HI>Kings,</HI></L>
<L>For first the <HI>Prophets</HI> words thus numbered,</L>
<L>To handle <HI>mystery's</HI> and <HI>holy things.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus <HI>Dauid</HI> all his <HI>Psalmes</HI> by <HI>measure sings,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Moses</HI> the freedome from <HI>Egyptian</HI> thrall,</L>
<L>And <HI>Miriam</HI> vpon a Timbrell rings</L>
<L>Gods Praises; <HI>Iudith</HI> the <HI>Assirians</HI> fall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>They sang for Ioy, but <HI>Iob,</HI> and <HI>Ieremy</HI></L>
<L>Sing, when they with <HI>afflictions</HI> most are prest;</L>
<L>A <HI>Nunc Dimittis</HI> was the <HI>Poefie</HI></L>
<L>The Swan-like <HI>Simeon</HI> warbled in his brest:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Magnificat</HI> the blessed <HI>Virgin</HI> sings;</L>
<L>The <HI>Angells,</HI> Glory sing to God on high:</L>
<L>And <HI>Martyrs,</HI> bound to stakes with Iron strings</L>
<L>Sing Praises whilst in <HI>Flames</HI> their Body's fry▪</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="115" REF="63"/>
So burnes their <HI>zealous heate</HI> of <HI>Loues</HI> purefire,</L>
<L>They feele no outward for the inward flame:</L>
<L>So long as they haue <HI>Bowells</HI> to respire</L>
<L>They neuer cease to praise Gods holy name:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But he that seemes an <HI>Angell</HI> of the light,</L>
<L>More easie <HI>children</HI> of the <HI>light</HI> 'tabuse,</L>
<L>In Verse doth also his <HI>delusions</HI> write,</L>
<L>And for his <HI>Oracles</HI> did numbers chuse:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And for he know's that <HI>Loues</HI> pure heav'nly fire,</L>
<L>Is that by which we Gods whole Law fulfill;</L>
<L>His <HI>Prophets</HI> all must chant of Lusts desire,</L>
<L>And make great <HI>Ioue</HI> be rul'd by <HI>Cupids</HI> will.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus bloud corrupt th'inchanter doth instill</L>
<L>With lustfull <HI>Fire</HI> to scal'd youths hotter veines;</L>
<L>And poisons with this <HI>Copperis</HI> the quill</L>
<L>Of Heathen <HI>Poets,</HI> in their gentle straines.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Who to make more authenticke Ribauldry,</L>
<L>Doe faigne their <HI>Gods</HI> therein to take delight,</L>
<L>Where though they <HI>Natures secrets</HI> wittily</L>
<L>Oft vaile! yet thus to Lust they youth inuite.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I know in first pure streames of <HI>Poesie,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Muses Bath</HI> was chast as <HI>Pheebes shrine,</HI></L>
<L>The Virgin Graces, <HI>Ioues</HI> chast progeny,</L>
<L>And <HI>Pallas</HI> chast, and vertuous, as diuine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> was then with <HI>Almas</HI> title graced,</L>
<L>And lov'd her <HI>Spouse</HI> plaine <HI>Vultan, Mars</HI> scarce knew:</L>
<L>Whom though shee oft in nuptiall bed imbraced,</L>
<L>Twas not for wanton pleasure but for due.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This <HI>Poetry,</HI> my Sonnes, reuiv'd againe,</L>
<L>To mortalls would restore the golden times,</L>
<L>And for your Brow's immortall Lawrells gaine,</L>
<L>And to their ancient honour raise your <HI>Rimes.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But <HI>Satan</HI> since another patterne set,</L>
<L>Which he would haue all his to imitate;</L>
<L>And like a Fowler draweth to his Net</L>
<L><HI>Poore Birds</HI> with merry notes and pleasing <HI>Bait.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="116" REF="64"/>
But thou that seek'st <HI>Gods Glory,</HI> not thine owne,</L>
<L>And striv'st to quench, not quicken lustfull <HI>Flame;</HI></L>
<L>Chuse these diuine ensamples I haue showne,</L>
<L>And guild not with faire words the foulest shame.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>When thou do'st feele <HI>Loue's Fury</HI> in thy breast,</L>
<L>What better theame or matter canst thou take;</L>
<L>Than sing his <HI>Loue</HI> who <HI>Heav'n</HI> and <HI>Earth</HI> possest,</L>
<L>Yet here himselfe for <HI>Loue</HI> a <HI>Slaue</HI> did make.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>Loue</HI> betweene the <HI>Bridgroome</HI> and his <HI>Deare,</HI></L>
<L>Were matter to immortalize a Song:</L>
<L>No Man or Angell euer yet did heare</L>
<L>Diuiner Musicke from a mortall tongue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This is a deepe, broad, boundlesse Ocean;</L>
<L>A high <HI>Pernassus</HI> of sweet <HI>Meditation;</HI></L>
<L>No holy Fury diue the bottome can,</L>
<L>Nor reach the height thereofby <HI>contemplation.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Soule-rapting Tunes:</HI> when <HI>Turtles</HI> voyce doth sound</L>
<L>The <HI>Songs</HI> of <HI>Sion,</HI> in a <HI>Holy Land.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Sweet accents,</HI> making Hills and Mountaines bound,</L>
<L>And <HI>Cedars</HI> of the <HI>Forrest</HI> trembling stand.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This better will thy heart; enrich thy mind;</L>
<L>Here profit thou shalt reape with sweet delight.</L>
<L>Here thou refreshing <HI>Nectar</HI>-streames shalt find,</L>
<L>To coole thy thirst, and cleare thy dimmer sight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>For thus thou safely maist enioy delight,</L>
<L>The pleasure which shall last for euermore;</L>
<L>Vaine Worldly <HI>Pleasures</HI> leaue men ere their night,</L>
<L>But when the iudgement comes, they run before.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These heav'nly precepts sweetned by her voyce,</L>
<L>So rauished my Soule with delectation:</L>
<L>My <HI>Muse</HI> at quiet since doth sole reioyce,</L>
<L>And take delight in heav'nly contemplation.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And though I neuer hope to touch with hand,</L>
<L>Much lesse my head with <HI>Lawrell Bough</HI> adorne,</L>
<L>May I yet mine owne Passions thus command</L>
<L>My Cost and Tilt's short of my Crop of Corne.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="64"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Authors</HI> Vow or wish, at the Consecration of a Chap∣pell newly founded by the Right Ho∣norable WILLIAM Lord <HI>Maynard,</HI> at his House in <HI>Eston</HI> in <HI>Essex.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>LEt others heape vp <HI>Titles, Lands,</HI> and <HI>store,</HI></L>
<L>Their <HI>names on earth,</HI> for euer to maintaine!</L>
<L><HI>Thou to</HI> thy <HI>house</HI> dost <HI>surer honour</HI> gaine,</L>
<L>By adding of this <HI>Consecrated Floore:</HI></L>
<L>Where <HI>Thou</HI> and <HI>Thine</HI> may euer him adore</L>
<L>That <HI>Proud</HI> throw's downe, and <HI>Humble</HI> men doth raise,</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Father</HI> built the <HI>Palace</HI> in his day's,</L>
<L>But leaues Gods <HI>house</HI> vnto his <HI>prudent Sonne;</HI></L>
<L>Who <HI>Numa</HI>-like now plants <HI>Religion,</HI></L>
<L>Where <HI>Romulus</HI> the first <HI>Foundation</HI> lay's.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This <HI>Leauen</HI> makes the whole <HI>Lump</HI> to endure,</L>
<L>Shis <HI>Salt</HI> to <HI>Thee</HI> and <HI>Thine</HI> shall season all,</L>
<L>And gainst thy <HI>Foes</HI> shall be a <HI>Brasen Wall:</HI></L>
<L>This shall <HI>Thee waking</HI> keepe most safe and sure,</L>
<L>And nigh this <HI>Altar</HI> thou shalt <HI>sleepe</HI> secure:</L>
<L>By this <HI>Thy Honour</HI> ay continue shall,</L>
<L>And Blessed make <HI>Thy Names memoriall:</HI></L>
<L>(Alas! <HI>this worlds</HI> vaine, seeming, <HI>glittring Glory</HI></L>
<L>Is <HI>lubrike, full of hazard, transitory)</HI></L>
<L>What's built on this <HI>Foundation</HI> cannot fall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>So long as <HI>Sions Temple's</HI> vndefil'd,</L>
<L>The <HI>line</HI> of <HI>Dauid</HI> doth the <HI>Scepter</HI> sway;</L>
<L>But suddenly are <HI>captiue</HI> led away,</L>
<L>When <HI>Altars</HI> they with <HI>Idols</HI> had defil'd;</L>
<L>Wherefore they wise did <HI>Gods house</HI> rebuild,</L>
<L>When out of <HI>Babylon</HI> they were translated:</L>
<L>Then since <HI>Thou</HI> wisely has determinated</L>
<L>Thine <HI>House</HI> and <HI>Honour</HI> by <HI>Gods Church</HI> to raise;</L>
<L>Hee <HI>Blissings</HI> send, so long as <HI>You</HI> him <HI>praise,</HI></L>
<L>So may both stand for ay <HI>vnruinated!</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Be it like <HI>Sions Mount</HI> inaugurated,</L>
<L>Which is by <HI>Sions MOVNTAIGNE</HI> Consecrated!</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="65"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Muses Health,</HI> To the Right Honourable, WLLIAM, Lord <HI>Maynard,</HI> at the Consecration of his Chap∣pell at <HI>Eston</HI> Lodge in <HI>Essex.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THis building thus adorn'd, and rais'd in state,</L>
<L>Shall now be made a Chappell consecrate:</L>
<L>Embleme of <HI>Adam,</HI> whom as God did rowle</L>
<L>First vp in clay, next breath'd a liuing soule,</L>
<L>So to these faire materialls preparation,</L>
<L>A Spirit shall be giuen by Consecration:</L>
<L>Not stol'n from <HI>Iupiter,</HI> (as ports tell</L>
<L><HI>Prometheus</HI> did, for which he hangs in Hell:)</L>
<L>Nor yet a <HI>sparke</HI> of <HI>strange</HI> or <HI>common fire,</HI></L>
<L>Which brought on <HI>Aarons</HI> sonnes consuming ire;</L>
<L>But <HI>coales</HI> on <HI>Gods owne Altar</HI> kindled,</L>
<L>By right succession to vs fostered:</L>
<L>The sum is, that, the <HI>Bishop</HI> doth inspire</L>
<L>Into this <HI>Edifice</HI> an <HI>holy fire;</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>liuing flame,</HI> which neuer shall goe out,</L>
<L>So long as they, which tend it are deuout:</L>
<L>But aye, thereby shall safe and quiet rest,</L>
<L>As <HI>swallowes</HI> which besides is build their nest.</L>
<L>Oh may this fire within these walls indure,</L>
<L>So long as <HI>Neptunes</HI> waues this <HI>Ile</HI> immure:</L>
<L>And as from <HI>Mountaines</HI> comes that wholesome breath,</L>
<L>Which healthfull makes the <HI>Valleys</HI> all beneath:</L>
<L>So from this <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Bi∣shop <HI>Mon∣taigne</HI></NOTE> MONTAIGNE health come and saluation,</L>
<L>Vnto the Founder, and his generation:</L>
<L>Let Prophets, Priests, in Prayers all combine</L>
<L>To make this House a Blisse to Thee and Thine:</L>
<L>And when by their deuotions ioy'nd, this <HI>flame</HI></L>
<L>Is kindled; let thy <HI>Priests</HI> maintaine the same</L>
<L>And offer vp thy prayers day and night,</L>
<L>Like <HI>fumes of Incense,</HI> in th' Almighties sight;</L>
<L>Oh <HI>force vnited,</HI> of a <HI>Congregation</HI></L>
<L>That ioyne in prayer at a <HI>Consecration;</HI></L>
<L>With these my <HI>Muse</HI> (now thine) shall beare a part,</L>
<L>And whilst they pray by booke, shee'le pray by hart.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="65"/>
<P>THE CONVERTS CONQVEST.</P>
<Q><BIBL>PSAL. 119. V. <HI>Ultimo.</HI></BIBL>
<HI>I haue gone astray like a sheepe that is lost: oh seeke thy seruant, for I doe not forget thy Commandements.</HI></Q>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM STANSBY. 1625.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="66"/>
<HEAD>TO THE MOST SINCERELY, RELIGIOVS, AND TRVLY Vertuous: Mistresse SARAH AR∣GAL, Wife to IOHN ARGAL of <HI>Badew</HI> Esquire.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">L</SEG>East I be deem'd a thiefe, I will disclose;</L>
<L>I turn'd to <HI>Verse</HI> what you gaue me in <HI>Prose:</HI></L>
<L>In so few lines I neuer yet did find</L>
<L>More heav'nly Comforts to a grieued mind:</L>
<L><HI>Mans sinfull Heart, Hells Malice, Grace diuine,</HI></L>
<L>Is intermixed so in ev'ry <HI>Line.</HI></L>
<L>I praise God, I this speake with feeling Sense,</L>
<L>God grant the <HI>Reader</HI> like experience!</L>
<L>Good publish't, doth more good, by being knowne,</L>
<L>Wherein I seeke <HI>Gods glory,</HI> not mine owne:</L>
<L>Of <HI>Reading</HI> and of <HI>Writing's</HI> but one end,</L>
<L><HI>Repent, beleeue, for sake Sinne</HI> and <HI>amend.</HI></L>
</LG>
<P>Your true vnfeigned Friend,</P>
<P><HI>R. A.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="66"/>
<HEAD>THE CONVERTS CONQVEST.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Certaine <HI>Christian</HI> which had often bin</L>
<L>Tempted, and by his weaknesse ouertaken</L>
<L>To his great sorrow, with one selfe same sin,</L>
<L>At last sate downe as if he were forsaken;</L>
<L>Where of sins bondage first he doth complaine,</L>
<L>And then himselfe thus comforteth againe:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From my all-seeing God I cannot flye,</L>
<L>Still in my loathed sins I may not lye;</L>
<L>Yet ought I not of mercy to despaire,</L>
<L>Yet dare I not for Grace to God repaire▪</L>
<L>Pray would I, but I cannot it intend;</L>
<L>Repent I doe, but not my life amend:</L>
<L>I to beleeue desirous am, yet doubt,</L>
<L>In this lewd wicked custome holding out;</L>
<L>God is by me dishonoured, whilst I</L>
<L>Professe to serue him true and faithfully:</L>
<L>Disples'd, whilst I prouoke him to his face;</L>
<L>Both griev'd and quenched is his Spirit of <HI>Grace;</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>Graces</HI> I abated, withered, find,</L>
<L>My sense benum'd; besotted is my mind,</L>
<L>My memory dull'd, more strong grows <HI>Satans</HI> dart,</L>
<L>My Soule's aduentred, hardned is my hart;</L>
<L>I grow in Sin rich, poore in Goodnesse, Grace,</L>
<L>My head's vex'd, Conscience is in wofull case;</L>
<L>My calling stain'd, crack'd credit, Time mispended,</L>
<L>My strength consum'd, and my God offended:</L>
<L>As doth my sin, my burthen doth increase;</L>
<L>My pain's inlarged, troubled is my peace.</L>
<L>I sigh, but sorrow not aright, would faine</L>
<L>Be rid of it, but soone returne againe:</L>
<L>I grieue, not weepe; Lord! could I from it part,</L>
<L>Forsake, confesse it with a broken hart.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>How farre aduenture, Lord! how long shall I</L>
<L>Dare to prouoke thy powerfull Maiesty?</L>
<L><PB N="122" REF="67"/>
How long shall he forbeare? how often might</L>
<L>He cut mee off? Or suddenly dead smite,</L>
<L>How long shall hee chastise mee, yet in vaine?</L>
<L>At length, <HI>O Lord,</HI> be mercifull againe:</L>
<L>Oh tarry not, <HI>Lord,</HI> tarry not too long,</L>
<L>But make my resolution firme and strong.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oh loathsomenesse, deceitfulnesse of sin,</L>
<L>Sweetnesse, and bitternesse wee find therein;</L>
<L>Beginnings, fawnings, growing, terrour, smart,</L>
<L><HI>Faiths</HI> weakenesse; <HI>Satans</HI> enuy, <HI>Mans</HI> false heart:</L>
<L>When shall I now these? Oh that I could know</L>
<L>Them better, Lord! by farre than yet I doe:</L>
<L>Yet wish (though much asham'd thus to be tainted)</L>
<L>I were not as I am with them acquainted.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>What shall I doe? Goe on! Nay, God defend!</L>
<L>Shall I retire? Stand idle? Not amend?</L>
<L>Shall I despaire? Why so? Haue my sins quite</L>
<L>Dride vp Gods mercies which are infinite?</L>
<L>Such thing to thinke, were cursed Blasphemy,</L>
<L>Who succours all that are in misery:</L>
<L>Will not God heare what I in <HI>Faith</HI> desire?</L>
<L>Humbled with Griefe? Then make I him a Lier.</L>
<L>Shall I presume yet longer? Ah I haue</L>
<L>Presum'd too much: Oh let mee mercy craue,</L>
<L>By true Repentance, and abundant teares;</L>
<L>What is thy heart so harden'd, as it feares</L>
<L>It neuer can be mollify'd againe?</L>
<L>Then Gods Omnipotence thou dost restraine:</L>
<L>What? Hath this thing without God come to passe?</L>
<L>Hath <HI>Satan</HI> got the Victory? Alas!</L>
<L>Is not th'Almightie far nore strong than hee?</L>
<L>Hath not my Lord, <HI>Christ Iesus</HI> dy'd for mee?</L>
<L>Hath God ere lov'd thee? Sure hee once me lov'd,</L>
<L>For then I it by good experience prov'd;</L>
<L>Then Loues he still, for where he doth begin</L>
<L>Hee loues for euer, and his gifts haue bin</L>
<L>Without Repentance: hee for mee destry'd</L>
<L>And vanquisht Death, Sin, Satan when he dy'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="123" REF="67"/>
O Lord encrease my faith, why should not I</L>
<L>Beleeue in him, obey him willingly?</L>
<L>How faine would I beleeue, and him obay;</L>
<L>How fame would I repent, amend, and pray:</L>
<L>I cannot then conclude, nor will, nor dare,</L>
<L>That I am damn'd, for these desires sure are</L>
<L>The motions of Gods Spirit in mee indeed;</L>
<L>Who neither smoaking flax, nor bruised reed</L>
<L>Will quench, or breake, But all will satisfie</L>
<L>Who thirst and hunger after equitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Blist euer be his name who hath begun,</L>
<L>To make me Conqueror through Christ his Sonne.</L>
<L>By his assistance gracious, then I Vow</L>
<L>To serue God better then I haue, till now,</L>
<L>On his behests more carefully attend,</L>
<L>Thy Grace mee strengthen, as a sheild defend.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Satan auoid, thou hast in mee no part,</L>
<L>From the beginning thou a Liar art;</L>
<L>Before and after mine, in <HI>Adams</HI> fall,</L>
<L>Thou to deceiue mee practisest in all:</L>
<L>But God is true, iust, mercifull to mee</L>
<L><HI>In Iesus Christ his blessed Sonne</HI> and <HI>hee,</HI></L>
<L>For honour of his Name and Maiesty,</L>
<L>Will doe away all mine iniquitie:</L>
<L>So as the siftings here of <HI>Satan</HI> shall</L>
<L>Not turne to my destruction; But they all</L>
<L>Gods Grace in mee shall further magnifie</L>
<L>And bind mee to him more assuredly;</L>
<L>More hee forgiues, the greater is his grace,</L>
<L>Him faster we with Loue in Christ imbrace.</L>
<L>Henceforth my soule remember well, what gaine</L>
<L>Thou reaped hast, and oft maist reape againe,</L>
<L>By that whereof thou iustly art ashamed,</L>
<L>For which thy Name and Conscience now is blamed.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Restore me to the Ioy of thy Saluation,</L>
<L>Which better is then ioyes continuation;</L>
<L>For by the want, the worth discerne we may,</L>
<L>And be stirr'd vp more earnestly to pray.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</GROUP>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

