{
    "May 22, 1623": [
        {
            "text": "10 RECORDS OF THE VIRGINIA COMPANY\n\nIV. The Records of the Company under the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization of the company—Membership, meetings, officers. Methods of procedure—General usage and elections, Rewards. Record books provided for by the company.\n\nThe extant records—The court book. History of the contemporary copy. Description of the lectionary in the Library of Congress. System of keeping the court book. Contents of the court book. \n\nThe extant supplementary records - Documents giving an outline of the activity of the company. Documents revealing the movements for trade and industry. Documents which concern the relation with the colony. Records of the colony. Documents which concern the development of factions and the recall of the charter. Documents which record the relations between the company and the Crown. \n\nConclusion—Value of the Virginia Records. Understanding of the organization and activity of the company. Value in understanding problems of state and of proprietary colonies.\n\nV. The Fate of the Original Records of the Company: Events leading up to the confiscation of the records by the Privy Council. The confiscation of the records, May 22, 1623: In charge of the clerk of the Privy Council, May 22-November 1, 1623. In charge of commissioners. Theories as to the fate of the records. Retention by the Privy Council for the successive commissions of 1625, 1631, and 1634. Dissipation among the members of the successive commissions. Private collections which have been searched in vain for these records. Destruction of the records.\n\nBIBLIOGRAPHICAL LIST OF THE RECORDS OF THE COMPANY.\n\nTABLE OF EXPLANATIONS\n\nTHE COURT BOOK, VOLUME I. \n\nApril 28, 1619, To May 8, 1622.\n\nIllustrations\n\nI. Certification or Volume I of the Original MS. \nII. Writing of Thomas Coutert (?). Being page 54 of Volume I of the original MS. \nIII. Writing of the First Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED) with John Ferrar’s Notes. A record of the Summer Islands’ Courts, from the Ferrar Papers. \nIV. Writing of the Third Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED). Being page 214 of Volume I of the original MS. \n\nPage 74 75 78 87 103 107 108 115 119 207 215 Front. 280 344 464",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "10",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "The Records of the Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Library of Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22-November 1, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1625, 1631",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1634",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "VOLUME I.",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 8, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Illustrations\n\nI. Certification",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Coutert",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "54",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the First Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Ferrar’s Notes",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Summer Islands’ Courts",
                    "label": "EVENT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Third Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "214",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "74",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "87",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "108",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "215",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "280",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "November 1, 1623": [
        {
            "text": "10 RECORDS OF THE VIRGINIA COMPANY\n\nIV. The Records of the Company under the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization of the company—Membership, meetings, officers. Methods of procedure—General usage and elections, Rewards. Record books provided for by the company.\n\nThe extant records—The court book. History of the contemporary copy. Description of the lectionary in the Library of Congress. System of keeping the court book. Contents of the court book. \n\nThe extant supplementary records - Documents giving an outline of the activity of the company. Documents revealing the movements for trade and industry. Documents which concern the relation with the colony. Records of the colony. Documents which concern the development of factions and the recall of the charter. Documents which record the relations between the company and the Crown. \n\nConclusion—Value of the Virginia Records. Understanding of the organization and activity of the company. Value in understanding problems of state and of proprietary colonies.\n\nV. The Fate of the Original Records of the Company: Events leading up to the confiscation of the records by the Privy Council. The confiscation of the records, May 22, 1623: In charge of the clerk of the Privy Council, May 22-November 1, 1623. In charge of commissioners. Theories as to the fate of the records. Retention by the Privy Council for the successive commissions of 1625, 1631, and 1634. Dissipation among the members of the successive commissions. Private collections which have been searched in vain for these records. Destruction of the records.\n\nBIBLIOGRAPHICAL LIST OF THE RECORDS OF THE COMPANY.\n\nTABLE OF EXPLANATIONS\n\nTHE COURT BOOK, VOLUME I. \n\nApril 28, 1619, To May 8, 1622.\n\nIllustrations\n\nI. Certification or Volume I of the Original MS. \nII. Writing of Thomas Coutert (?). Being page 54 of Volume I of the original MS. \nIII. Writing of the First Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED) with John Ferrar’s Notes. A record of the Summer Islands’ Courts, from the Ferrar Papers. \nIV. Writing of the Third Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED). Being page 214 of Volume I of the original MS. \n\nPage 74 75 78 87 103 107 108 115 119 207 215 Front. 280 344 464",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "10",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "The Records of the Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Library of Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22-November 1, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1625, 1631",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1634",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "VOLUME I.",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 8, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Illustrations\n\nI. Certification",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Coutert",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "54",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the First Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Ferrar’s Notes",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Summer Islands’ Courts",
                    "label": "EVENT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Third Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "214",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "74",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "87",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "108",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "215",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "280",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "April 28, 1619": [
        {
            "text": "10 RECORDS OF THE VIRGINIA COMPANY\n\nIV. The Records of the Company under the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization of the company—Membership, meetings, officers. Methods of procedure—General usage and elections, Rewards. Record books provided for by the company.\n\nThe extant records—The court book. History of the contemporary copy. Description of the lectionary in the Library of Congress. System of keeping the court book. Contents of the court book. \n\nThe extant supplementary records - Documents giving an outline of the activity of the company. Documents revealing the movements for trade and industry. Documents which concern the relation with the colony. Records of the colony. Documents which concern the development of factions and the recall of the charter. Documents which record the relations between the company and the Crown. \n\nConclusion—Value of the Virginia Records. Understanding of the organization and activity of the company. Value in understanding problems of state and of proprietary colonies.\n\nV. The Fate of the Original Records of the Company: Events leading up to the confiscation of the records by the Privy Council. The confiscation of the records, May 22, 1623: In charge of the clerk of the Privy Council, May 22-November 1, 1623. In charge of commissioners. Theories as to the fate of the records. Retention by the Privy Council for the successive commissions of 1625, 1631, and 1634. Dissipation among the members of the successive commissions. Private collections which have been searched in vain for these records. Destruction of the records.\n\nBIBLIOGRAPHICAL LIST OF THE RECORDS OF THE COMPANY.\n\nTABLE OF EXPLANATIONS\n\nTHE COURT BOOK, VOLUME I. \n\nApril 28, 1619, To May 8, 1622.\n\nIllustrations\n\nI. Certification or Volume I of the Original MS. \nII. Writing of Thomas Coutert (?). Being page 54 of Volume I of the original MS. \nIII. Writing of the First Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED) with John Ferrar’s Notes. A record of the Summer Islands’ Courts, from the Ferrar Papers. \nIV. Writing of the Third Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED). Being page 214 of Volume I of the original MS. \n\nPage 74 75 78 87 103 107 108 115 119 207 215 Front. 280 344 464",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "10",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "The Records of the Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Library of Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22-November 1, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1625, 1631",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1634",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "VOLUME I.",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 8, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Illustrations\n\nI. Certification",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Coutert",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "54",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the First Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Ferrar’s Notes",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Summer Islands’ Courts",
                    "label": "EVENT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Third Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "214",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "74",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "87",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "108",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "215",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "280",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "text": "UNDER SIR THOMAS SMYTHE 25 pelled against its will to submit to the treatment of its plantation as a penal colony by James I in his spasmodic efforts to develop a policy which should save England from an overpopulation of vagabonds.* With the exception of these unimportant relations with the Crown, the company seems to have conducted its business independently of royal aid or interference during the first decade of its existence as a corporate body. \n\nII.—THE COURT BOOK It is therefore in the court book of the company and in its instructions, correspondence, and other records suggested under the preceding classifications II and III, that its activity and methods must be found. That court books were kept under the administration of Sir Thomas Smythe is known from the receipt in the Ferrar papers, already referred to. The first book extended from January 2, 1606, to February 14, 1615, and with it were “other perticuler writings belonging to the company.” The second included the period between January 31, 1615, and July 28, 1619. What these books contained can only be surmised from the scope of the two later volumes, dated April 28, 1619, to May 22, 1622, and May 20, 1622, to April 2, 1623, the contemporary copies of which are now extant and in the Library of Congress, at Washington. The contents of the “other perticuler writings,” none of which are now known to be extant, are suggested by a memorandum of Sir Nathaniel Rich in a document among the Manchester papers. In attempting to prove the good done during Sir Thomas Smythe’s administration Rich cites certain records as authority. The first one mentioned was a “booke of perticulers” containing the “Public workes: done in Sr. T. Smithes tyme,” and showing “the plenty of Armes &c left in Sr. Th. Smithes tyme”; the second was a “particular already delivered to the Com.” in which appeared the “Staple Commodities raysed in Sr. T. Smithes tyme”; while the third formed a “collect of the publick workes made by Sr. Sa. Argall when he commenced” and was entitled “The particulars of the Boates.” Rich mentions two documents contained in this volume. He states “There is a series of 14 orders of the Privy Council for the transportation of prisoners to Virginia in the years 1617 and 1618 not hitherto noted. List of Records, pp. 121-131, Nos. 4, 41, 65, 90. The transportation thus effected is mentioned by Miss E. M. Leonard, The Early History of the English Poor Relief, pp. 229-230, n. >This receipt covered these four volumes, “the other perticuler writings belonging to the company,” and two volumes of the court book of the Somers Islands Company, December 3, 1613, to January 24, 1620, and February 7, 1620, to February 19, 1622. However, the second volume of the court book, which is now in the Library of Congress—the fourth volume here mentioned—was continued until June 19, 1624, after the return of the records to the company.",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "James",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "England",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the first decade",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Smythe",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Ferrar",
                    "label": "NORP"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "January 2, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "February 14, 1615",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the period",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1615",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "July 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 20, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 2, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Washington",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Nathaniel Rich",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Manchester",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Smythe’s",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Rich",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Sr",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "T. Smithes",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Armes &c",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Sr",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Com",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Staple Commodities",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "T. Smithes",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "third",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Boates",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "14",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the years 1617 and",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1618",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "List of Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "121",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Nos",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "4",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "41",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "65",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "90",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Miss E. M. Leonard",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "The Early History of the English Poor Relief",
                    "label": "WORK_OF_ART"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "229-230",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "four",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Somers Islands Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "December 3, 1613",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "January 24, 1620",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "February 7, 1620",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "February 19, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "fourth",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "June 19, 1624",
                    "label": "DATE"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "May 8, 1622": [
        {
            "text": "10 RECORDS OF THE VIRGINIA COMPANY\n\nIV. The Records of the Company under the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization of the company—Membership, meetings, officers. Methods of procedure—General usage and elections, Rewards. Record books provided for by the company.\n\nThe extant records—The court book. History of the contemporary copy. Description of the lectionary in the Library of Congress. System of keeping the court book. Contents of the court book. \n\nThe extant supplementary records - Documents giving an outline of the activity of the company. Documents revealing the movements for trade and industry. Documents which concern the relation with the colony. Records of the colony. Documents which concern the development of factions and the recall of the charter. Documents which record the relations between the company and the Crown. \n\nConclusion—Value of the Virginia Records. Understanding of the organization and activity of the company. Value in understanding problems of state and of proprietary colonies.\n\nV. The Fate of the Original Records of the Company: Events leading up to the confiscation of the records by the Privy Council. The confiscation of the records, May 22, 1623: In charge of the clerk of the Privy Council, May 22-November 1, 1623. In charge of commissioners. Theories as to the fate of the records. Retention by the Privy Council for the successive commissions of 1625, 1631, and 1634. Dissipation among the members of the successive commissions. Private collections which have been searched in vain for these records. Destruction of the records.\n\nBIBLIOGRAPHICAL LIST OF THE RECORDS OF THE COMPANY.\n\nTABLE OF EXPLANATIONS\n\nTHE COURT BOOK, VOLUME I. \n\nApril 28, 1619, To May 8, 1622.\n\nIllustrations\n\nI. Certification or Volume I of the Original MS. \nII. Writing of Thomas Coutert (?). Being page 54 of Volume I of the original MS. \nIII. Writing of the First Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED) with John Ferrar’s Notes. A record of the Summer Islands’ Courts, from the Ferrar Papers. \nIV. Writing of the Third Copyist (NOT IDENTIFIED). Being page 214 of Volume I of the original MS. \n\nPage 74 75 78 87 103 107 108 115 119 207 215 Front. 280 344 464",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "10",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "The Records of the Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Sandys-Southampton Administration: Organization",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Library of Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22-November 1, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1625, 1631",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1634",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "VOLUME I.",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 8, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Illustrations\n\nI. Certification",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Coutert",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "54",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the First Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Ferrar’s Notes",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Summer Islands’ Courts",
                    "label": "EVENT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Third Copyist",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "214",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MS",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "74",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "87",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "108",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "215",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "280",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "October 30, 1605": [
        {
            "text": "The Records of the Company under Sir Thomas Smith\n\nTHE ORGANIZATION OF THE COMPANY AS IN 1606\n\nIn the year preceding the grant of a charter to the Virginia Company there had been movements along two lines for establishing plantations in Virginia, one by private investment and the other by royal patronage. Examples of the private interests are the enterprise of the Earl of Southampton in 1605 and that of Lord Zouch as set forth in his contract with Captain George Waymouth of October 30, 1605. In this Lord Zouch agreed to secure and provide two ships and 200 men of “arts suitable for a colony,” and to pay £100 to Captain Waymouth for the transportation of the same. The interesting feature is the agreement, suggestive of feudal relations, that Lord Zouch should be the first officer and have the first choice of land, while Captain Waymouth as second officer should have second choice of land, which he was to hold from the former as lord paramount for himself, his heirs and assigns. At the same time Sir John Popham was busily engaged in the attempt to form royal colonies by obtaining charters from the Crown, whereby the territory from 34° to 45° north latitude should be taken under the protection of the King, and private settlements should thus be excluded. The plan which obtained followed neither course, though it was bound to result in a modification of Popham’s scheme. The motives of the grantees and the arguments which induced the King in 1606 to abandon the policy of Elizabeth and to give royal patronage to the undertaking, and even to assume royal control, are set forth in a petition presented to Parliament in 1606, entitled “Reasons for raising a publique stocke to be imploied in the discovering of such countries as may be found most convenient.” It is evident, however, that the unknown plan of investment in the adventure of 1606 is not here suggested, since there was no intimation of financial support by the King. The stock was apparently to be raised by a tax “Upon the moderate gaines of those that contrary to lawe abuse the poore,” and was not in any way to be “raised upon the sweat of the poore or the industrie of the poore.”",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Smith",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the year",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "one",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Earl of Southampton",
                    "label": "FAC"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1605",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "George Waymouth",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "October 30, 1605",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "200",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "100",
                    "label": "MONEY"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Waymouth",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Zouch",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Waymouth",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Popham",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "34",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "45",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Popham",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Elizabeth",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Parliament",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "November 20, 1606": [
        {
            "text": "18 INTRODUCTION  \nhusbandmen, Artificer, or tradesman,” but in such a way that nothing should be demanded from any man without presente assurance of gaine and hope of future profit * * * but in such sorte that the payer shall for every 2* paied gaine 4*. To the Kingdom and to the Crown were to redound the greatest gain. Ten thousand pounds a year were to be added to His Majesty’s receipts by an increase of many thousand pounds in the imposts and customs; and furthermore it “would savour too much of affectation of a popular State to levie monies without imparting some convenient portion to his Majestie.” But the value to shipping was emphasized perhaps more vigorously as developing a defence to the island, as furnishing a source for the necessities for ships—cordage, pitch, tar, and resin—and as protecting the shipping from decay. The desirability of a revival of the declining export trade, as well as that of establishing the importation of necessities from a part of the dominions, though distant, was urged, together with the importance of strengthening by settlement those countries already acquired by discovery. That such undertakings by private enterprise had been failures; that it was more honorable for the State to back an exploitation by public consent than by private monopoly; that public colonies were bound to be more obedient and industrious because of the greater confidence in the character of the control, were all reasons which had long before been set forth whereby to gain the support of the Crown.  \nCHARTER OF 1606.  \nThe royal aid as finally obtained for a colonial enterprise came in a somewhat different form. The letters patent to Sir Thomas Gates and others for plantations to be made in Virginia show that the investment was made solely by individuals, and that the joint stock was not public, although in the regulation of affairs in the colony the body of undertakers was to have little influence, even as far as its commercial interests in the plantation were concerned. The business management was left to the joint stock companies, and the magazine was controlled by a treasurer or cape merchant and by two clerks elected by the President and Council in the Colony. In fact, the only activity of the adventurers, so far as it is revealed in the extant documents, consisted in the choice in London of one or more groups of agents, called “companies,” to manage the goods sent out and received and to look after the profits. The undertakers were to have all lands with their resources.  \na For a reprint of the letters patent, see Brown, Genesis, I, 52-62, or Poore’s Constitutions.  \nb Articles, Instructions and Orders for the government of the Colonies, November 20, 1606. Reprinted in Brown, Genesis, I, 64-75, from a manuscript record book in the register’s office of Virginia. There is a manuscript copy in the Library of Congress, in the Virginia Miscellaneous Records, 1606-1692, pp. 26-33.",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "18",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Artificer",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "2",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "4",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Kingdom",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Ten thousand pounds",
                    "label": "MONEY"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "State",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Majestie",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "State",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Gates",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Colony",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "London",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "one",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Brown",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Genesis",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "52-62",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Poore’s Constitutions",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Articles, Instructions and Orders",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Colonies",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "November 20, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Genesis",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "64-75",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Library of Congress",
                    "label": "WORK_OF_ART"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Miscellaneous Records",
                    "label": "FAC"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606-1692",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "26-33",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "text": "THE COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS, 1616-1624  \n2. Fundamental orders, charters, ordinances, and instructions by the company in London and laws of the assembly in Virginia, pp. 5-21. Partly holographs as above. No. A 42. “The other side:” 1. (a) Letters from the colony to the King or to the company between 1621 and 1625. An unknown holograph. (b) Letters from the company to the colony between 1621 and August 6, 1623. Holographs of Edward Sharpless. 2. Instructions, commissions, proclamations, orders, warrants, and letters of the governor and captain-general of Virginia and of the assembly, pp. 36-53. Partly the holograph of Edward Sharpless and partly perhaps of Christopher Davison, the secretary of the colony from November, 1621, until his death in the winter of 1623/4. 4. Petitions to the governor and council in Virginia, pp. 58-63. Holographs as of the preceding. 5. A miscellaneous collection of letters between the Privy Council and the Commissioners for Virginia on the one hand and the governor and council in Virginia on the other, in 1625, pp. 68-70; a letter from the Virginia Company of London in 1626, p. 71, and a census of 1624, pp. 71-75. Unknown holographs similar to those in the first part of this end of the volume. The first part of the volume thus opens with the letters of the Privy Council to the colony on April 28, 1623, when the King first began the action looking toward the dissolution of the company, and with the first direct correspondence with the officers of the colony. The writing and the dates place the documents as consecutive through the entry of the acts of the assembly, March 5, 1623/4, when the assembly seems to have ceased. After that page, copies of scattered documents appear in a different writing, commencing on the back of the last assembly record. These are largely fundamental or constitutional, including the instructions of November 20, 1606, the charter of 1606, the order of 1607 enlarging the council, and the oaths administered to officials of the colony of the same period. The other part of the volume opens with the correspondence between the colony and the home government. After a hiatus of fifteen pages the documents of the governor and assembly begin as indicated under the second division above. The writing is that of Edward Sharpless and Christopher Davison, and remains the same throughout the petitions of the next group. The last group of miscellaneous documents agrees in subject with the  \nThis volume is cited in the List of Records, as “MSS. Records of the Virginia Company of London, Vol. III, pt. i.” Christopher Davison was appointed at a quarter court, June 23, 1621. His commission was sealed November 28, 1621. Cited in the List of Records as “MSS. Records of the Virginia Company, Vol. III, pt. ii.” 16455—vo_ 1—06——4",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "1616-1624",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "2",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "London",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "5-21",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "42",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "between 1621 and 1625",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "between 1621 and August 6, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Edward Sharpless",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "2",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "36-53",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Edward Sharpless",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Christopher Davison",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "November, 1621",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the winter",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1623/4",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "4",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "58-63",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "5.",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1625",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "68-70",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Company of London",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1626",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "71",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1624",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "71-75",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 28, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "March 5",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "November 20, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1607",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "fifteen",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Edward Sharpless",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Christopher Davison",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the List of Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MSS",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Company of London",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Christopher Davison",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "quarter",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "June 23, 1621",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "November 28, 1621",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the List of Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "MSS",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Virginia Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "16455",
                    "label": "DATE"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "December 10, 1606": [
        {
            "text": "UNDER SIR THOMAS SMYTHH 19 which lay within 50 miles of the plantation in any direction, together with the islands within 100 miles of the coast, and were privileged to inhabit and fortifie the same according as the council for Virginia should direct. The right freely to transport subjects was granted the investors, while they were permitted customs free for seven years to export armor, provisions, and all necessities of life for the colonists. They could impose upon any subjects of the Crown, who were not adventurers, trafficking in those regions, a tax of 24 per cent of the articles concerned, and upon foreigners twice that amount, and thus maintain a control of the trade for twenty-one years. But the government of the colonies and of the territory of Virginia was reserved to the Crown through the council of thirteen for Virginia, which was to be appointed by the King and to reside in England. Instructions were issued and signed by the royal hand, which outlined the form of administering affairs in the settlement and created a council of thirteen in the colony. They conferred upon it the right to coin money and to pass ordinances which should be valid till altered by the Crown, provided that they should be consonant with the laws of England. This council in Virginia was to choose its own president for one year. It could remove him or any member for just cause and fill the vacancies. All civil causes and all lesser criminal cases were to be decided by the president and council, the former having two votes in case of a tie. Cases of manslaughter and the more heinous crimes were to be tried before a jury and were punishable with death. To the president and council was reserved the right of pardon. The council in England nominated to the Crown the persons to whom lands were to be granted by the King. It had, in fact, the supervision of affairs, appointed the first council in Virginia, issued orders for the conduct of the first expedition under Captain Newport, and provided a paper of advice as to the establishment of a fort and of a town. It is in this latter document that the first indication of the real motive of the undertaking is found. The orders laid down were to “make choice” of the river “which bendeth most toward the North-West, for that way you shall soonest find the other sea,” while the choice of a healthy location, wise intercourse with the natives, and the fortification and preparation of a single settlement were emphasized. The chief objects, however, were to plant in a place. \n\nPrinted in full, Brown, Genesis, I, 64-75. See Certain Orders and Directions, December 10, 1606. Manuscript in the Library of Congress, Virginia Miscellaneous Records, 1606-1692, pp. 19-23. Reprinted in Brown, Genesis, I, 75-79. See Instructions by way of Advice, December, 1606. Manuscript in the Library of Congress, Virginia Miscellaneous Records, 1606-1692, pp. 14-17. Reprinted in Brown, Genesis, I, 79-85.",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "SIR",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "THOMAS",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "19",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "50 miles",
                    "label": "QUANTITY"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "100 miles",
                    "label": "QUANTITY"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "seven years",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "24 per cent",
                    "label": "MONEY"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "twenty-one years",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the council of thirteen",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "England",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "thirteen",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "England",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "one year",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "England",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the North-West",
                    "label": "LOC"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Brown",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Genesis",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "64-75",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Certain Orders",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "December 10, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia Miscellaneous Records",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606-1692",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "19-23",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Genesis",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "75-79",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Advice",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "December, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia Miscellaneous Records",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606-1692",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "14-17",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Genesis",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "79-85",
                    "label": "DATE"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "February 18, 1609": [
        {
            "text": "20 INTRODUCTION which should be fitted to receive the trade of all the countries about, to discover minerals, and to find the passage to the western sea. The loss of the records, both of the council and of the \"companies\" for trade, covering this period, leaves, as the only source of information, both for affairs in England and in Virginia, the narratives of the early settlers. Of these the most important are the reports of Captain Newport, and the relations of John Smith, of Edward Maria Wingfield, and of George Percy.* The council had dispatched three expeditions, all under Captain Newport; one in December, 1606, in three ships with 120 emigrants; another in October, 1607, with two vessels and about the same number of passengers; and a third in August of 1608 with about 70 emigrants. The reports of Newport, Percy, Wingfield, and Smith encouraged the managers of the enterprise to continue their efforts, but proved that a change in object as well as in policy would be necessary. From Newport came descriptions of the fruitful- ness of the soil, of the quantities of fish and of timber, and of clay for making brick, and enumerations of the possible exports, comprising sturgeon, clapboard, wainscot, saxafrage, tobacco, dyes, furs, pitch, resin, turpentine, oils, wines, wood and soap ashes, iron, copper, pearls; but the reports as to the mines were vague. He declared that the country was rich in gold and copper, and took home with him earth to be assayed, while Smith, in A True Relation, states that he had been left to dig a rock which Captain Newport thought was a mine, but no mention of results is made. The full description of the country by Newport and also by Captain John Smith gave the council a clear idea of its geography, as is indicated by the instructions to Sir Thomas Gates in 1609. But the expedition, which penetrated to a distance of 160 miles up the river, brought the explorers to hostile tribes and left the council still uncertain, though hopeful of the discovery of a passage to the south sea. Furthermore, Captain Newport positively stated that there could be no commerce with the Indians, and all evidence shows that the natives were to be a resource for the necessities of life rather than for the exchange of lucrative objects of trade. Hence it is that the broadside which was issued by the company in 1609, as an incident of its *See John Smith, A True Relation, 1608, reprinted in Arber, Works of John Smith, 1884; Discourse of Virginia, by Edward Maria Wingfield, printed in the Archaeologia Americana, IV, 77-103; Observations gathered out of a Discourse of the Plantation in Virginia 1606, by George Percy, printed in Brown, Genesis, I, 152-168; and the following documents probably written by Captain Archer: A Relation of the Discovery of Our River, from James Forte into the maine: by Capt. Christopher Newport, 1607, printed in Archaeologia Americana, IV, 40-58; The Description of the now-discovered river and country of Virginia, printed in the Archaeologia Americana, IV, 59-62; A Brief Description of the People, printed in Archaeologia Americana, IV, 63-65. b Nova Britannia, printed February 18, 1609. This document is reprinted in Force’s Tracts, I, No. 6.",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "20",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "England",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Captain Newport",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Smith",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Edward Maria Wingfield",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "George Percy",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "three",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "one",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "December, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "three",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "120",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "October, 1607",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "a third",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "August of 1608",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "about 70",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Percy",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Wingfield",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Smith",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Smith",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "A True Relation",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Smith",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Gates",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1609",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "160 miles",
                    "label": "QUANTITY"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the south sea",
                    "label": "LOC"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Indians",
                    "label": "NORP"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1609",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Smith",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "A True Relation",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1608",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Arber",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Works",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "John Smith",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1884",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Edward Maria Wingfield",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Archaeologia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "IV",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "77",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "George Percy",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Brown",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Genesis",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "152",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Archer",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "James Forte",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Christopher Newport",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1607",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Archaeologia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Americana",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "IV",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "40-58",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Archaeologia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "IV",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "59",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "A Brief Description of the People",
                    "label": "WORK_OF_ART"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Archaeologia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Americana",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "IV",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "63-65",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Nova Britannia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "February 18, 1609",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "6",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "April 21, 1623": [
        {
            "text": "99 INTRODUCTION  \ncourt book, in which were kept the records of the acts of the council and perhaps of the companies for the administration of trade. This book, covering the period from the 28th of January, 1606, to the 14th of February, 1615, was in the possession of the company as late as 1623, but unfortunately no trace of the book has yet been discovered and even its existence has heretofore been unknown. Whatever may have been the source of control, the narrations of Captain Percy, Edward-Maria Wingfield, and Captain Newport indicate that the business of the company consisted chiefly in raising funds and equipping expeditions to be sent to Virginia under Captain Newport. This failure of the investment to bring in returns of gold and silver and of articles for trade, or to accomplish anything in the way of discovery of trade routes to the East Indies during the first three years, served to convince both King and undertakers that a change in method of control was essential. The document known as “Reasons against publishing the Kings title to Virginia. A justification for planting Virginia” seems to show an agitation among the investors arising from fear lest the desire to placate Spain, or religious considerations, might lead the Crown to abandon the scheme. The arguments there adduced may well explain the readiness of the King to surrender not only the commercial and territorial control but also full rights of government to the corporate body of the Virginia company, and thus to avoid any rupture with Spain. Certain it is that the desire for more direct authority and for securing larger investments were the motives of the petitioners in asking for a new charter. As a result of this movement the letters patent of 1609 were issued, transforming the undertakers into a body politic. In this case also the documents are especially characteristic of the organization. Whereas the Crown was formerly the source of all power, beginning with 1609 the council of the company, acting as a standing committee for the adventurers rather than in the name of the King, exercised the controlling authority. After the charter of 1612 had provided for more frequent meetings of the generality, the council was gradually superseded by special committees and the tendency arose to decide all matters of importance in the general quarter courts and to insist upon all communications being addressed to the company rather than to the council. The act of incorporation erected a commercial company and made it the overlord of a proprietary province. It at once strengthened its plantation as a center for traffic and established a system for joint management of land and trade to extend over a period of seven years.  \n“When the Privy Council demanded the records of the company, a receipt bearing the date April 21, 1623, was given to the secretary of the company for the ‘several court books.’ This document was discovered by the Editor among the Ferrar papers, Magdalene College, Cambridge, in December, 1903. See List of Records, p. 171, No. 470. This document was recently found by the Editor in the Bodleian Library. Jbid., p. 121, No. 1.",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "99",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the 28th of January, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the 14th of February, 1615",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Percy",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Edward-Maria Wingfield",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Captain Newport",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Newport",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the East Indies",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the first three years",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "King",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Kings",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Spain",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Spain",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1609",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1609",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the council of the company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1612",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the general quarter",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "seven years",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the date April 21, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Ferrar",
                    "label": "NORP"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Magdalene College",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Cambridge",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "December, 1903",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "171",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "470",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Bodleian",
                    "label": "NORP"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "121",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "January 2, 1606": [
        {
            "text": "UNDER SIR THOMAS SMYTHE 25 pelled against its will to submit to the treatment of its plantation as a penal colony by James I in his spasmodic efforts to develop a policy which should save England from an overpopulation of vagabonds.* With the exception of these unimportant relations with the Crown, the company seems to have conducted its business independently of royal aid or interference during the first decade of its existence as a corporate body. \n\nII.—THE COURT BOOK It is therefore in the court book of the company and in its instructions, correspondence, and other records suggested under the preceding classifications II and III, that its activity and methods must be found. That court books were kept under the administration of Sir Thomas Smythe is known from the receipt in the Ferrar papers, already referred to. The first book extended from January 2, 1606, to February 14, 1615, and with it were “other perticuler writings belonging to the company.” The second included the period between January 31, 1615, and July 28, 1619. What these books contained can only be surmised from the scope of the two later volumes, dated April 28, 1619, to May 22, 1622, and May 20, 1622, to April 2, 1623, the contemporary copies of which are now extant and in the Library of Congress, at Washington. The contents of the “other perticuler writings,” none of which are now known to be extant, are suggested by a memorandum of Sir Nathaniel Rich in a document among the Manchester papers. In attempting to prove the good done during Sir Thomas Smythe’s administration Rich cites certain records as authority. The first one mentioned was a “booke of perticulers” containing the “Public workes: done in Sr. T. Smithes tyme,” and showing “the plenty of Armes &c left in Sr. Th. Smithes tyme”; the second was a “particular already delivered to the Com.” in which appeared the “Staple Commodities raysed in Sr. T. Smithes tyme”; while the third formed a “collect of the publick workes made by Sr. Sa. Argall when he commenced” and was entitled “The particulars of the Boates.” Rich mentions two documents contained in this volume. He states “There is a series of 14 orders of the Privy Council for the transportation of prisoners to Virginia in the years 1617 and 1618 not hitherto noted. List of Records, pp. 121-131, Nos. 4, 41, 65, 90. The transportation thus effected is mentioned by Miss E. M. Leonard, The Early History of the English Poor Relief, pp. 229-230, n. >This receipt covered these four volumes, “the other perticuler writings belonging to the company,” and two volumes of the court book of the Somers Islands Company, December 3, 1613, to January 24, 1620, and February 7, 1620, to February 19, 1622. However, the second volume of the court book, which is now in the Library of Congress—the fourth volume here mentioned—was continued until June 19, 1624, after the return of the records to the company.",
            "entities": [
                {
                    "entity": "James",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "England",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Crown",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the first decade",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Smythe",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Ferrar",
                    "label": "NORP"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "January 2, 1606",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "February 14, 1615",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the period",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1615",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "July 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 28, 1619",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 22, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "May 20, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "April 2, 1623",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Washington",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Nathaniel Rich",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Manchester",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Thomas Smythe’s",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Rich",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "first",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Sr",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "T. Smithes",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Armes &c",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Sr",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Com",
                    "label": "PRODUCT"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Staple Commodities",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "T. Smithes",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "third",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Boates",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "14",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Privy Council",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Virginia",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the years 1617 and",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "1618",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "List of Records",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "pp",
                    "label": "GPE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "121",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Nos",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "4",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "41",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "65",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "90",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Miss E. M. Leonard",
                    "label": "PERSON"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "The Early History of the English Poor Relief",
                    "label": "WORK_OF_ART"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "229-230",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "four",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "two",
                    "label": "CARDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "the Somers Islands Company",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "December 3, 1613",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "January 24, 1620",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "February 7, 1620",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "February 19, 1622",
                    "label": "DATE"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "second",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "Congress",
                    "label": "ORG"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "fourth",
                    "label": "ORDINAL"
                },
                {
                    "entity": "June 19, 1624",
                    "label": "DATE"
                }
            ]
        }
    ],
    "February 14, 1615": [
        {
